<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>a necessitous blog</title>
<link>https://erauchway.github.io/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://erauchway.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>A blog full of pedantry about the era of the Roosevelt administration, 1933--1945</description>
<generator>quarto-1.2.269</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>A red herring in the fog of war</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_5_confusion/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_4_facts_2/">Hasselwander noted that</a> historians will sometimes say or suggest that Lt. Fraatz, commander of U 652, might have mistaken <em>Greer</em> for one of the Wickes-class destroyers the US traded to Britain in exchange for Western-hemisphere bases in the deal of September 1940, and thus a legitimate target; Hasselwander specifically cites Kurt Assman to this effect (<em>Nur Assmann erklärt, daß der Kommandant geglaubt habe, sein Verfolger sei einer der fünfzig amerikanischen Zerstörer, welche die Vereinigten Staaten ab September 1940 Großbritannienüberlassen hatten.</em>).<span class="citation" data-cites="hasselwanderUSZerstorerGreerUnd1962"><sup>1</sup></span> I’ll have more to say about destroyers-for-bases another time; for now, I’ll give this post over to a discussion of this possibility of mistaken identity.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_5_confusion/NH67637.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">The USS <em>Greer</em> sometime during the war; image mirrored for comparison. US Naval History and Heritage Command.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_5_confusion/large_000000.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">HMS <em>Newmarket,</em> one of the US destroyers of the same class as <em>Greer</em> traded to Britain in 1940. IWM.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>You can see above a photograph of the <em>Greer</em> and a photograph of one of her sister ships traded to Britain, which became HMS <em>Newmarket.</em> The question of whether <em>Greer</em> might have looked like one of these newly British ships was raised within a couple weeks of the incident, and <em>Time</em> magazine took it up, explaining that the <em>Greer</em> had been modified and therefore looked different from other, once-similar destroyers. It’s true, I think, that you can see this in these photos if you look: the forward stack has been changed, with a “spark screen” added; the stacks have been lowered, too. The guns are different. And of course, so is the livery. <a href="https://content.time.com/time/subscriber/article/0,33009,766028,00.html">Moreover, <em>Time</em> noted, the <em>Greer</em> was sailing on its own, as British destroyers did not.</a> It was, as we have seen, broad daylight—that is why Fraatz did not surface.</p>
<p>Still, I would concede that the two ships look quite similar and if I were looking through a U-boat periscope I might well not be able to tell the difference. Hasselwander notes further that there is no indication Fraatz thought he was looking at a British destroyer. (<em>Die verfügbaren Teile des Logbuchs von U652 deuten jedoch darauf hin, daß die Ähnlichkeit von Greer mit den England überlassenen Zerstörern Fraatz nicht aufgefallen ist.</em>)<span class="citation" data-cites="hasselwanderUSZerstorerGreerUnd1962"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
<p>Moreover, to repeat again what we noted in <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_4_facts_2/">the earlier post,</a> Fraatz <em>did</em> notice that the <em>Greer</em> was not <em>acting</em> like a British destroyer, given its “hesitating behavior” (<em>„zögernde Verhalten,“</em> Hasselwander is quoting Fraatz). Hasselwander goes on to suggest that Fraatz didn’t mean the torpedoes to sink the ship, but rather intended them as a (momentarily successful) effort to throw the <em>Greer</em> off his trail (<em>Die geringe Entfernung, auf die U 652 seinen zweiten Torpedo schoß, und die anscheinend überstürzte Art, in der dies geschah, lassen vermuten, daß Fraatz seinen Angriff hauptsächlich als Ablenkungsmanöver gedacht hatte, um seinen Verfolger abzuschütteln. Tatsächlich gelang es ja U 652, bis 15.07 h weitere Horchkontakte zu vermeiden</em>).<span class="citation" data-cites="hasselwanderUSZerstorerGreerUnd1962"><sup>3</sup></span></p>
<p>We should not, it seems to me, throw out this suggestion absent evidence. But also, it is a bit of a red herring. Roosevelt’s argument about the appropriate US response to the incident did not hinge on the U-boat captain’s knowing that the <em>Greer</em> was a US ship.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Gerald E. Hasselwander, <span>“Der US-Zerstörer <span>‘Greer’</span> Und <span>‘U 652’</span>”</span> 59 (1962): 156.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Hasselwander, <span>“Zerstörer <span>‘Greer’</span>,”</span> 156.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Hasselwander, <span>“Zerstörer <span>‘Greer’</span>,”</span> 155–56.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Greer</category>
  <category>Destroyers-for-bases</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_5_confusion/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_5_confusion/NH67637.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Greer: just some more facts</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_4_facts_2/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Earlier I posted a bare-bones, <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_1/">“just-the-facts” narrative</a> of the <em>Greer</em> incident, from Samuel Eliot Morison’s account. Here are some more facts; as the Dude would say, <a href="https://tenor.com/view/new-shit-has-come-to-light-big-lebowski-reveal-gif-16492009">“new shit has come to light.”</a> Or rather, thanks to Inter-Library Loan, I received some new information that I’ve not seen cited in the standard accounts.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_4_facts_2/large_000000.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">An RAF Hudson off the shore of Dunkirk. IWM.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Morison says the British plane, an RAF Hudson, “dropped his depth charges more or less at random.” I did know that <em>Greer</em> was broadcasting the U-boat’s position, so that it wouldn’t have been all that random, but I hadn’t picked up on that in the account.</p>
<p>But there is also the question, often raised, of whether the U-boat commander saw the <em>Greer;</em> you usually read that we don’t know what he observed, or historians will impute behavior to him, as I quoted Waldo Heinrichs doing, saying the U-boat captain “must have regarded as hostile pursuit” the <em>Greer’s</em> continued following of the U-boat. Or consider Kenneth S. Davis’s account: “the harassed U-boat, its desperate commander probably believing the destroyer had made the depth-charge attack actually made by the British plane, suddenly fired a torpedo at the destroyer, then a second one, perhaps a third.”<span class="citation" data-cites="davisFDRWarPresident2000"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
<p>It did occur to me that someone might have sometime looked into the German records, and (again, thanks to ILL) I can now say the U-boat captain’s state of mind was not so clear as all that. Nor was the firing of the torpedo sudden.</p>
<p>The U-boat, U 652, under the command of Lieutenant Georg-Werner Fraatz, had been running on the surface, and then “dived after sighting an aircraft” (<em>und hatte dann nach Sichten eines Flugzeuges getaucht,</em>) according to Gerald E. Hasselwander, who was working with the war diaries (<em>Kriegstachebücher</em>) of U 652. So Fraatz, the U-boat captain, did know he was being pursued by an aircraft—although Hasselwander says that when the depth charges exploded, the crew believed they had come from the destroyer they could hear overhead (<em>glaubte seine Besatzung, daß der Zerstörer, den sie über sich hören konnten, der Angreifer sei</em>).<span class="citation" data-cites="hasselwanderUSZerstorerGreerUnd1962"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
<p>After the two hours’ pursuit without further attack, Fraatz was somewhat confused; he could not understand what he called the destroyer’s “hesitant behavior.” (<em>Der U-Bootkommandant konnte jedoch das „zögernde Verhalten” des Zerstörers nicht verstehen.</em>) So he came to periscope depth and had a look at it. He might even have surfaced, Hasselwander says, had not the weather been so good and the high visibility thus a risk to him—he could see, now, another plane above the <em>Greer.</em> At this point, he fired two torpedoes at the destroyer.</p>
<p>Hasselwander says we don’t really know why those two hours passed before Fraatz fired on the destroyer. Maybe he didn’t have a clean shot. But maybe also he had “concerns” (<em>Bedenken</em>)—about what, Hasselwander doesn’t say; but one possible concern would be that the destroyer was certainly not acting like a British destroyer, which meant that it might belong to a neutral power, possibly the United States.<span class="citation" data-cites="hasselwanderUSZerstorerGreerUnd1962"><sup>3</sup></span> Given what we know about <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_2_nazi/">the division in German thinking about a naval war against the United States at this time,</a> we might suppose that this same division was reflected in Fraatz’s mind.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Kenneth S. Davis, <em>FDR: The War President, 1940--1943</em> (New York: Random House, 2000), 277.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Gerald E. Hasselwander, <span>“Der US-Zerstörer <span>‘Greer’</span> Und <span>‘U 652’</span>”</span> 59 (1962): 153.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Hasselwander, <span>“Zerstörer <span>‘Greer’</span>,”</span> 153–54.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Greer</category>
  <category>convoys</category>
  <category>Nazi strategy</category>
  <category>US strategy</category>
  <category>UK strategy</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_4_facts_2/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_4_facts_2/large_000000.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Four Fears, Four Freedoms: US ideology</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/atlantic_ideology/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Admiral Stark’s <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_3_dog/">“Plan Dog” memo</a> sets as a basic aim the “preservation of the territorial, economic, and ideological integrity of the United States plus that of the remainder of the Western hemisphere.” Which for me raises a question Stark doesn’t address: what does he mean by “ideological integrity”? That question is difficult enough when applied to the United States; it’s even more knotty when applied to the rest of the Western Hemisphere. We can take up the question of the Good Neighbor Policy later; let’s look specifically at the United States. A couple months after the Plan Dog memo, Roosevelt would speak to Congress and outline the “four freedoms,” an ideological basis for US involvement in the war: freedom of speech, freedom of worship, freedom from want, and freedom from fear—everywhere in the world. I’ll talk more about that speech later, too; for this post I want to talk about the earliest public mention I know of those four basic rights, in <a href="http://www.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/_resources/images/pc/pc0101.pdf">a discussion between the Roosevelts and members of the American Youth Congress on June 5, 1940.</a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/atlantic_ideology/https:/tile.loc.gov/storage-services/service/pnp/hec/27700/27738v.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">William Hinckley of the American Youth Congress addresses the Dies (House UnAmerican Activities) Committee, November 30, 1939. Library of Congress.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The American Youth Congress (AYC) included a variety of organizations, among them the Boy Scouts and Girl Scouts, but it was widely supposed to have fallen under the influence of communists. It was also a favorite cause of Eleanor Roosevelt, who liked the idea of being in touch with the young people of the nation, which is why members of the AYC were in the state dining room of the White House on June 5, to talk to the president—and to prod him from his political left. One delegate after another asked him about the nation’s, and the administration’s, lackluster record on voting rights for Black citizens. They pressed him on the poll tax. They asked him whether the Allies were not in fact colonialist powers with at best a selective implementation of democracy. Roosevelt gave an honestly relativist answer, saying that whatever the Allies were fighting for, it was “a better form of democracy, certainly, than Germany is fighting for.”</p>
<p>After a while, one questioner gave him an opening to try something different. How, the president was asked, would he ensure that an Allied victory would produce a better outcome than it had in 1918?</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Let’s take this assumption that the world, the people of the world entrusted you to write the next peace. . . . How would America be effective in establishing democratic governments if that is the clue to future peace?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>For this question, Roosevelt sounded prepared.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>We have a pretty good idea of what we would seek. That is something. In other words, we have a program that is no secret. It is the elimination—I have put it that way on several occasions—it is the elimination of four fears.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He went on to explain these “four fears” as the worry people had that they might not be able to exercise their essential freedoms: freedom of religion, freedom of expression—and “the fear of arms” as well as, “the fear of not being able to have normal economic and social relations with other nations. . . . freedom of commerce and freedom of culture, because the two go hand in hand.”</p>
<p>Pressed on this amorphous last point—“Doesn’t it seem there should be a fifth item, that of giving people economic security in all countries?”—Roosevelt said, “Yes, that is the fourth point I am making.”</p>
<p>After the president left the room, the First Lady and Harry Hopkins answered more questions. In the course of this continued discussion, Eleanor Roosevelt said of the president’s positions on aid to the Allies,</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>A year and a half, two years ago, he said every single thing on defense that he said aloud today to individual members of Congress and gave the very same reasons. . . . Today, they are all running to him because the circumstances, the life of the world, have hit them in the face. . . . But they were not ready two years ago.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The president’s statement that he had used the “four fears” formulation “on several occasions,” together with Eleanor’s saying that he had been using these reasons for somewhere between eighteen months and two years, suggest—as did the president’s saying that his views were “no secret”—that he had somehow, to someone or several someones, mentioned ensuring these basic rights as the essential basis for US aid to the Allies. But as I say, this is the first public occasion of which I’m aware. And even here, as you can see, the formulation is not complete; the “freedom from want” was anything but clearly framed.</p>
<p>What you can also see is that Roosevelt, whether using this argument with “individual members of Congress” or young, evidently leftist Americans, was trying to provide an ideological answer to why the US should aid the Allies: to fight for a world in which essential human rights were globally guaranteed.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>US strategy</category>
  <category>US politics</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/atlantic_ideology/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://tile.loc.gov/storage-services/service/pnp/hec/27700/27738v.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The German threat: Plan Dog</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_3_dog/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>On November 12, 1940, shortly after Roosevelt’s re-election to a unique third term in the presidency, Chief of Naval Operations Harold Stark sent a memorandum to the Secretary of the Navy, Frank Knox, outlining the US military position. The document became known as “Plan Dog,” after the US-UK phonetic alphabet for “D” (Able, Baker, Charlie, Dog, Easy, Fox, etc.) because out of the options Stark considered, he recommended proceeding with the one he lettered “D”—a joint offensive with Britain against Germany in the Atlantic, in anticipation of a wider war.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_3_dog/https:/tile.loc.gov/storage-services/service/pnp/hec/47500/47500v.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Admiral Stark, in the light gray business suit, stands behind the president, who is decorating Admiral Yarnell for his recent comportment in China. Photo of August 28, 1939. Library of Congress.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p><a href="http://www.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/_resources/images/psf/psfa0048.pdf">The memorandum</a> runs 26 pages and covers a lot of ground. Here is a single paragraph, from page 19, where Stark gives a succinct summary of his argument for US concern about the German threat.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>It is a fundamental requirement of our military position that our homeland remain secure against successful attack. Directly concerned in this security is the safety of other parts of the Western Hemisphere. A very strong pillar of the defense structure of the Americans has, for many years, been the balance of power existing in Europe. The collapse of Great Britain or the destruction or surrender of the British Fleet will destroy this balance and will free European military power for possible encroachment in this hemisphere.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The security of the US depends on the security of the Americas; the security of the Americas depends on a balance of power in Europe; German defeat of Britain will end that balance and its destruction or acquisition of the British fleet would enable a German attack on the Americas and thus imperil the United States.</p>
<p><a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_2_nazi/">We know Hitler thought in similar, if reversed, terms,</a> planning a war on the United States once he had secured his European triumph, though he did not necessarily feel he needed to defeat Britain—merely the Soviet Union, which he expected to do swiftly.</p>
<p>Stark thus believed the first question was how best to preserve Britain from defeat. He rejected focusing on likely war with Japan, or strictly defensive options, and advocated his option D: a joint offensive with Britain in the Atlantic, while keeping a strong defensive posture in the Pacific. The US fleet should remain in the Pacific until war was “imminent.” Assistance to Britain would mean protecting shipping in the western Atlantic, and reinforcing British naval operations around the British Isles and down the coast of Africa, as well as in the Mediterranean.</p>
<p>The chief of naval operations further acknowledged that “purely naval assistance, would not, in my opinion, <em>assure</em> final victory for Great Britain,” and moreover that Britain lacked the manpower to win an infantry campaign on its own. “I believe that the United States, in addition to sending naval assistance, would also need to send large air and land forces to Europe or Africa, or both, and to participate strongly in this land offensive.”</p>
<p>Any other option, Stark believed, would end in British collapse—and thus a serious threat to US security.</p>
<p>The memorandum thus recommended joint Army-Navy plans and moreover, “secret staff talks on technical matters with the British military and naval authorities” to assure coordination of the impending war effort.</p>
<p>The Army accepted Stark’s memo with the addition that the United States should expect to supply substantial air support in a war alongside the British. The president authorized the staff conversations, and on December 2, 1940, Stark invited the British to come to Washington for joint planning.<span class="citation" data-cites="connWesternHemisphereFramework1960"><sup>1</sup></span></p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Stetson Conn and Byron Fairchild, <em>The Western Hemisphere: The Framework of Hemispheric Defense</em>, vol. 12, part 1, United States Army in World War II (Washington, D.C.: Office of the Chief of Military History, 1960), 92.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>convoys</category>
  <category>Greer</category>
  <category>US strategy</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_3_dog/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://tile.loc.gov/storage-services/service/pnp/hec/47500/47500v.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Greer: Nazi strategy</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_2_nazi/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The September 4, 1941, U-boat attack on the <em>Greer</em> was materially inconsequential, but symbolically vital, and to understand why, we have to think about this particular moment in the war. In this post we will look at this moment in Nazi strategy, just a couple months after the start of Operation Barbarossa, the German assault on the Soviet Union. Although the conclusion of David Stahel is pretty well established—that is to say, that by August the collapse of Barbarossa was already determined; that the failure to put resources into the construction of railroads and other logistical necessities spelled catastrophe—we should remember that even if to us, the tanks racing East look foolishly disconnected from the infantry that could secure their advances, at the time, they looked like the irresistible advance guard of yet another successful Blitzkrieg. As Stahel notes, the British Joint Intelligence Committee thought the Germans would win within six weeks; in the US, Secretary of War Stimson and General George Marshall believed it would take Germany one to three months to defeat the Soviet Union.<span class="citation" data-cites="stahelOpearationBarbarossaGermany2009"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_2_nazi/https:/media.iwm.org.uk/cantaloupe/iiif/2/295%7C%7C613%7C%7Clarge_000000.jpg/full/730,/0/default.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">A panzer, part of Army Group Centre, advancing into the East. Imperial War Museum.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>And the Nazi high command, Hitler in particular, thought the same. Victory in the East was certain and imminent, which meant that the German navy need only stay its hand briefly before launching war on the United States.</p>
<p>According to Holger Herwig, Hitler told Admiral Erich Raeder to plan for a fleet of ten “superbattleships” by 1944, for war on Britain, the United States, or both. The Ziel Plan, or Z-Plan, drafted in 1939, sketched out the development of this Navy and, Herwig notes, the plan was modified in 1940 specifically for war on the United States, when Hitler “took an active interest in selecting future Atlantic bases, preferring Iceland, the Azores, the Cape Verdes, and the Canaries”; this in the flush of victory after the fall of France and “with an eye to the future war with America,” as of October 29, 1940.<span class="citation" data-cites="herwigPoliticsFrustrationUnited1976"><sup>2</sup></span> Herwig tells us that Raeder and Hitler viewed this plan differently; Raeder thought of it as an alternative to the war with the USSR, while Hitler—who was ideologically committed to the acquisition of <em>lebensraum</em> in the East and the killing of the people currently living there—thought of it as a consequence to the war with the Soviet Union.<span class="citation" data-cites="herwigPoliticsFrustrationUnited1976"><sup>3</sup></span></p>
<p>Therefore Hitler instructed Raeder repeatedly to avoid any incident with the United States, if only for the time being. Herwig has Hitler saying so as early as May 1941. In June, the day before Barbarossa, Hitler told Raeder, “avoid <em>every</em> incident with the United States until ‘Barbarossa’ unfolded itself. After a few weeks the situation would be cleared up.” In July, with the US occupation of Iceland, Raeder and the naval staff requested “immediate armed assault on all USA ships within our publicly proclaimed war zone.” Hitler did continue planning operations in Gibraltar and Northwest Africa to establish an “offensive stance against America” but also repeated his order to wait for outright operations against the United States until the campaign in the East had reached its successful conclusion. He repeated this order again on August 22.<span class="citation" data-cites="herwigPoliticsFrustrationUnited1976"><sup>4</sup></span></p>
<p>At the time of the <em>Greer</em> attack, Hitler and his naval commanders anticipated a war, soon, against the United States. The navy was eager for it and restrained only by Hitler’s belief that it must wait on the imminent victory against the USSR (which came, even to Hitler, to seem less imminent by the end of August, if still within reach).</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>David Stahel, <em>Opearation Barbarossa and Germany’s Defeat in the East</em> (Cambridge, Eng.: Cambridge University Press, 2009), 148.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Holger H. Herwig, <em>The Politics of Frustration: The United States in German Naval Planning, 1889--1941</em> (Boston: Little, Brown, 1976), 210, 214.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Herwig, <em>Politics of Frustration</em>, 216.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Herwig, <em>Politics of Frustration</em>, 224 and 224n, 226–227, 232 and 232n.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Greer</category>
  <category>convoys</category>
  <category>Nazi strategy</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_2_nazi/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://media.iwm.org.uk/cantaloupe/iiif/2/295||613||large_000000.jpg/full/730,/0/default.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Greer: just the facts</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_1/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>On September 4, 1941, the German submarine U-652 attempted to torpedo the U.S.S. <em>Greer,</em> a destroyer ferrying mail from the United States to Iceland. The president used the occasion to <a href="http://www.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/_resources/images/msf/msf01443">declare in a fireside chat</a> that</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>from now on, if German or Italian vessels of war enter the waters, the protection of which is necessary for American defense, they do so at their own peril.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_1/12248087.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Denmark, including Iceland, from an atlas of 1940–1945. David Rumsey Map Collection.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>There’s a lot to say about this episode, but let’s for this post try to get the facts straight, which historians often do not, even in otherwise reputable books. Consider for example,</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>On 4 September the German submarine U-652 unsuccessfully tried to torpedo the American escort destroyer U.S.S. <em>Greer,</em> which had attempted to depth-charge the U-boat south of Ireland.<span class="citation" data-cites="herwigPoliticsFrustrationUnited1976"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>While “Ireland” is probably an unfortunate typographical error, the assertion that <em>Greer</em> fired first is simply wrong and reflects German propaganda in the days after the attack.<span class="citation" data-cites="ClaimUBoatWas1941"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
<p>The bare facts are these:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>U.S.S. <em>Greer,</em> carrying the pennant of Commander G.W. Johnson and commanded by Lieutenant Commander L.H. Frost, was proceeding independently toward Iceland on 4 September 1941 in lat. 62°45’ N, long. 27°37’ W, at a speed of 17 1/2 knots. At 0840 a British plane signaled to her that a submerged U-boat lay athwart her course some ten miles ahead. <em>Greer</em> commenced zigzagging, increased speed to twenty knots, went to general quarters, laid a course for the reported position, and on reaching it slowed to ten knots in order to allow her sound gear to operate at full efficiency. She made sound contact with the submarine and maintained it for over three hours, keeping the submerged U-boat always on her bow but not attacking. At 1000 the British plane captain inquired whether <em>Greer</em> intended to attack, and was answered in the negative. He then dropped his depth charges more or less at random, and returned to base to refuel. At 1240 the submarine headed toward the American destroyer and launched a torpedo, which was sighted early enough to be dodged. <em>Greer</em> counterattacked with depth charges, and at 1300 the U-boat shot a second torpedo, which was also avoided. Unable to reestablish sound contact, <em>Greer</em> discontinued the search at 1416 and resumed course for Iceland.<span class="citation" data-cites="morisonBattleAtlanticSeptember1950"><sup>3</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>It seems essential to me for historians relating this episode to note that something like two hours passed after the British plane dropped its depth charges and before the U-boat fired on the <em>Greer.</em> The British attack, such as it was, was not ongoing at the time the German U-boat attempted to torpedo the American destroyer, although one may charitably say (as Waldo Heinrichs does) that the U-boat captain “must have regarded as hostile pursuit” the <em>Greer’s</em> continued persistence in tailing it.<span class="citation" data-cites="heinrichsThresholdWarFranklin1988"><sup>4</sup></span></p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Holger H. Herwig, <em>The Politics of Frustration: The United States in German Naval Planning, 1889--1941</em> (Boston: Little, Brown, 1976), 231.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>See, e.g., <span>“Claim U-Boat Was Acting in Self Defense,”</span> <em>Honolulu Star-Bulletin</em>, September 6, 1941, 1.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Samuel Eliot Morison, <em>The Battle of the Atlantic, September 1939--May 1943</em>, vol. 1, History of United States Naval Operations in World War II (Boston: Little, Brown, 1950), 79–80.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Waldo Heinrichs, <em>Threshold of War: Franklin D. Roosevelt and American Entry into World War II</em> (New York: Oxford University Press, 1988), 167.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Greer</category>
  <category>convoys</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_1/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_1/12248087.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The German threat to the United States, 1940–1941: Atlantic geography</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/atl_dist/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>This is a follow-up to <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/">the previous post</a> on Roosevelt’s assessment of the German threat in December 1940, pursuing the big question, “How much of a threat did Germany pose to the United States before Pearl Harbor?” This post looks at the question of Atlantic geography and German ambitions.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Likewise, the military scenarios Roosevelt sketched had little basis in reality. . . . He also stressed the narrowness of the Atlantic, even if not at the obviously most relevant place: “At one point between Africa and Brazil the distance is less than from Washington to Denver, Colorado—five hours for the latest type of bomber.”<span class="citation" data-cites="thompsonExaggerationAmericanVulnerability1992"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Let’s consider the Atlantic situation at the time of Roosevelt’s speech at the end of 1940.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/atl_dist/atlmap.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">The strategic situation in the Atlantic at the end of 1940.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>You can see the short distance from Brazil to West Africa; you can also see that French West Africa was at the time under the jurisdiction of the Vichy regime. France had fallen to Germany in June; Italy had entered the war and struck west across North Africa. Though the Italians had failed to take Egypt and were then suffering under British counter-attack, the Germans would shortly organize the Afrika Corps under Erwin Rommel and deploy it to the region.<span class="citation" data-cites="weinbergWorldArmsGlobal2005"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
<p>The status of West Africa was thus anything but evidently secure at the end of 1940, and indeed would only seem less secure quite soon.</p>
<p>Even as Roosevelt was warning that the Americas were vulnerable to German assault across the Atlantic, Hitler was planning for such an attack. In response to the Roosevelt administration’s September 1940 agreement to trade US destroyers for British bases in the western hemisphere, Hitler told Admiral Raeder that “England-USA must be thrown out of North-West Africa.” He opened negotiations with Spain to trade French Morocco for one of the Canary Islands, to establish a military outpost in the far West of the European hemisphere; he also began to consider whether the Azores could be used “to carry out aerial attacks from a land base against the United States.” German bomber technology would not then support it but nobody could then know of the limits on even the longest-range German bombers then under development, the Heinkel 177.<span class="citation" data-cites="herwigPreludeWeltblitzkriegGermany1971"><sup>3</sup></span></p>
<p>In the period between the fall of France and Pearl Harbor, Germany appeared to be at peak power, to Germans and to outside observers alike. Through 1941, aware of the impending Japanese attack, Hitler would continue to plan for a German war on the United States, in which an assault across the Atlantic would play a part.<span class="citation" data-cites="herwigPreludeWeltblitzkriegGermany1971"><sup>4</sup></span> There is thus no obvious reason to believe that Roosevelt was wrong, or alarmist, to consider the relative narrowness of the ocean or the possibility of a German aerial assault across its expanse.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>John A. Thompson, <span>“The Exaggeration of American Vulnerability: The Anatomy of a Tradition,”</span> <em>Diplomatic History</em> 16, no. 1 (January 1992): 30.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Gerhard L. Weinberg, <em>A World at Arms: A Global History of World War II</em>, 2nd ed. (Cambridge, Eng.: Cambridge University Press, 2005), 215.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Holger H Herwig, <span>“Prelude to Weltblitzkrieg: Germany’s Naval Policy Toward the United States of America, 1939-41,”</span> <em>Journal of Modern History</em> 43, no. 4 (December 1971): 657–58.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Herwig, <span>“Prelude to Weltblitzkrieg,”</span> 660–62.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>airpower</category>
  <category>Nazi strategy</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/atl_dist/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/atl_dist/atlmap.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="172" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The German threat to the United States, 1940–1941: bomber range</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>How much of a threat did Germany pose to the United States before Pearl Harbor? That’s the big question; let’s look at a small part of it. Historians often say Roosevelt exaggerated the specific threats Nazi Germany posed; here we’ll look at one claim about the threat posed by German bombers.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Likewise, the military scenarios Roosevelt sketched had little basis in reality. . . . In December 1940 he made the remarkable claim that “even today we have planes that could fly from the British Isles to New England and back again without refueling.”<span class="citation" data-cites="thompsonExaggerationAmericanVulnerability1992"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>It might seem to us remarkable that in December 1940, airplanes could fly the distance of an Atlantic round trip, but it was not remarkable to claim it. The crossing comes to about a 3,000-mile flight one way, so a return journey would total 6,000 miles. The Imperial Airways seaplane <em>Mercury</em> completed a flight of more than 6,000 miles non-stop from Dundee, Scotland to the Orange River in South Africa in October 1938.<span class="citation" data-cites="wraggBoatsAirIllustrated1984"><sup>2</sup></span> This feat was <a href="https://nyti.ms/3nTEwJC">reported in the newspapers, together with comparable records.</a> Not only was Roosevelt’s statement simply true, many of his listeners would have known it already.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/https:/www.nli.ie/digital/vtls000249986.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">The <em>Mercury</em> shown atop its launcher airplane, the flying boat <em>Maia.</em> National Library of Ireland.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Let’s look more closely at Roosevelt’s specific claim. This is what it says in the reading copy:</p>
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/range_claim.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>And here’s what Roosevelt actually said, according to transcription at the time:</p>
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/range_claim_as_said.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>First, this claim was refined in the process of writing the speech. Thanks to the FDR Presidential Library, we can <a href="http://www.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/_resources/images/msf/msf01403,">link to the relevant folder in the Master Speech File</a> and see that in earlier drafts, this paragraph read,</p>
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/earlier_claim.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The claim that planes could fly return from New York to London was probably supportable enough, given the flight of the <em>Mercury.</em> But at the seventh draft, Roosevelt changed it (notice the handwriting):</p>
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/revised_claim.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Now not only is the distance more accurate and defensible—from “the British Isles” to “New England” is more accurately the route Imperial Airways was even then, despite the war, flying; but by changing its direction Roosevelt was, of course, emphasizing the potential threat should Britain fall to Germany.</p>
<p>Second, the claim about the outside range of existing aircraft is coupled here with a second claim. It’s clear with these two sentences that Roosevelt and his speechwriters are making a distinction between what the longest-distance airplanes could already do, and what modern bombers could soon do. This observation supports a generalization I want to make and will probably make again: Roosevelt and his speechwriters were quite careful.</p>
<p>The claim about how bombers were then developing, and what their capacity would be, was also correct. The B-29, though it was still on the drawing board, would have a <a href="https://www.boeing.com/history/products/b-29-superfortress.page">maximum range of 5,830 miles.</a> The experimental predecessor to the B-29, the XB-15, had already flown in 1937, and derived from a plan for a bomber with an effective range of 5,000 miles.<span class="citation" data-cites="knaackEncyclopediaAirForce1988"><sup>3</sup></span> Americans attentive to the news would have known about the XB-15; Major Caleb Haynes of the US Army air corps <a href="https://nyti.ms/3GlePbu">had flown one on an earthquake relief mission from Langley to Santiago, Chile, stopping in Panama and Peru, in February 1939.</a></p>
<p>Again, not only did Roosevelt make a carefully constructed and factually correct claim, he made one that many of his listeners would have understood to be readily supportable.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>John A. Thompson, <span>“The Exaggeration of American Vulnerability: The Anatomy of a Tradition,”</span> <em>Diplomatic History</em> 16, no. 1 (January 1992): 30.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>David W. Wragg, <em>Boats of the Air: An Illustrated History of Flying Boats, Seaplanes and Amphibians</em> (London: Robert Hale, 1984), 149.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Marcelle Size Knaack, <em>Encyclopedia of U.S. Air Force Aircraft and Missile Systems</em>, vol. 2: Post–World War II Bombers, 1945--1973 (Washington, D.C.: Office of Air Force History, 1988), 479.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>airpower</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.nli.ie/digital/vtls000249986.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
