<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>a necessitous blog</title>
<link>https://erauchway.github.io/</link>
<atom:link href="https://erauchway.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>A blog about the era of the Roosevelt administration, 1933--1945</description>
<generator>quarto-1.8.25</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2025 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>What this country needs</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/hoover_cigar/hoover_cigar.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Herbert Hoover problem was <em>not</em> that he was a technocrat who didn’t understand politics. He was a savvy political operator and a master of public relations who understood that it was to his advantage to seem like a technocrat who didn’t understand politics. So when you say he was a technocrat who didn’t understand politics, you are falling for a hustle, in the manner of someone who perceives Fast Eddie Felson isn’t striking the balls quite so smartly as you had heard.</p>
<p>James MacLafferty, one of Hoover’s aides and fixers, kept a diary and in the entry for April 14, 1932, he pasted a couple of Hoover’s cigar bands he found in the Cabinet room of the White House that morning, after an all-night session in which the Chief (Hoover’s loyal aides preferred to call him “the Chief”) had lobbied Congress—successfully, as it would turn out—to cut federal salaries.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./cigar.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Havana cigar bands pasted into MacLafferty’s diary. Click to enlarge."><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/hoover_cigar/cigar.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Havana cigar bands pasted into MacLafferty’s diary. Click to enlarge."></a></p>
<figcaption>Havana cigar bands pasted into MacLafferty’s diary. Click to enlarge.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Now you can say this episode shows that Hoover had terrible instincts, so far as macroeconomic policy goes, but I wouldn’t say it shows he didn’t know how to do politicking. He was able by dint of traditional jawboning and soft-selling to get his bad ideas through a Democratic House majority. He was a very good politician—which doesn’t by any stretch mean he had good policies.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Hoover</category>
  <category>Historiography</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/hoover_cigar/hoover_cigar.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Social Security at 90</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/ssa_100/ssa_100.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The Social Security Act is ninety years old this year. Here’s a chart showing expenditures in its first ten years, 1936–1935, from the <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015086702803&amp;seq=484&amp;q1=June">United States <em>Treasury Bulletin.</em></a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./ssa.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Chart showing Social Security Board expenditures by category, 1936–1945. Click to enlarge."><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/ssa_100/ssa.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Chart showing Social Security Board expenditures by category, 1936–1945. Click to enlarge."></a></p>
<figcaption>Chart showing Social Security Board expenditures by category, 1936–1945. Click to enlarge.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>Social Security</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/ssa_100/ssa_100.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Some interwar booknotes from recent TLS issues</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/tls_interwar/tls_interwar.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The TLS has recently run a number of essays on books that cover fascism in the interwar period, which thus fall within this blog’s <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/about.html">very sternly enforced remit.</a></p>
<p>Fintan O’Toole <a href="https://www.the-tls.com/politics-society/politics/burn-them-out-padraig-og-o-ruairc-year-of-the-rat-harry-shukman-book-review-fintan-otoole">writes</a> about Pádraig Óg Ó Ruairc’s history of fascism in Ireland, including “the IRA’s collaboration with the Nazis during the Second World War (on the time-honoured but idiotic grounds that ‘England’s difficulty is Ireland’s opportunity’).”</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./blue_blouses.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="A line of mostly women (Blue Blouses) with some men (Blueshirts) all giving a stiff-armed fascist salute. RTE. Click to enlarge."><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/tls_interwar/blue_blouses.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A line of mostly women (Blue Blouses) with some men (Blueshirts) all giving a stiff-armed fascist salute. RTE. Click to enlarge."></a></p>
<figcaption>A line of mostly women (Blue Blouses) with some men (Blueshirts) all giving a stiff-armed fascist salute. RTE. Click to enlarge.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The book also discusses the Irish Blueshirts, fascists who opposed the Irish government, which they believed “a crowd of Spaniards, Jews and Manxmen” O’Toole aptly notes, “I have yet to discover what the Irish fascists had against the Manx, but the point is obvious enough – it is the far right that generates the alien threat and not the other way around.”</p>
<p>Charles Darwent <a href="https://www.the-tls.com/arts/visual-arts/comrades-in-art-andy-friend-book-review-charles-darwent">reviews</a> Andy Friend’s study of the Artists International (swiftly renamed the Artists International Association, to avoid unwanted if accurate associations), a leftist anti-fascist organization. Though the book covers the period up to 1943, the essay doesn’t mention how the AIA dealt with the pact. I guess I have to read the book.</p>
<p>Catherine Taylor <a href="https://www.the-tls.com/literature-by-region/european-literature/crooked-cross-sally-carson-book-review-catherine-taylor">writes about</a> Sally Carson’s recently reprinted <em>Crooked Cross,</em> a 1934 novel about how the rise of the Nazi government affects a family in a small Bavarian mountain town. I picked up a copy earlier this year when I was in Britain and read it then. It’s so prescient, it’s difficult to believe it was written before the Hitler government had long been in power. Indeed Carson died before the Nazis’ horrors could be fully revealed: she passed away on June 21, 1941, as the Germans were just invading the Soviet Union.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Nazis</category>
  <category>Fascism</category>
  <category>TLS</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/tls_interwar/tls_interwar.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Plattism and the Gibraltar of Puerto Rico</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/monroe_d/monroe_d.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Cuba provided one of the first tests of Franklin Roosevelt’s initially ill defined “good neighbor” policy in 1933. Down to the autumn, Roosevelt’s Ambassador to Cuba Sumner Welles had been advising that the US might well need to send troops to Cuba under the terms of the Platt Amendment—the clause <a href="https://www.archives.gov/milestone-documents/platt-amendment">US officials inserted into the Cuban constitution of 1901</a> to permit US military intervention—to restore order after the fall of the Machado government.<span class="citation" data-cites="cronon1959-11"><sup>1</sup></span> But in November, Roosevelt said he wanted <a href="https://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/documents/presidential-statement-non-intervention-cuba">“a modification of the permanent treaty between the United States and Cuba,”</a> which as E. David Cronon writes, “could only mean that Washington contemplated relinquishing some of its rights under the Platt Amendment.”<span class="citation" data-cites="cronon1959-11"><sup>2</sup></span> In the following month, at the Pan American Conference in Montevideo, Secretary of State Cordell Hull agreed to a general nonintervention pledge and in 1934, the US signed a revised treaty with Cuba removing the Platt Amendment. The Platt Amendment, and what Latin Americans called “Plattism” more broadly, was gone; the good neighbor policy, so vague at the start, suddenly had a clear meaning: the era of interpreting the Monroe Doctrine as a general license for US military action in the Americas had ended.</p>
<p>As part of this revision of hemispheric policy, the Roosevelt administration also adjusted US relations to the territories it would not relinquish: Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, Alaska, and Hawaiʻi. Each of them would get its own version of the New Deal, including relief, public works, and programs for economic development.</p>
<p>The implementation of the New Deal in Puerto Rico was vexed, to say the least: for all that it achieved, much remained undone, and no party or faction in Puerto Rican politics lacked a critique of the Roosevelt administration’s policies. But many Puerto Rican politicians nevertheless preferred the New Deal to the treatment of their island “as a Caribbean Gibraltar”—that is, as a strategically located military outpost, whose inhabitants’ welfare was of little interest to Washington.<span class="citation" data-cites="ErnestGrueningdiary"><sup>3</sup></span></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./sf_pr.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="The fortess of San Felipe del Morro, Puerto Rico, 1943. US Navy History and Heritage Command. Click to enlarge."><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/monroe_d/sf_pr.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The fortess of San Felipe del Morro, Puerto Rico, 1943. US Navy History and Heritage Command. Click to enlarge."></a></p>
<figcaption>The fortess of San Felipe del Morro, Puerto Rico, 1943. US Navy History and Heritage Command. Click to enlarge.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Anyway it seems Marco Rubio has announced that <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cx23nzwjnwwo">Plattism is back.</a> And it has brought <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/sep/05/trump-fighter-planes-puerto-rico-venezuela-drug-cartel">Puerto Rico-as-Gibraltar</a> with it.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>E. David Cronon, <span>“Interpreting the New Good Neighbor Policy: The Cuban Crisis of 1933,”</span> <em>Hispanic American Historical Review</em> 39, no. 4 (1959): 538–67.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p><span>“Interpreting,”</span> 560.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Ernest Gruening, diary, Ernest Gruening Papers, Arctic and Polar Regions Collections, University of Alaska, Fairbanks, May 12, 1939.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Empire of the New Deal</category>
  <category>Puerto Rico</category>
  <category>Cuba</category>
  <category>Platt Amendment</category>
  <category>Monroe Doctrine</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/monroe_d/monroe_d.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Full of, buckets of</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/language/language.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As <a href="https://www.google.com/books/edition/Days_of_Fire/eXCJDQAAQBAJ?hl=en&amp;gbpv=1&amp;dq=john+nance+garner+%22bucket+of+warm+spit%22&amp;pg=PA60&amp;printsec=frontcover">recently as 2014,</a> serious writers of nonfiction still considered it appropriate to coyly bowdlerize John Nance Garner’s reported remark that the vice presidency was not worth a bucket of warm piss.<sup>1</sup> (Garner, Roosevelt’s vice president for his first two terms, was picked to assuage Texas and William Randolph Hearst in the nominating convention of 1932. Had Roosevelt been killed when he was shot at in February 1933, Garner would have become president. The New Deal would have looked a good deal different with the Texan who was (according to Hearst at least) an America Firster at the helm.)</p>
<p>I wonder what will become of the current vice president’s <a href="https://nymag.com/intelligencer/article/rfk-jr-to-testify-before-senate-committee-live-updates.html#reaction-time">similarly excretory remark</a> about the health and human services secretary’s senatorial critics. Will the likes of Peter Baker (cited above) feel they must clean it up for publication? Or have we entered an era of greater authenticity in rendering vice presidential speech?</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Which he may actually have said, and <a href="https://www.historynewsnetwork.org/article/not-worth-a-bucket-of-warm-spit">maybe even to Lyndon Johnson.</a>↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>John Nance Garner</category>
  <category>Language</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/language/language.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The American Family</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/duke/duke.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The FDR Library has this photo, captioned, “The Last of the Royalty of Hawaii! Salutes the President—26 July 1934,” <a href="https://fdr.blogs.archives.gov/hawaii1-2/">on its website.</a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./duke.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Outrigger canoes, one with a platform covered in what are maybe ki leaves bearing a man in a traditional feathered cape and headdress. Click to enlarge."><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/duke/duke.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Outrigger canoes, one with a platform covered in what are maybe ki leaves bearing a man in a traditional feathered cape and headdress. Click to enlarge."></a></p>
<figcaption>Outrigger canoes, one with a platform covered in what are maybe ki leaves bearing a man in a traditional feathered cape and headdress. Click to enlarge.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’m pretty sure—especially from the description in the US Navy Historical Command’s <a href="https://www.history.navy.mil/research/histories/ship-histories/danfs/h/houston-ii.html">history of the <em>USS Houston</em></a>—that the caption, written on the original photo, is intentionally whimsical, and the person wearing the feathered cape and headdress of Hawaiian aliʻi (familiar to viewers of <em>Chief of War</em>) is actually Duke Kahanamoku, Olympic swimming champion, longboard surfer, and then-serving sheriff of Honolulu. Duke Kahanamoku would also greet Ernest Gruening, as administrator of the Division of Territories and Island Possessions, in 1937—though apparently without the special garb.</p>
<p>Roosevelt’s 1934 trip was a combined Good Neighbor Policy / Territorial relations tour. He would first visit Haiti, from which <a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015049924361?urlappend=%3Bseq=409%3Bownerid=13510798884175400-409">he had ordered the accelerated end</a> of the US occupation (reversing not only US policy but his own earlier views, when he was Assistant Secretary of the Navy under Wilson); he would also go to Colombia.</p>
<p>Maybe more importantly, he visited Puerto Rico and the Virgin Islands, and afterward Hawaiʻi (the first sitting president to do so). He had just created the Division of Territories and Island Possessions to administer the New Deal in Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, Hawaiʻi, and Alaska—the territories whose people were US citizens—and on this trip he would explain that US citizens in the territories were as much a part of the “American family” as anyone else.<span class="citation" data-cites="frankind.Radio1934 PresidentStCroix1934 franklindRadio1934-07-28"><sup>1</sup></span></p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Franklin D. Roosevelt, <span>“Radio Address of the President, San Juan, Puerto Rico,”</span> July 7, 1934, <span>“July 7–21, 1934,”</span> Master Speech File, FDRL; <span>“The President at St. Croix, V.I. (Transcript),”</span> July 8, 1934, fldr <span>“Speech at San Juan, St. Croix, Panama—Caribbean Tour,”</span> Master Speech File, FDRL; Franklin D. Roosevelt, <span>“Radio Address at Honolulu, T.H.”</span> July 28, 1934.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Empire of the New Deal</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/duke/duke.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Unconditional Surrender</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/USgrant/usgrant.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>On January 24, 1943, Franklin Roosevelt and Winston Churchill held a joint press conference in Morocco, after some days discussing combined Allied strategy in the Casablanca meeting. (Stalin declined to attend.) They met there—they could meet there—because the US army had begun to assist the British army in clearing the Nazis from North Africa.</p>
<p>The most important immediate result of the conference was probably the plan for the Combined Bomber Offensive, but the more important in terms of strategy—and one that was very much, like the “United Nations,” like the prioritization of North Africa, Roosevelt’s personal preference—was the announcement of an Allied policy to demand unconditional surrender.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/USgrant/usgrant.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Press conference text of Roosevelt’s “unconditional surrender” remarks.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Roosevelt believed peace could only come with the utter defeat of the fascist powers. Not the destruction of their people, as he was quick to stipulate: but the destruction of their ability to make war. For him, the war was, necessarily, a war against fascism, not merely against a particular enemy, and fascism needed to be not only defeated but widely seen to have been defeated.</p>
<p>The demand for unconditional surrender was, and remains, debated in its wisdom. As Marc Gallicchio’s <em>Unconditional</em> establishes quite clearly, though, it was the New Dealers’ position; people on the political right—the pre-war isolationists, chiefly—were the ones who preferred an accommodation with the fascist powers.<span class="citation" data-cites="gallicchioUnconditionalJapaneseSurrender2020"><sup>1</sup></span></p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Marc Gallicchio, <em>Unconditional: The Japanese Surrender in World War II</em> (New York: Oxford University Press, 2020).↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Strategy</category>
  <category>Unconditional surrender</category>
  <category>Isolationists</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/USgrant/usgrant.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Beginning a Planned Program</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/concepts_plan/concepts.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>On April 7, 1932, while campaigning for the Democratic presidential nomination, Governor Franklin D. Roosevelt gave a radio speech laying out “a few essentials, a beginning, in fact, of a planned program” of economic recovery; what you might call the basic concepts of a plan.</p>
<p>First, he said, the plan needed to run “bottom to top and not from top to bottom”—in contrast to the recently created Reconstruction Finance Corporation, which put some billions of dollars “at the disposal of the big banks, the railroads and the corporations of the nation.”</p>
<p>He said that even a large emergency public works program “would be only a stopgap,” and said that really what the nation needed was a “cure.”</p>
<p>He then sketched three basic ideas: pushing up the prices of farm commodities “to restore purchasing power to the farming half of the country”; protection for homeowners from foreclosure by protecting the smaller banks and lending companies; lowering tariffs “on the basis of a reciprocal exchange” with other countries.</p>
<p>He said these would be “only a part of ten or a dozen vital factors.” But that “temporary relief from the top down” would not suffice; the nation needed “permanent relief from the bottom up.”<span class="citation" data-cites="rooseveltAlbany1932-04-08"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
<p>The <em>New York Times</em> editorial board were shocked at this “demagogic claptrap.” The Reconstruction Finance Corporation was “conceived by the best financial and business brains of this country.” As for the smaller banks, “the closing of these little local banks has been stayed and almost stopped.” It had not, of course, been stopped on what the governor would have called a “permanent” basis and would resume and accelerate later in the summer.<span class="citation" data-cites="BottomManApril"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
<p>Roosevelt enjoyed “the howl from the New York Times and other leading papers,”<span class="citation" data-cites="roosevelt1932-04-12"><sup>3</sup></span> as he wrote to Josephus Daniels, who had been his boss in the Navy Department. For his part, Daniels said, “you hit the bullseye”:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>We cannot win by letting the folks think the Republican party is 51% bad and we are only 49% bad. Some of our folks in Washington have thought if we acted not quite as subservient to the big interests as the Republicans we could win. You have shown that we must have a definite policy and that prosperity cannot be invoked by incantations and lending money to people who do not use it to start the wheels of industry.<span class="citation" data-cites="daniels1932-04-09"><sup>4</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/concepts_plan/daniels.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Franklin Roosevelt and Josephus Daniels in 1940. FDRL</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Roosevelt would come to emphasize a large program of public works more, later in the campaign; at one point he would say that his proposed reforestation program alone—the idea that became the Civilian Conservation Corps—might employ a million workers.<span class="citation" data-cites="rooseveltChicago1932-07-02"><sup>5</sup></span> And he would continue to campaign on the ideas of propping up farm prices, lowering tariffs, and protecting the smaller lenders and borrowers.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Franklin D. Roosevelt, <span>“Albany, NY - Radio Speech,”</span> April 8, 1932, Master Speech File, FDRL.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p><span>“The <span>‘Bottom’</span> Man,”</span> <em>New York Times</em>, April 9, 1932.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Franklin D. Roosevelt to Josephus Daniels, April 12, 1932, fldr <span>“Daniels, Josephus, 1932,”</span> box 19, series 1, FDR Governorship Papers, FDRL.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Josephus Daniels to Franklin D. Roosevelt, April 9, 1932, fldr <span>“Daniels, Josephus, 1932,”</span> box 19, series 1, FDR Governorship Papers, FDRL.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>@ Franklin D. Roosevelt, <span>“Chicago, IL - Acceptance Speech for Presidential Nomination,”</span> July 2, 1932, Master Speech File, FDRL.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/concepts_plan/concepts.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 09 Aug 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Rapid Involuntary Retirement</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/stewart/stewart_sacked.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Shortly after the chief of the Bureau of Labor Statistics declined to support a factually insupportable rosy jobs report, the president had him forcibly retired. In 1932, labor statistics commissioner Ethelbert Stewart was indignantly reclassified as dispensable.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I have a contract with the Government and it has been broken. Retired? Don’t put it that way. I’ve had a tin can tied to the end of my coat tail.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He had very recently been yelled at by Secretary of Labor William Doak in front of reporters for <a href="https://time.com/archive/6749502/the-cabinet-tin-can/">disputing a bright employment forecast.</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Hoover</category>
  <category>Depression</category>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/stewart/stewart_sacked.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Empire of Relief, 1933</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/relief_pc/relief_st_terr.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The Federal Emergency Relief Act of 1933, <a href="https://uscode.house.gov/statviewer.htm?volume=48&amp;page=55">48 Stat. 56,</a> proposed to relieve “hardship and suffering caused by unemployment” in the United States, which meant not only the States and the District of Columbia, but the Territories, as the title and the first section of the law stated. The people of the United States in the Territories were also entitled to relief from the Depression, in keeping with Roosevelt’s broadly inclusive message about the interdependence of all the sprawling republic’s people.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./pc_relief.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Per capita relief in states and territories. Click to enlarge."><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/relief_pc/pc_relief.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Per capita relief in states and territories. Click to enlarge."></a></p>
<figcaption>Per capita relief in states and territories. Click to enlarge.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As you can see in the chart, relief went to the territories (shown in orange) on a basis commensurate with that of the states. While I’m skeptical of drawing any substantial inference based on the relative position of localities in the per-capita expenditures of the New Deal, the fact that the territories are in the same general run of per-capita spending as the states, and not outliers, suggests to me the early relief programs in the territories were comparable to those in the states. At least, for these four territories: these were the ones whose people were, by law, US citizens.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>Territories</category>
  <category>Empire of the New Deal</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/relief_pc/relief_st_terr.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Chicago 18 in the Zotero Style Repository</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/chicago18/chicago18.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>If you were eagerly waiting for the innovations of the eighteenth edition of the Chicago Manual of Style to come to Zotero, you can breathe easier. They are <a href="https://forums.zotero.org/discussion/125429/implementation-of-the-chicago-manual-of-style-18th-edition">here.</a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/chicago18/cmos18.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="250"></p>
<figcaption>The bright-yellow cover of the Chicago Manual of Style, 18th edition.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Maybe you were ready to drop place of publication. Maybe you weren’t. But as your university press representative has probably told you, it is time.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/chicago18/chicago18.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Historians and the Isolationists: National Security</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/preston/tls_liberty.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’ve <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/williams_hoover/williams_hoover.html">said</a> here <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/polling_ww2/polling_ww2.html">before</a> that I think scholars of US foreign relations give too much credence to isolationist arguments and now I guess I’ve said it <a href="https://www.the-tls.com/history/twentieth-century-onwards-history/total-defense-andrew-preston-book-review-eric-rauchway">in the <em>TLS,</em> too.</a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/preston/fdr_wsc.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Franklin D. Roosevelt and Winston Churchill fishing. FDR Library.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I structured the essay around implications of the Roosevelt–Churchill destroyers-for-bases deal of 1940, and in discussing Andrew Preston’s <em>Total Defense,</em> which lays out the case that Roosevelt invented a modern discourse of “national security” that defined threats to the United States more broadly than ever before—indeed, globally and ideologically—I suggest we might not want to accept the arguments of those like Herbert Hoover and Charles Lindbergh that the Axis posed no threat to the United States itself.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>when Preston says that “geopolitical logic came down on the side of anti-interventionists like Hoover and Lindbergh: the United States was actually never in danger of being attacked by the Axis powers”, he is accepting implicitly their narrow definition of “the United States” – one that excluded the people of the US territories, many of whom were US citizens or nationals. It is perhaps understandable that Lindbergh, who was never known for his analytical acuity, should have left such people out of his geopolitical logic; for Roosevelt to do so would probably have violated his oath of office as president. Eventually, most of the US territories listed above did come under Axis attack and even occupation. If Roosevelt defined US national security with unprecedented breadth, then his opponents defined the defensible US so narrowly that they proposed to cede parts of the US to fascist invaders.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There’s more in that vein there, though I didn’t get into the nitty-gritty of it: the people in the US territories of Alaska, Hawaiʻi, and Puerto Rico were all defined by law as US citizens. All these places came under Axis attack during the war.<sup>1</sup> US citizens on Howland Island were <a href="https://oceanexplorer.noaa.gov/okeanos/explorations/ex1705/background/jarvis/welcome.html">killed by Japanese attack.</a> There are of course excellent cases that these lands and people ought not to have been under US government, but they were; and I suppose the morality or legality of US sovereignty over them, however dubious, would not have been notably improved by leaving them to the mercy of the Axis powers.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Pearl Harbor is, I suppose, obvious; the Aleutian campaign and the bombing of Dutch Harbor reasonably well known. A <a href="https://www.newspapers.com/article/the-fresno-bee/176933638/">U-boat shelled a National Youth Administration camp</a> (though with no casualties) on Mona Island, part of the Puerto Rico archipelago, in 1942.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Historiography</category>
  <category>Isolationists</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/preston/tls_liberty.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>DRINK TAROCO</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/taroco/taroco.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Part of the <a href="https://www.rai.ox.ac.uk/event/empire-of-the-new-deal">empire of the New Deal</a> was finding sustainable businesses to run in the US territories. Hawaiʻi grew lots of taro (kalo); why not find a market for it? The Department of the Interior ordered taro flour and a drink called Taroco in quantity, to be served in the department’s cafeteria.<span class="citation" data-cites="USOfficialsTaro1938-03-19"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="pasadena.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Detail of an ad for the drink Taroco, from the Pasadena Star-News of November 28, 1938. Click to enlarge."><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/taroco/pasadena.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Detail of an ad for the drink Taroco, from the Pasadena Star-News of November 28, 1938. Click to enlarge."></a></p>
<figcaption>Detail of an ad for the drink Taroco, from the <em>Pasadena Star-News</em> of November 28, 1938. Click to enlarge.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Secretary of the Interior Harold Ickes was photographed drinking Taroco and eating taro-flour biscuits in March 1938. Sadly, it was only about seven months before the project’s promoters reported to director of the Division of Territories and Island Possessions that “Taro products are having a hard time getting started.”<span class="citation" data-cites="ErnestGrueningdiary"><sup>2</sup></span> Before long the company gave up and sold its assets to another firm that made similar products for local manufacture.<span class="citation" data-cites="rada1952-12"><sup>3</sup></span></p>
<p>For what it’s worth, we’ve had taro-flour biscuits; they were pretty tasty. Never had chocolate taro milk though.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p><span>“U.S. Officials Like Taro; Gruening, Ickes Order It,”</span> <em>Honolulu Star-Bulletin</em>, March 19, 1938.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Entry for October 18, 1938, Ernest Gruening, diary (n.d.), Ernest Gruening Papers, Arctic and Polar Regions Collections, University of Alaska, Fairbanks.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Edward L. Rada, <span>“Mainland Market for Taro Products: A Preliminary Study”</span> (University of Hawaii, College of Agriculture, December 1952), 2.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>Territories</category>
  <category>Empire of the New Deal</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/taroco/taroco.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Pitt Rivers and Totem Bight</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/pitt_rivers/pitt_rivers.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The TLS has <a href="https://www.the-tls.com/politics-society/social-cultural-studies/every-monument-will-fall-dan-hicks-book-review-tristram-hunt">a fairly bracing essay</a> by Tristram Hunt, curator of the V&amp;A, on a book by Dan Hicks, curator of the Pitt Rivers Museum in Oxford, an institution which Hunt describes (in my view aptly) as “a darkened labyrinth of cabinets” arranged in a “riotously Victorian, deliriously Gormenghast manner.” Adorning the essay is a photo like this one which gives a hint of the jumble that is the Pitt Rivers’s main hall, presided over by the tall Haida totem pole you can see near center, which once stood outside Star House in Massett Village in what is now Canada.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./pitt_rivers.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Photo of the Pitt Rivers main hall like the TLS one, but not the TLS one (this one by me). Click to enlarge."><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/pitt_rivers/pitt_rivers.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Photo of the Pitt Rivers main hall like the TLS one, but not the TLS one (this one by me). Click to enlarge."></a></p>
<figcaption>Photo of the Pitt Rivers main hall like the TLS one, but not the TLS one (this one by me). Click to enlarge.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Hicks, according to Hunt anyway, cordially loathes the collection of which he is curator, which perhaps accounts for the ambivalence on some of the explanatory plaques, like the one for that Haida totem, which asserts its figures and stories remain “part of Haida culture.”</p>
<p>As it happens a couple weeks ago Kathy Olmsted and I were on a research trip, mainly to go to archives, but also to see some other Haida, and Tlingit and Tsimshian, totem poles together with a clan house not unlike Star House, in Saxman Village near Ketchikan, Alaska. Together with Totem Bight, also near Ketchikan, and some other totem poles in town, these sites are the legacy of a New Deal program to, as one of its creators wrote, “see that these totems are preserved <em>in situ.</em>”</p>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout-ncol="2">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./saxman.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Totems and clan house at Saxman Village. Click to enlarge."><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/pitt_rivers/saxman.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Totems and clan house at Saxman Village. Click to enlarge."></a></p>
<figcaption>Totems and clan house at Saxman Village. Click to enlarge.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./totem_bight.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Totems at Totem Bight. Click to enlarge."><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/pitt_rivers/totem_bight.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Totems at Totem Bight. Click to enlarge."></a></p>
<figcaption>Totems at Totem Bight. Click to enlarge.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Under the New Deal, the federal government hired Native carvers to practice and pass on their art, which had fallen out of favor under missionary influence. The explanatory plaques there, unlike the one in the Pitt Rivers, do not assert that the totem poles and their figures and stories remain part of Native culture but perhaps that is because it is obvious; there Native people retain stewardship of the living art.</p>
<p>It is of course true that the Roosevelt reform program in the territories constituted an <a href="https://www.rai.ox.ac.uk/event/empire-of-the-new-deal">empire of the New Deal.</a> Does it matter that this empire, instead of carting cultural artifacts away to the Pitt Rivers, funded the preservation and perpetuation of the artifacts and moreover the art form amongst the people to whom it belonged?</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>Territories</category>
  <category>Empire of the New Deal</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/pitt_rivers/pitt_rivers.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>History of Tariffs 2</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/aha_tariffs2/aha_tariffs2.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>If you are among the legions who enjoy the history of tariffs (as previously discussed <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/aha_tariffs/aha_tariffs.html">here</a>) but prefer it with lively hand gestures—</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/aha_tariffs2/rauchway_gestures.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>A historian talking and making hand gestures with rapidity sufficient to stymie the camera’s ability clearly to record them.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>—then you can watch the AHA Congressional Briefing on the History of Tariffs in the US on C-SPAN2, at <a href="https://www.c-span.org/program/american-history-tv/history-of-tariffs/661101?_gl=1*7ur5hl*_up*MQ..*_gs*MQ..&amp;gbraid=0AAAAAoVMygI8eDcYnfta-pGsJGXFhS5lH">this link</a>.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Historiography</category>
  <category>Tariffs</category>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>Reciprocal Tariff Agreements Act of 1934</category>
  <category>Smoot-Hawley</category>
  <category>C-SPAN</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/aha_tariffs2/aha_tariffs2.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>AHA Congressional Briefing: History of Tariffs</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/aha_tariffs/aha_tariffs.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The AHA hosted a Congressional briefing this morning in the Rayburn office building with about 70 people in attendance and a panel including Douglas Irwin, Sharon Ann Murphy, and me. C-SPAN filmed it for later broadcast. My remarks as prepared appear below, though if you should someday watch the C-SPAN recording you’ll know I went off script, based on what Doug had already said.</p>
<hr>
<p>Good morning. I’m going to speak for a few minutes on the origins of presidential authority to make tariff deals with other countries in the Reciprocal Trade Agreements Act of 1934.</p>
<p>Franklin Roosevelt first ran for president in 1932 arguing for lower tariffs as part of the New Deal by saying the <strong>“outrageously excessive [tariff] rates . . . must come down. . . . by consenting to reduce . . . some of our duties in order to secure a lowering of foreign tariff walls.”<span class="citation" data-cites="roosevelt1932-09-29"><sup>1</sup></span></strong> The idea was to reduce tariffs in exchange for other countries’ doing likewise, so as to open overseas markets for US goods. This is the trade principle known as reciprocity. Opinion polls demonstrate that Roosevelt supporters expected him to reduce tariffs.<span class="citation" data-cites="norpothAmericanVoter19322019"><sup>2</sup></span> Herbert Hoover vigorously opposed reducing tariffs and warned that if it happened, <strong>“The grass will grow in [the] streets of a hundred cities, a thousand towns.”<span class="citation" data-cites="hoover1977"><sup>3</sup></span></strong> Roosevelt won the election and the right to reduce tariffs; his inaugural parade included a group of men with lawnmowers marching through the streets of Washington, DC.<span class="citation" data-cites="rauchwayWinterWarHoover2018"><sup>4</sup></span> Once in office, he acquired the power to negotiate lower tariffs on a reciprocal basis.</p>
<p>To fulfill Roosevelt’s campaign promise, the Reciprocal Tariff Agreement Act of 1934 amended the Smoot-Hawley Tariff Act of 1930 to allow the president to make trade agreements with foreign countries <strong>“so that foreign markets will be made available.”</strong> The law aimed at <strong>“increasing the purchasing power of the American public”</strong> and <strong>“restoring the American standard of living.”<span class="citation" data-cites="ActAmendTariff1934-06-12"><sup>5</sup></span></strong> It enacted the idea of reciprocity; the US and another country would each agree to lower rates to improve trade between the two. It incorporated an idea of gradualism—in no case could the reduction in rate be more than fifty percent of the Smoot-Hawley rate.<span class="citation" data-cites="tasca1938"><sup>6</sup></span> And although it described bilateral agreements, when those agreements included most-favored-nation clauses—which was language ensuring that any nation signing an agreement would gain any advantage later secured by any other nation signing an agreement—the Roosevelt administration acquired the means to gradually liberalize trade with many parties.<span class="citation" data-cites="allen1953-03"><sup>7</sup></span> Within three years the administration negotiated sixteen agreements and more would soon follow, increasing trade among participating countries.<span class="citation" data-cites="tasca1938"><sup>8</sup></span></p>
<p>I want to focus now on the mechanism for reducing tariffs, and for reducing them gradually, which was as important as the general aim of lower tariffs.</p>
<p>Let me talk first about gradualism. Roosevelt appreciated the need for a gentle shift away from protectionism. As he said privately, protectionism might be <strong>“all right today”</strong> but he opposed it <strong>“as a long-term policy,”</strong> saying, <strong>“in the long run it would work against us and our world trade and our industry.”<span class="citation" data-cites="rauchwayWinterWarHoover2018"><sup>9</sup></span></strong> He had similar views about monetary policy; he wanted to devalue the dollar gradually.<span class="citation" data-cites="rauchwayMoneyMakersHow2015"><sup>10</sup></span> In both cases he knew he wanted to make an ultimately dramatic change in the cost of doing business but he wanted to make it without too much disruption to business plans then in effect. So gradualism was the order of the day.</p>
<p>Second, as to the mechanism: the Reciprocal Trade Agreements Act delegated tariff power to the president, who would strike deals with other countries. The point of delegating this power to the president was to lower tariffs. By 1934 it was clear Congress had great difficulty doing so.<span class="citation" data-cites="tasca1938"><sup>11</sup></span></p>
<p>When Congress made tariffs, as both William McKinley and Herbert Hoover found to their disappointment, lawmaking quickly became an exercise in log-rolling—you vote for a tariff increase protecting industry in my district; I’ll vote for a tariff increase protecting industry in your district. Log-rolling tended generally to produce higher rates, as every lawmaker looked to get protection for his district. The tariff became a mechanism for providing constituent service and patronage—a domestic, rather than an international, policy, even though it worked by affecting international trade.</p>
<p>By the time of Smoot-Hawley, protectionist lawmakers described log-rolling not as an unfortunate side effect but as an essential feature of tariff-making. As Reed Smoot said, <strong>“the tariff is a domestic matter, and an American tariff must be framed and put into force by the American Congress and administration. No foreign country has a right to interfere.”<span class="citation" data-cites="lake1988"><sup>12</sup></span></strong></p>
<p>The reciprocal mechanism begun in 1934 let the president reach agreements with foreign countries—much against what Smoot said—and let him do so in broad consultation with various experts throughout the executive branch.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./trade2.drawio.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Click to enlarge; diagram after Tasca, 55."><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/aha_tariffs/trade2.drawio.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="250" alt="Click to enlarge; diagram after Tasca, 55."></a></p>
<figcaption>Click to enlarge; diagram after Tasca, 55.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The handout has an organization chart of the trade agreements mechanism set up under the Roosevelt administration.<span class="citation" data-cites="tasca1938"><sup>13</sup></span> As you can see, there are some state department committees, and many more interdepartmental committees—including representatives from commerce, agriculture, treasury, and so on.</p>
<p>This broad range of committees served not only to get input from a variety of sources—thus ensuring everyone got heard—but also to diffuse, and actually to obscure, the process by which a decision got made. A politician or business representative might look at this chart and say to himself, well, this is a nightmare; I don’t know who to lobby—and that’s exactly the point. There were lots of people you could talk to but shy of the president himself, you didn’t know who’s making decisions. And even if you did have access to the president, having this elaborate mechanism allowed the president to say, well, you know, I have multiple, carefully composed expert recommendations; I can’t very well go against them.<span class="citation" data-cites="tasca1938"><sup>14</sup></span> So these economic experts could toil away, untroubled by influence, and recommend action to the president. John Maynard Keynes famously hoped that economics would one day become as dull as dentistry; he meant this as a compliment to his future profession—that it would become boringly professional, rather than heated and political.<span class="citation" data-cites="keynes1933"><sup>15</sup></span> The Reciprocal Trade Agreements Act (like, as it happens, much of the New Deal) embodied this view.</p>
<p>This emphasis on gradual movement, international agreement, and a mechanism centered in the executive but informed by an array of expert advisors had the intended effect of reaching generally lower tariffs and increasing world trade. By the end of the Roosevelt administration in 1945, twenty-eight agreements were in place and the fifty percent limit in rate reductions had been nearly reached. Congress then extended the authority and allowed another fifty percent reduction.<span class="citation" data-cites="goldstein1993"><sup>16</sup></span></p>
<p>Having the president make international agreements shielded legislators from having to vote for a tariff reduction. And it allowed them to reap the benefits of increased exports from their district. It allowed lower rates and increased global trade. Moreover, the real and widespread benefits to the US economy of increased exports helped forge a bipartisan consensus on free trade.<span class="citation" data-cites="bailey1997-04 haggard1988 lowi1964-07"><sup>17</sup></span></p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Franklin D. Roosevelt, <span>“Sioux City, IA - Campaign Address,”</span> September 29, 1932, 17, Master Speech File, FDRL.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Helmut Norpoth, <span>“The American Voter in 1932: Evidence from a Confidential Survey,”</span> <em>PS</em> 52, no. 1 (January 2019): 17.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Herbert Hoover, <span>“Address at Madison Square Garden,”</span> in <em>Public Papers of the Presidents of the United States</em>, <em>Herbert Hoover, 1932–1933</em> (Washington, DC: Government Printing Office, 1977), 669.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Eric Rauchway, <em>Winter War: Hoover, Roosevelt, and the First Clash Over the New Deal</em> (New York: Basic Books, 2018), 233.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p><span>“An Act to Amend the Tariff Act of 1930,”</span> Pub. L. No. 316, § 350, 48 US Statutes at Large 943 (1934).↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn6"><p>This was the first measure allowing for presidential negotiation with another country to mutual benefit; the Smoot-Hawley Tariff had previously allowed for what Henry Tasca called “the penalty type of tariff bargaining,” allowing the president to impose punitive tariffs on a country discriminating against the United States. <em>The Reciprocal Trade Policy of the United States: A Study in Trade Philosophy</em> (Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1938), 41.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn7"><p>William R. Allen, <span>“The International Trade Philosophy of Cordell Hull, 1907–1933,”</span> <em>American Economic Review</em> 43, no. 1 (March 1953): 114.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn8"><p>Tasca, <em>Reciprocal Trade Policy</em>, 266, 271.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn9"><p>Roosevelt was speaking here to Hearst emissary Ed Coblentz in January 1933. Rauchway, <em>Winter War</em>, 176.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn10"><p>Eric Rauchway, <em>The Money Makers: How Roosevelt and Keynes Ended the Depression, Defeated Fascism, and Secured a Prosperous Peace</em> (New York: Basic Books, 2015), 82.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn11"><p>Tasca finds only three of 21 previous efforts to negotiate reciprocal treaties, which required Senate approval, succeeded. <em>Reciprocal Trade Policy</em>, 43.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn12"><p>David A. Lake, <em>Power, Protection, and Free Trade: International Sources of U.S. Commercial Strategy, 1887–1939</em> (Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 1988), 192.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn13"><p>The diagram is derived from one in Tasca, <em>Reciprocal Trade Policy</em>, 55.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn14"><p>For an indication that this effect was intended, see the discussion in Tasca, <em>Reciprocal Trade Policy</em>, 50–66, including the observation that the membership of many committees was not publicized.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn15"><p>John Maynard Keynes, <em>Essays in Persuasion</em> (London: Macmillan and Co., Limited, 1933), 373.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn16"><p>Judith Goldstein, <em>Ideas, Interests, and American Trade Policy</em> (Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 1993), 162–64.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn17"><p>Michael A. Bailey, Judith Goldstein, and Barry R. Weingast, <span>“The Institutional Roots of American Trade Policy: Politics, Coalitions, and International Trade,”</span> <em>World Politics</em> 49, no. 3 (April 1997): 309–38; Stephan Haggard, <span>“The Institutional Foundations of Hegemony: Explaining the Reciprocal Trade Agreements Act of 1934,”</span> <em>International Organization</em> 42, no. 1 (Winter 1988): 91–119; Theodore J. Lowi, <span>“American Business, Public Policy, Case-Studies, and Political Theory,”</span> <em>World Politics</em> 16, no. 4 (July 1964): 677–93.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Historiography</category>
  <category>Tariffs</category>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>Reciprocal Tariff Agreements Act of 1934</category>
  <category>Smoot-Hawley</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/aha_tariffs/aha_tariffs.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Teaching the Depression and New Deal</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/oah_mag/oah_mag.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The editors of the Organization of American Historians’ magazine, <em>The American Historian,</em> asked me to contribute an essay on the Great Depression and the New Deal to a series on “US History at 250.” I tried to get all the salient historiographical points into 2500 or so words. You can find it <a href="https://www.oah.org/tah/america-in-a-world-at-war/the-great-depression-and-the-new-deal/">here;</a> this is how it begins:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Even with COVID and (for the older among us) the 2008 recession in our memories, the Great Depression remains a catastrophe whose scale and scope we have trouble imagining. Historians tasked with conveying it to others try to illustrate scale with statistics, though numbers imply a spurious precision our sources cannot wholly support; indicating its scope requires a grasp of the interconnected national and world economies, and how that web of links, so apparently robust, could be so suddenly swept aside and afterward, only painstakingly rebuilt.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It carries on in an effort to offer contemporary points of comparison or contrast, with the idea that might help non-specialists teach it, if they find themselves wanting to do so. <img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/oah_mag/fsa_camp.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt="Woman at the community laundry on Saturday, Farm Security Administration labor camnp, Robstown, TX; Arthur Rothstein for the FSA. Library of Congress."></p>
<p>The other essays, covering the period of both world wars, might be worth your while too: they’re by Jennifer D. Keane, Lynne Dumenil, Natalie Mendoza, Viola Burlew, and Tom Zeiler.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Historiography</category>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/oah_mag/oah_mag.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Hitler Diaries</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/samoans/samoans.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>When up for a lecturership at Oxford in 1998, I received notice to report for an interview at the Indian Institute, then the home of the Faculty of Modern History, in the Trevor-Roper Room. I possessed the maturity to refrain from saying aloud, though not to refrain from thinking, “Are we sure it’s really the Trevor-Roper Room, and not a tea-stained forgery?” Which is a very unfair thing to think about a distinguished historian, but in my defense I was young and the episode of the faked Hitler diaries, during which Hugh Trevor-Roper was briefly taken in by the forgeries, tea-stained to give the appearance of age, was fresh in memory. It might have been the first time I thought about what professional historians got up to.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/samoans/indian_inst.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The Oxford Indian Institute, at the bottom of the Broad Street, next to the Sheldonian Theatre. Photo by me.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The BBC has a good article looking back at the story of <a href="https://www.bbc.com/culture/article/20250414-the-fake-hitler-diaries-that-fooled-rupert-murdoch">the Hitler diaries forgery of 1983.</a> Despite the <code>url</code>, there, it looks like Murdoch was not so much fooled as determined to have a story for the Sunday <em>Times.</em> And I felt bad for Lord Dacre, aka Trevor-Roper:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“I must say as a historian, I regret that the normal methods of historical verification have, perhaps necessarily, been to some extent sacrificed to the requirements of the journalistic scoop,” he said.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This episode was also the occasion for one of my favorite comic strips of all time, the Bloom County bit in which Milo forges (for fun and a news sensation) the diaries of Margaret Mead.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/samoans/samoans.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Milo Bloom and Steve Dallas watching a tv report about Margaret Mead’s diaries. When the announcer reaches the zinger, Milo—who knows about it because he is the forger—says simultaneously with the anchor, “Man, those Samoans are a surly bunch.”</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It was, and remains, a delight to me that this strip riffed on a contemporary news story in such a way as to make a joke which required you to know enough about Margaret Mead’s <em>Coming of Age in Samoa</em> to laugh.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Historiography</category>
  <category>Forgery</category>
  <category>Oxford</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/samoans/samoans.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Historians and the isolationists: polling</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/polling_ww2/polling_ww2.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/williams_hoover/williams_hoover.html">previously</a> said the professional opinion of mine most likely to have me like—</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/polling_ww2/flynn_swords.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>A still of Flynn from the movie <em>Tangled,</em> standing blithely in the center of a circle of swords pointed at his face; it is a popular meme for designating unpopular opinions.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>is that scholars of US foreign policy are far too kind to interwar isolationists. In that post I talked about William Appleman Williams, who is long dead. What about modern scholars?</p>
<p>Well, let’s take <a href="https://networks.h-net.org/group/discussions/20030100/h-diplorjissf-roundtable-review-15-39-connelly-declassification-engine">a claim by Matthew Connelly:</a> that Franklin D. Roosevelt deceived the American people in the run-up to the war. I’m not going to tackle all the elements of this claim in this post, just this one part about what Americans generally thought about the war.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I do not know if there was any alternative to deceiving the American people, who largely opposed what they perceived to be a war of choice.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Connelly’s claim here is similar to <a href="https://libertiesjournal.com/articles/war-and-the-liberal-hegemony/">Robert Kagan’s;</a> both believe the Roosevelt administration forced this “war of choice” on a reluctant American people for a greater good.</p>
<p>How much did the American people actually oppose US entry to the war, though?</p>
<p>Over the course of 1941, polls frequently asked Americans “If you were asked to vote on the question of the United States entering the war against Germany and Italy [sometimes adding Japan], how would you vote—to go into the war, or to stay out of the war?”</p>
<p>On this question, opinion only very slightly shifts during the year in the direction of “go into the war.” Americans overwhelmingly answer they would vote to “stay out.”</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./vote.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Click to enlarge: A graph showing support for going into the war in the middle 20 percent, and for staying out in the range of 70 percent. Data from Roper Center iPoll."><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/polling_ww2/vote.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Click to enlarge: A graph showing support for going into the war in the middle 20 percent, and for staying out in the range of 70 percent. Data from Roper Center iPoll."></a></p>
<figcaption>Click to enlarge: A graph showing support for going into the war in the middle 20 percent, and for staying out in the range of 70 percent. Data from Roper Center iPoll.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>If that was all the information you had, you would say Americans overwhelmingly opposed US entry to the war.</p>
<p>But: over the same period, pollsters also often asked, “Which of these two things do you think is more important—that this country keep out of war, or that Germany be defeated, even at the risk of our getting into the war?”</p>
<p>On this question, Americans quite consistently answered they thought Germany needed to be defeated, even at the risk of US entry to the war. There’s not really that much of a shift.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./germany.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Click to enlarge: A graph showing support for the defeat of Germany, even at the risk of war, running in the range of 65 percent, as against the US keeping out running in the range of 30-ish percentage points."><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/polling_ww2/germany.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Click to enlarge: A graph showing support for the defeat of Germany, even at the risk of war, running in the range of 65 percent, as against the US keeping out running in the range of 30-ish percentage points."></a></p>
<figcaption>Click to enlarge: A graph showing support for the defeat of Germany, even at the risk of war, running in the range of 65 percent, as against the US keeping out running in the range of 30-ish percentage points.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>So considering this second result, it looks like Americans were broadly in favor of the US doing what it could to ensure German defeat, even—explicitly—at the risk of the US getting into the war. In other words, respondents favored what was pretty much the Roosevelt administration’s policy.</p>
<p>You can if you like add one question asked at the start of November 1941: “If our present leaders and military advisors say that the only way to defeat Germany is for this country to go into the war, would you be in favor of this country’s going into the war against Germany?” To that, 70 percent of respondents said “yes,” as against only 24 percent “no” and 6 percent “no opinion.” It appears, then, that respondents were willing to go along with the Roosevelt administration’s judgment about the necessity of US entry to war to defeat Germany.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Historiography</category>
  <category>Isolationists</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/polling_ww2/polling_ww2.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Andrew Hickey, practitioner of old-school American Studies (laudatory)</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/hickey/hickey_500.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Even though I am not old enough to have encountered the mid-century American Studies scholars when they were flourishing or in many cases, when they were even still alive, the books that brought me into my own career in US history belong to that tradition: <em>American Humor,</em> by Constance Rourke, or <em>Love and Death in the American Novel,</em> by Leslie Fiedler, say. This work is not necessarily <em>right,</em> per se, but it is certainly thought-provoking and inasmuch as that is the point of scholarship, <em>good.</em><sup>1</sup> In most cases it tells you things you didn’t already know and maybe more important it works by making connections which wouldn’t have occurred to a reader not as deeply steeped in the sources as the writer—which is essentially every reader.</p>
<p>Andrew Hickey does the podcast, “A History of Rock Music in 500 Songs,” which you have probably already had recommended to you but maybe not because it plainly belongs to that tradition, into which we could also throw Richard Hofstadter, David M. Potter, John Hope Franklin, and some of the other cast of characters from <a href="https://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/P/bo196664682.html">Nick Witham’s recent scholarship.</a></p>
<p>Hickey is an admirable cultural historian in part because he lets you know how he <a href="https://500songs.com/podcast/song-177-never-learn-not-to-love-by-the-beach-boys-part-one/#more-2348">works:</a></p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>connections are <em>everywhere</em>. We only see them when we’re looking for them. And they only have the meaning that we impose. Now, this happens to be a big chunk of the way I tell stories — and indeed it’s an important part of the way <em>anyone</em> tells stories. You look for patterns and connections that other people haven’t seen before, and present them to the audience. Sometimes those patterns have actual meaning that sheds light on the history, other times they’re just interesting resonances and coincidences that make for an interesting story.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He also revises himself in light of what he finds to be <a href="https://500songs.com/2024/12/10/next-episode-coming-soon/">persuasive evidence:</a></p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>when checking a minor detail I discovered a book published this year, after I’d bought the books I used for the research, which showed that everything in the first half of the episode—everything that had been published in every book on Huddie Ledbetter, who is the focus of that first half—was badly mistaken. I had to totally scrap a completed script and redo the research from scratch.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And he has wonderful, no-nonsense <a href="https://500songs.com/podcast/song-177-never-learn-not-to-love-by-the-beach-boys-part-3-mister-can-you-give-me-some-direction/#more-2421">asides:</a></p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>[John] Lomax was born in Mississippi in 1867, two years after the ending of the Slaveholders’ Rebellion (later euphemised as the American Civil War)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The podcast is a delight; I gather there is also now <a href="https://books2read.com/u/mVrzYM">a book.</a></p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>I think much of it is also wrong, but in interesting ways, because it addresses interesting questions, and therefore merits engagement.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Historiography</category>
  <category>American Studies</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/hickey/hickey_500.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 13 Apr 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
