<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>a necessitous blog</title>
<link>https://erauchway.github.io/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://erauchway.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>A blog full of pedantry about the era of the Roosevelt administration, 1933--1945</description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.340</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>The Holocaust as a historians’ problem</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/epist/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The effort to <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/stone/">quantify the dead of the Holocaust</a> inspires a queasy feeling, as of dealing with the genuinely obscene, but it is a necessary methodological substitute for the evidentiary absence at the center of the event: that is to say, we have no representative subjective account of it. That is to say, we have survivors’ accounts but, as Primo Levi (among others) points out, survivors’ accounts are not representative. The representative Jewish experience of the Holocaust was death.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I must repeat: we, the survivors, are not the true witnesses. . . . We survivors are not only an exiguous but also an anomalous minority: we are those who by their prevarications or abilities or good luck did not touch bottom. Those who did so, those who saw the Gorgon, have not returned to tell about it or have returned mute, but they are the ‘Muslims,’ the submerged, the complete witnesses, the ones whose deposition would have a general significance. They are the rule, we are the exception.<span class="citation" data-cites="leviDrownedSaved1986"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>It is a shocking thing to consider: that, for example, <a href="https://www.yadvashem.org/holocaust/about/fate-of-jews/poland.html#narrative_info">of the 3.3 million Jews who lived in Poland in 1939, perhaps 380,000 survived</a> the war. Historians generally use first-hand testimony of great historical events as an indication of what it must have been like to experience the event. A survivor’s testimony cannot serve that purpose when the dead outnumber the survivors by something like 7.6 to 1.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/epist/hol_bef_aft.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Estimated presence of Jewish population in Europe and surrounding areas before and after the Nazi era.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Primo Levi, <em>The Drowned and the Saved</em>, trans. Raymond Rosenthal (New York: Simon &amp; Schuster, 1986), 70.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Holocaust</category>
  <category>Historiography</category>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/epist/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 24 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Time and rate of the Holocaust</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/stone/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Of the effort to arrive at a number of Jews murdered in the Nazi death camps, Yitzhak Arad writes,</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>There were never any records of the killing activities in these camps: the entire operation was <em>Geheime Reichssache—</em>a secret matter of the Reich, and any written documentation on what was actually taking place in the death camps would have exposed the secret. The deportation orders and reports on their implementation were sometimes written down but usually given orally. Even the SS men who served in the camps were utterly prohibited from counting the number of Jews they murdered, or even to discuss the matter. SS <em>Unterscharführer</em> Robert Jührs, when asked at the Belzec war crimes trial on the number of Jews murdered in the camp responded: “In the matter of this question, permit me to emphasize that we were explicitly prohibited from discussing numbers.”<span class="citation" data-cites="aradOperationReinhardDeath2018"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>But the Germans used the railways to deport Jews from the Polish towns and ghettos to Belzec, Sobibor, and Treblinka to be killed, and railways run on bureaucracy; they must know when trains leave and how many cars are on them. Arad was able to discover records of 480 or so such trains and, knowing that “the Germans pushed 100 to 150 people into each freight car,” arrive at an estimate of their burden.<span class="citation" data-cites="aradOperationReinhardDeath2018"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
<p>Auschwitz presents a trickier problem because it was not solely a death camp. Deportees arriving in the camp went through a selection process from which some were registered and sent to labor; the unregistered were sent to their death. One must therefore look at the number of deportees and the number registered and in most cases, as Robert Jan van Pelt writes, “All the deportees were either killed on arrival, and therefore not registered; or admitted to the camp and registered.”<span class="citation" data-cites="vanpeltCaseAuschwitzEvidence2016"><sup>3</sup></span> He cites the work of Franciszek Piper, who in the 1980s began working from previously compiled documentation and estimates to arrive at reliable figures.<span class="citation" data-cites="piperEstimatingNumberDeportees1991"><sup>4</sup></span></p>
<p>In 2019, Lewi Stone put together a data series including Arad’s and Piper’s figures, together with some more representing Jews killed by the <em>Einsatzgrüppen</em> during the invasion of the Soviet Union (the “Shoah by bullet”) to come up with a time series showing the number of Jews murdered in the death camps as against Auschwitz and by shooting. Stone’s concern is the intensity of this genocide as against others, but for the purpose of teaching World War II, it’s more useful for showing the timing of the Holocaust and its relation to the other events of the war. Stone’s article doesn’t have his raw data, but <a href="https://theconversation.com/quantifying-the-holocaust-measuring-murder-rates-during-the-nazi-genocide-108984">a piece he wrote for The Conversation</a> does.<span class="citation" data-cites="stoneQuantifyingHolocaustHyperintense2019"><sup>5</sup></span> From it one can make a chart such as the below.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/stone/stone_holocaust.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Chart showing number and date of Jews murdered in various locations and manners during the Holocaust, using data from Lewi Stone.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Yitzhak Arad, <em>The Operation Reinhard Death Camps: Belzec, Sobibor, Treblinka</em>, revised and expanded (Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2018), 435.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Arad, <em>Operation Reinhard</em>, 436.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Robert Jan van Pelt, <em>The Case for Auschwitz: Evidence from the Irving Trial</em> (Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2016), 113.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Franciscek Piper, <span>“Estimating the Number of Deportees to and Victims of the Auschwitz-Birkenau Camp,”</span> <em>Yad Vashem Studies</em> 21 (1991): 49--103.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>Lewi Stone, <span>“Quantifying the Holocaust: Hyperintense Kill Rates During the Nazi Genocide,”</span> <em>Science Advances</em> 5, no. 1 (2019): 1--10.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Holocaust</category>
  <category>Historiography</category>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/stone/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 22 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Travel by map</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/travel_map/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>In <em>The Muppets</em> (2011) the almost fully reunited gang, together with Jason Segel and Amy Adams, need to travel to France from the United States to find Miss Piggy. They have a car and (robot; don’t ask) driver; they discuss how they can get there from here.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/yIQKVITyaMI" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>Like much Muppet humor, this joke asks the viewer to have a knowledge of show business tropes, of which “travel by map” is one. Many of us will probably associate it with Indiana Jones; here’s what we see when, in <em>Raiders of the Lost Ark,</em> Indy leaves Marshall College (University of the Pacific in Stockton, CA in real life and apparently fictionally located in Northern California as well) to find Marian in Nepal, traveling by flying boat.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/travel_map/raiders.gif" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Travel by map in <em>Raiders of the Lost Ark.</em></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Of course, as with the Muppets, much that is in Indiana Jones is pastiche and homage, and the travel by map sequence serves the same purpose here as it did thirty years later: nudging the viewer to say see, this is like those old-timey movies. But which ones?</p>
<p>The best known example I can think of is <em>Casablanca.</em> At the beginning, the narrator tells us about the refugee trail that leads people fleeing Nazi-occupied Europe to the Vichy-controlled city. As he talks, we see their path, shifting from globe to map.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/travel_map/casab.gif" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Travel by map in <em>Casablanca.</em></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I don’t know where this trope originated but I wouldn’t be surprised to learn it came from, or became common during, the years around World War II. As Susan Schulten <a href="https://newrepublic.com/article/117835/richard-edes-harrison-reinvented-mapmaking-world-war-2-americans">points out,</a> more Americans saw more maps of more kinds because of the war. Many had never before been overseas or even had to think about it much.<span class="citation" data-cites="schultenGeographicalImaginationAmerica2002"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
<p><em>Casablanca</em> of course dramatizes the American journey from isolation to intervention in the character arc of Rick Blaine. Maybe it’s also the first real popular instance of the geographical awareness that made that arc possible.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Susan Schulten, <em>The Geographical Imagination in America, 1880-1950</em> (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2002).↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Geography</category>
  <category>Historiography</category>
  <category>Movies</category>
  <category>Muppets</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/travel_map/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The literature of the Irving case</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/irving/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>David Irving sued the historian Deborah Lipstadt for libel in 1996, and lost in 2000, when an English judge’s opinion held that Lipstadt was justified in her characterization of Irving in her book <em>Denying the Holocaust.</em> It was one of the most exciting and high-stakes things to happen to historiography during my professional career; that I happened to be teaching history in England at the time magnified it as an event in my imagination.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/irving/large_HU_059545_A.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">SS officers of Auschwitz and Belsen awaiting trial at Lüneberg, 1945. Imperial War Museum.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Lipstadt wrote a book about it, <em>History on Trial,</em> but in this post I want to focus on the books written by historians called to give expert opinions in the case, because it seems to me they were asked to do something unusual for professional historians, but perhaps helpful.</p>
<p>For a while I used to assign graduate students Richard Evans’s <em>Telling Lies About Hitler</em> because it echoed his title <em>Telling the Truth About History,</em> and tied into his broader concerns about the historical profession.<span class="citation" data-cites="evansTellingLiesHitler2002"><sup>1</sup></span> But I came to feel that this feature, which attracted me, was making the book less good for graduate students; Evans may perhaps assume too much of readers, expecting them to know his particular position regarding evidence and argumentation, and to be too aware of the arguments he opposes.</p>
<p>But what his book has, and shares with the others, is an awareness that what the trial asked of historians is not what ordinary scholarship asks of historians—although maybe it should: an aggressively forensic approach to developing the evidence for a case and establishing, point by point, the narrative we know. As Robert Jan van Pelt says in his book,</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I was to write a report on the evidence of our knowledge about Auschwitz fifty-five years after the world had first learned of the atrocities in that camp, amid a society that had reached a consensus about what happened at Auschwitz.<span class="citation" data-cites="vanpeltCaseAuschwitzEvidence2016"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the crucible of a legal case, what we think we know must be, if not discarded, then picked carefully apart to rediscover its basis. Van Pelt’s book, <em>The Case for Auschwitz,</em> seems to me now the most useful of the three, because he explicitly develops the nature of the problem he, and other expert witnesses, faced. He returns—as I think one should—to Marc Bloch for a discussion of the nature of evidence and historical proof.</p>
<p>The third expert book that is of occasional use to me as a teacher is Peter Longerich’s <em>Unwritten Order,</em> about Hitler’s personal role in the Holocaust. Perhaps we have no document reading, “Dear Heinrich and Reinhard, Please go ahead and kill all the Jews, like we discussed. Kisses, Adolf.” But there is copious evidence of Hitler’s involvement in the evolution of the Final Solution.<span class="citation" data-cites="longerichUnwrittenOrderHitler2003"><sup>3</sup></span> And this is a question students, perhaps immersed in “just-asking-questions” internet forums or worse, sometimes pose in class.</p>
<p>Karl Jaspers has what I think is a funny line:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>We are always ready to flee from creative work into that which is automatic. On days when the savant makes no progress in his researches, he is still able to give an expert opinion.<span class="citation" data-cites="jaspersOriginGoalHIstory2021"><sup>4</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>But as these books show, there is nothing automatic about the best expert opinions.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Richard J. Evans, <em>Telling Lies About Hitler: The Holocaust, History, and the David Irving Trial</em> (London: Verso, 2002), the American edition is called <em>Lying About Hitler,</em> which is less helpful in illustrating the point.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Robert Jan van Pelt, <em>The Case for Auschwitz: Evidence from the Irving Trial</em> (Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2016), 100.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Peter Longerich, <em>The Unwritten Order: Hitler’s Role in the Final Solution</em> (Stroud (UK): Tempus, 2003).↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Karl Jaspers, <em>The Origin and Goal of HIstory</em>, trans. Michael Bullock (London: Routledge, 2021), 120.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Historiography</category>
  <category>Holocaust</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/irving/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ray Moley as a source</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/moley/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Historians often rely on Raymond Moley’s memoirs for accounts of the early New Deal.<span class="citation" data-cites="moleySevenYears1939 moleyFirstNewDeal1966"><sup>1</sup></span> I have been skeptical of leaning too hard on these sources: memoirs written after the fact are fallible because memory is fallible; moreover, Moley left the administration because he disagreed with Roosevelt’s policies and he came to disagree with them even more, ultimately contributing to Barry Goldwater’s speeches, and so this rupture colored his recollection. But most of all, his memoirs are like all memoirs “intentional,” to use Marc Bloch’s term; as historians we generally prefer sources that serve as “witnesses in spite of themselves.” That is, Moley (like all memoirists) composed his memoirs and in that act of composition made decisions in keeping with his intentions, seeking to influence historical narrative. We’d rather have a document written in 1933 whose author didn’t necessarily mean it to see the light of day, which was supposed to communicate something of importance in 1933, and which therefore unintentionally bears witness when we look at it now.<span class="citation" data-cites="blochHistorianCraft1953"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/moley/moley.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Raymond Moley (right) greets Senator William Borah (R-ID) as Moley arrives in Congress to testify in opposition to the president’s judicial reform bill, 1937. Library of Congress.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I was able to look at Moley’s papers in the Hoover Institution at Stanford some years ago. They are full of witnesses in spite of themselves, but they also include evidence of Moley’s intention to shape the historical record, which is perhaps more than anything else what put me on alert as to his reliability. Notably, Moley’s papers include the diary of his assistant, Celeste Jedel, covering January 1 to August 1, 1933—essentially, the short period when Moley was of at least some consequence to the Roosevelt administration. Moley directed that this diary be kept sealed until 1976, and included a covering memorandum to researchers, which he wrote in 1972 on his Phoenix, Arizona, stationery.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The diary which accompanies this statement was written by my assistant, Celeste Jedel. . . . It was written at my direction. . . . at the end of every day I explained to her what I wanted recorded in the diary, telling her whom I had seen and where I had been in my periods out of the office. . . . She was a brilliant girl and had a photographic memory, so that the entries are all correct, but since she was only 22 years old, her judgment about what should go into the diary was sometimes faulty. In other words, she included certain comments of her own which did not represent my opinion. . . . I would not have these exposed now since some of the individuals are living, and in other cases there are relatives. I did not agree with her evaluations.<sup>3</sup></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This note says a lot, I think, especially when read together with the diary and with knowledge of Moley’s general attitude toward the early Roosevelt administration. Moley really seems to want to have it both ways: the diary belongs in his papers because he directed it be written but also it includes things he didn’t say should go in it. He didn’t agree with what she said but she was brilliant and had a photographic memory. Also the entries are all correct! I think one can parse this passage so that these things are all true at once, but it requires hard work, and it also requires you to believe that Moley’s grasp of the past from forty years onward be better than Jedel’s contemporary commentary. It is much more likely that Moley in 1972 was uncomfortable with some of the candid, and true, observations that Jedel made in 1933, which often include tart evaluations of other people in the administration, not all of which seem to a judicious historian at all inconsistent with what we know of Moley’s opinions.</p>
<p>Whether the historian reading Moley’s covering note accepts, a historian should certainly understand it as an indication that Moley remained, decades later, deeply concerned with how he appeared in 1933. He wanted that moment remembered, to be sure, because it was the moment when he was nearest to power and maybe exercised a little of it. But also he wanted it remembered in a particular way; he was ambivalent later about what he did and said then. Which is maybe no different than any other historical figure, but Moley’s note serves as an unusually express reminder to the historian to take care with Moley’s intentional versions of the historical record.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Moley’s memoirs are Raymond Moley, <em>After Seven Years</em> (New York: Harper &amp; Brothers, 1939); Raymond Moley and Elliot A. Rosen, <em>The First New Deal</em> (New York: Harcourt, Brace &amp; World, 1966).↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Marc Bloch, <em>The Historian’s Craft</em>, trans. Peter Putnam (New York: Vintage, 1953), 60–61.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Covering note to Celeste Jedel Diary, Raymond Moley Papers, Hoover Institution, Stanford, CA.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>Raymond Moley</category>
  <category>Historiography</category>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/moley/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Oppenheimer and the horseshoe</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/oppenheimer/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The new trailer for Christopher Nolan’s <em>Oppenheimer,</em> which press coverage says is based on the Kai Bird and Martin Sherwin biography <em>American Prometheus,</em> dropped today.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/uYPbbksJxIg" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>I don’t know anything about Nolan’s movie other than what appears in the trailer, but I’ve seen enough Nolan to know that the politics in his movies can appear quite conservative. Conversely, I reviewed the Bird and Sherwin book when it came out, and I know it is not conservative. But if there’s one area where the modern US right and left meet, it’s on the subject of World War II.</p>
<p>Indeed, one might without too much exaggeration say that the Cold War scholarly left largely adopted the wartime right’s critique of the Roosevelt administration. To prove this statement fully would take more space than this post but I will cite in support of it the Cold War historian William Appleman Williams’s <a href="https://www.nybooks.com/articles/1970/11/05/what-this-country-needs/">enthusiastic summary</a> of Herbert Hoover’s thinking: “So right it shakes you.” I will also, even though it is not fully relevant here, provide Williams’s description of Hoover’s response to the Bonus Army, because it is hilarious:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For the feel of how Hoover reacted, do not waste your time ransacking the archives. Just listen to The Doors doing the first verse of “The Soft Parade.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Maybe quoting that is unfair to leftists who admire Hoover, but as I say, it is funny. Less funny is Williams’s conviction that somehow Hoover opposed “the empire” and therefore was a sage we should heed.</p>
<p>Anyway, without (in this post) talking about whether I think the shared right/left critique of Roosevelt is correct, I just want to note that this sharing is real, and this similarity is most visible in an analysis of the war’s end. As Marc Gallicchio’s excellent 2020 book <em>Unconditional</em> makes clear, for the New Dealers, the war was an ideological war, and one that had to be pursued to the bitter end. Fascism had to be defeated utterly, in Japan as it was in Germany. “The supporters of unconditional surrender were mostly liberal Democrats, and the opponents were not,” Gallicchio notes.<span class="citation" data-cites="gallicchioUnconditionalJapaneseSurrender2020"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
<p>By contrast, the American right wanted a swifter end to the war, which they had always thought was unnecessary, and merciful treatment of Japan so that it could serve as a bulwark against the Soviet Union. As Gallicchio points out, early critiques of the atomic bombings came from the political right, including from Hoover, from Douglas MacArthur, and from MacArthur aide and <a href="https://www.timesofisrael.com/new-book-deciphers-forgotten-intel-war-that-kept-the-nazis-from-the-holy-land/">actual wartime security risk</a> as well as later John Birch member Bonner Fellers. Hoover and MacArthur agreed that an earlier peace would, in the general’s words, “have avoided all our losses, the Atomic Bomb, and the entry of Russia into Manchuria.” Hoover went further; “the whole Japanese war was a madman’s desire to get into war.” Gallicchio notes too that on the postwar right, “it became an article of faith” that MacArthur had, in January 1945, told Roosevelt the United States did not need the Soviets to help finish the war—a story that “was later publicly revealed to be a bald-faced lie.”<span class="citation" data-cites="gallicchioUnconditionalJapaneseSurrender2020"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
<p>Within a few years of the war, Republicans eager to blame Democrats for Mao’s victory in China constructed a narrative in which the Roosevelt administration’s unwillingness to accept peace overtures from Japan had led to Soviet entry into the war against Japan and thus the triumph of communism in Asia. Gallicchio notes that this narrative was “patently ridiculous,” but it was widely accepted among “conspiratorially minded critics of Roosevelt.”<span class="citation" data-cites="gallicchioUnconditionalJapaneseSurrender2020"><sup>3</sup></span></p>
<p>Gallicchio goes on to note the appeal of this right-wing critique to the later left, citing Oliver Stone’s deployment of Hoover and MacArthur to assert that the Japanese were ready to surrender long before the use of the atomic bombs. And he also notes that “invoking the opinions of the two Roosevelt haters contributes little to our understanding of Japan’s willingness to surrender before August 1945.” But it does highlight the continuity of right-wing and left-wing criticisms of US wartime policy.<span class="citation" data-cites="gallicchioUnconditionalJapaneseSurrender2020"><sup>4</sup></span></p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Marc Gallicchio, <em>Unconditional: The Japanese Surrender in World War II</em> (New York: Oxford University Press, 2020), 209.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Gallicchio, <em>Unconditional</em>, 184–85.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Gallicchio, <em>Unconditional</em>, 194.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Gallicchio, <em>Unconditional</em>, 213.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>US strategy</category>
  <category>Unconditional surrender</category>
  <category>New Dealers at war</category>
  <category>Historiography</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/oppenheimer/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Pan Am for hemispheric defense</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/pan_am/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Shortly after the German invasion of France in June 1940, the Roosevelt administration authorized Pan American Airways to build and maintain airfields for the US military. The army and navy wanted a network of coastal bases to assure access to Natal, in the eastern part of Brazil—at the narrowest point of the Atlantic. The administration determined that signing a deal with Pan Am would be quicker than undertaking any more formal process, and as Congress had given Roosevelt a discretionary fund of $34 million for such purposes on June 11 in the naval appropriations act, it was swiftly done.<sup>1</sup> According to General George Marshall, these airfields were “more essential to out national defense than any other single matter.”<span class="citation" data-cites="connWesternHemisphereFramework1960"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/pan_am/pan_am.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Pan Am Mural from Rockefeller Center. Library of Congress.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>These bases would not, for the most part, be the bases acquired from Britain in trade for old US destroyers, though Pan Am played a small part in setting up the base in Trinidad. These would be new bases, in which Pan Am had its own interest—it wanted a network of runways that would suit the new stratoliner, the first passenger aircraft with a pressurized cabin, <a href="https://airandspace.si.edu/collection-objects/boeing-307-stratoliner-clipper-flying-cloud/nasm_A19730267000">which shared components with the B-17.</a></p>
<p>Settling on locations for the bases entailed some difficulties. The planners wanted one in Martinique, but the island’s Vichy proclivities made that impossible. The Vichy governor in French Guiana was a bit more obliging and worked with Pan Am in secret—until the Nazis kicked him out.</p>
<p>Although Pan Am made a slow start, the airfields ultimately proved vital, especially in managing traffic to and from Europe bound through Natal. Moreover, as Marshall said in April 1941, the network constituted an investment: “an asset to us for military use and for future trade relations. Anything we can do now toward providing airfields is an enduring thing and not a venture.”<span class="citation" data-cites="connWesternHemisphereFramework1960"><sup>3</sup></span></p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>54 Stat. 265.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Stetson Conn and Byron Fairchild, <em>The Western Hemisphere: The Framework of Hemispheric Defense</em>, vol. 12, part 1, United States Army in World War II (Washington, D.C.: Office of the Chief of Military History, 1960), 252.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Conn and Fairchild, <em>Framework</em>, 12, part 1:259.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>US strategy</category>
  <category>Pan Am</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/pan_am/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Franklin Roosevelt, budget-cutter</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/budgets/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Much as I crankily complain about e-texts (tldr; for scholarly use and for instruction they are not as accessible as they should be), we live in an age of wonderful online documents, including the US Treasury Bulletin, of which one may find the December 1940 number <a href="https://fraser.stlouisfed.org/title/treasury-bulletin-407/december-1940-6528">here.</a> And in that number one may find the Treasury’s own breakdown of the New Deal budgets, which I depict here in graphical format.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/budgets/budg2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">US budgets, 1933–1940 by Treasury categories, dividing “ordinary” from “New Deal” expenditures.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>During the 1932 campaign, Franklin Roosevelt tried (as candidates often do) to have his cake and eat it too—that is, to promise both that he would be more frugal than Herbert Hoover and that he would spend extraordinary sums on unemployment relief as part of his New Deal. Roosevelt gave a respectable cast to this pledge to have it both ways by distinguishing between the “ordinary” expenditures of the federal government, which he would cut, and the necessary emergency expenditures of the New Deal, which would grow as large as they must to provide relief. As he said in his speech on the budget in Pittsburgh, (<a href="http://www.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/_resources/images/msf/msf00570">transcript here</a>) under Hoover “our Federal Government has experienced unprecedented deficits,” which needed paying for in taxation, “a brake on any return to normal business activity.” He proposed therefore to cut the expenditures of the federal government—while excepting the emergency expenditures necessary for the New Deal:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>what I am talking about more especially tonight are the taxes which go to the ordinary costs of conducting government year in and year out—and that is where the question of extravagance comes in. There can be no extravagance when starvation is in question; but extravagance does apply to the mounting budget of the Federal Government in Washington during these past four years.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Roosevelt kept budget-cutting a priority, while also preserving this exception, once inaugurated. The first major New Deal measure after the banking and currency legislation was the Economy Act, which gave the president extraordinary powers to cut the budget. On March 24, 1933, just after the passage of the Economy Act, <a href="http://www.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/_resources/images/pc/pc0184.pdf">a reporter asked Roosevelt</a> if he would balance the budget, and the president gave an answer that hewed to the distinction, however inventive, he had made during the campaign.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/budgets/depends.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Press conference remarks distinguishing ordinary from emergency spending. FDRL</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As you can see from the chart, Roosevelt (through his budget-cutting deputy Lewis Douglas) used the Economy Act’s authority to reduce what he considered “ordinary” federal spending in his first budget, and the “ordinary” expenses of the government remained down through his first term. Of course, he more than made up for that drop with New Deal spending.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>Balanced budget</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/budgets/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Geolexigraph</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/geolexigraph/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Today’s fun source is the “Geolexigraph of the Neutrality Act of 1939,” in the Department of Commerce’s own journal, <em>Comparative Law Series,</em> of May 1940.<span class="citation" data-cites="perkinsGeolexigraphNeutralityAct1940"><sup>1</sup></span> The journal provided information to US businesses on how to navigate US laws and policy; this particular article included all manner of information from the Department of Commerce itself, the post office, the Department of State, the customs office, and various other entities on how not to run afoul of the neutrality act passed just after the beginning of World War II in Europe.</p>
<p>But beware! for the Commerce Department folks introduced an error into their reproduction of the president’s declaration of a combat area under the law, and two of the geographic points are swapped. The original authoritative source is in the Department of State’s own bulletin.<span class="citation" data-cites="ProclamationDefiningCombat1940"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
<p>And for yet more fun here is a map showing that same combat area.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/geolexigraph/zonemap.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Map of the north Atlantic and countries in Europe, Africa, and North America, including their status with respect to the war, as of about the end of 1940, including the combat area declared by presidential proclamation on April 10, 1940.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Samuel E. Perkins, <span>“Geolexigraph of the Neutrality Act of 1939,”</span> <em>Comparative Law Series</em> 3, no. 5 (May 1940): 241--285.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p><span>“Proclamation Defining Combat Area,”</span> <em>Department of State Bulletin</em> 2, no. 42 (April 13, 1940): 278--379.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>US strategy</category>
  <category>Neutrality</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/geolexigraph/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Basics of the Greer speech</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_speech/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Ultimately, what troubles me most about standard accounts of the <em>Greer</em> incident is the tendency to treat evidence showing the U-boat captain didn’t know the destroyer was a US ship as a gotcha for the Roosevelt administration. Roosevelt’s speech on the incident, and the policy he announced as a result, didn’t depend on the U-boat captain knowing <em>Greer</em> was a US ship; in fact, Roosevelt quite expressly said otherwise.</p>
<p>A transcript of the president’s remarks as delivered appear in the Master Speech File at the Roosevelt Library in the second folder on this address; <a href="http://www.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/_resources/images/msf/msf01445">big pdf link here.</a></p>
<p>Here’s what seems to me the most important passage, so far as the <em>Greer</em> incident itself goes:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_speech/speech.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Excerpt from the transcript of Roosevelt’s national broadcast of September 11, 1941, speech file 1381B, box 62, Master Speech File, FDRL.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Roosevelt does say before this passage that it was broad daylight and the destroyer was flying the American flag. Moreover he imputes to the U-boat commander the “deliberate design to sink her.”</p>
<p>But the key, so far as his argument goes, seems to me here: <em>if</em> the German U-boat saw <em>Greer</em> was a US ship and fired at her, that’s an act of war—but! if it <em>didn’t</em> see <em>Greer</em> and ascertain her identity, that’s “even more outrageous”; it’s “indiscriminate violence,” and even worse.</p>
<p>Thus Roosevelt’s argument does not hinge on the Germans’ knowing they were firing on a US ship. You’d never know it the way many historians talk about it. For example:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>In a fireside chat delivered on September 11, FDR deliberately distorted the details of the incident. He claimed that the <em>Greer’s</em> identity as a U.S. ship was unmistakable and that the German submarine fired first without warning. He went on to outline a Nazi design to abolish the freedom of the seas as a prelude to domination of the United States.<span class="citation" data-cites="schuesslerDeceptionDividendFDR2010"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>But Roosevelt’s speech didn’t, as I say, depend on <em>Greer’s</em> identity as a US ship. Much to the contrary; he says it’s actually worse if the U-boat didn’t know it. (Moreover, as previously noted, the Nazis <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_2_nazi/">absolutely did mean to abolish freedom of the seas as prelude to war with the United States.</a>)</p>
<p>Further: Roosevelt then goes on in the speech to outline a pattern. The Germans had previously sunk the US merchantman <em>Robin Moor,</em> the Panamanian ship <em>Sessa,</em> and the US merchant vessel <em>Steel Seafarer.</em> You could reasonably suppose the Germans didn’t particularly care whose ships they were sinking.</p>
<p>Indeed, historians now know—or should know, at any rate—that’s precisely the case, both in the specific case of the <em>Greer</em> and in general. In the National Archives, one may find a decrypted message from Lt. Fraatz, of U 652, to the German commander of submarines, dated September 5, 1941, explaining he had fired torpedoes at “DESTROYER, FLING [<em>sic</em>] UNKNOWN FLAG.”<span class="citation" data-cites="fraatz1941"><sup>2</sup></span> <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_4_facts_2/">Fraatz knew <em>Greer</em> wasn’t acting like a British ship.</a> <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_5_confusion/">He didn’t think it was a British ship.</a> He was puzzled by its behavior, and he didn’t know whose ship it was. But he fired on it anyway. Which is what Roosevelt described as “even more outrageous” than knowing it was a US ship.</p>
<p>Perhaps Fraatz, via the various communications channels of Raeder’s navy, absorbed the message given by Hitler earlier in the summer. On July 25, 1941, one of the many occasions when Hitler urged patience, awaiting the right moment to attack the United States, he said,</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>His original view has undergone no changes whatsoever. He would, however, like to avoid having the U.S.A. declare war while the Eastern Campaign is still in progress, also out of consideration for the Army which is involved in heavy combat. But he will never call a submarine commander to account if he torpedoes an American ship by mistake.<span class="citation" data-cites="FuehrerConferencesNaval1990"><sup>3</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>As I say, Fraatz’s specific behavior reflects this general carelessness. The <em>Greer</em> might have been an American ship; it might not. But there was no harm in shooting at it if it were. That’s precisely the view that Roosevelt objected to, describing it as “piracy.”</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>John M. Schuessler, <span>“The Deception Dividend: FDR’s Undeclared War,”</span> <em>International Security</em> 34, no. 4 (April 2010): 157, <span>https://doi.org/10.1162/isec.2010.34.4.133</span>.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Fraatz to ComSubs, September 5, 1941, Entry A1 9019 German Navy U-Boat Message Translation and Summaries, SRGN 2720, RG 457, National Archives and Records Administration.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p><em>Fuehrer Conferences on Naval Affairs, 1939--1945</em> (London: Greenhill Books, 1990), 222.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Greer</category>
  <category>US strategy</category>
  <category>Nazi strategy</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_speech/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Chiseling on Justice</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/jurisdiction/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The Roosevelt administration considered a series of methods to improve an obstructionist federal judiciary in the 1930s; its best known was the Judicial Reform Bill of 1937, which sought to increase the membership of the federal bench, but before that officials seriously considered the idea of “jurisdiction stripping,” or removing the Court’s right to hear certain kinds of cases.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/jurisdiction/https:/tile.loc.gov/storage-services/service/pnp/hec/39600/39637v.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Gino Ratti, sculptor, working on “Contemplation of Justice,” at the new Supreme Court Building, 1935. Library of Congress.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The US constitution, in Article III, grants only limited original jurisdiction to the Court—that is, cases in which the Court is the first resort. So for example, disputes between states come in the first place before the Supreme Court. It appellate jurisdiction—that is, cases that can come to the Court for appeal after decision elsewhere—is broader, including “all Cases, in Law and Equity, arising under the Constitution, the Laws of the United States, and Treaties made, or which shall be made, under their Authority”—but “with such Exceptions, and under such Regulations as the Congress shall make.”</p>
<p>This latter clause has been interpreted by the Court to allow Congress to remove certain classes of cases from the Court’s purview. The preeminent example was <a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/74/506"><em>Ex Parte McCardle</em> of 1868.</a></p>
<p>Officers of the Department of Justice considered this possibility fraught for various reasons but chiefly for a practical one:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>If the appellate jurisdiction of the Supreme Court were to be abolished, District Courts and Circuit Courts of Appeals would still be in a position to declare statutes unconstitutional if such questions arose in cases brought before them. A statute preventing the inferior courts from declaring statutes unconstitutional would itself be invalid, in view of the doctrine of <em>Marbury v. Madison.</em><span class="citation" data-cites="holtzoffMemorandumAttorneyGeneral1935"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>One has only to look at recent, conflicting decisions in federal districts to see this problem in action, such as in 2014 when <a href="https://www.glaad.org/blog/6th-circuit-court-appeals-upholds-ban-marriage-same-sex-couples">the Sixth Circuit upheld bans on marrying someone of the same gender, while other courts upheld it;</a> absent a final court of appeal, there might be no way to resolve such a conflict. This concern prevailed within the Roosevelt administration, which turned to expansion instead.</p>
<p>Scholars since then have suggested what <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/Moyn-Testimony.pdf">Samuel Moyn calls “channeling” or “fine-tuning” jurisdiction,</a> including requiring by statute a super-majority on the Court for invalidating a federal statute, or reassigning final jurisdiction for invalidating a federal statute to Congress itself, which would have to ratify a Supreme Court decision to strike down a federal law.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Alexander Holtzoff, <span>“Memorandum for the Attorney General,”</span> June 6, 1935, entry A1 112-B, file 235773, RG 60, National Archives and Records Administration.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>SCOTUS</category>
  <category>Judicial reform</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/jurisdiction/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Fearless finger</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/fearless/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Fiorello La Guardia, Federal Director of the Office of Civilian Defense and candidate for a third term as mayor of New York City on a Fusion ticket, in a photograph used in the <em>Saturday Evening Post</em> of September 6, 1941.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/fearless/IMG_5672.JPG" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">One of seven evocative portraits of La Guardia featured on the first page of “Fearless Fiorello” by William R. Conklin; this version is from an ad for the article that appeared in <em>Time,</em> because in the bound version of the <em>Saturday Evening Post</em> the photograph is too close to the gutter to be reproduced intact.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The article begins with a La Guardia-ism many people will know, but perhaps without the context. In February 1941, appearing before the Senate Foreign Relations Committee to testify in favor of Lend-Lease, La Guardia was asked about earlier remarks by Justice Herbert O’Brien of the Queens Domestic Relations Court, who told the committee that passing Lend-Lease would lead to racial conflict. One of the senators reminded the Little Flower he had appointed O’Brien. The mayor replied, “Senator . . . I have made a lot of good appointments, and I think I’m pretty good. But when I make a mistake—it’s a beaut!”<span class="citation" data-cites="conklinFearlessFiorello1941"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
<p>The article does not give context for the wordless remark depicted in the photograph.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>William R. Conklin, <span>“Fearless Fiorello,”</span> <em>Saturday Evening Post</em>, September 6, 1941, 12.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>La Guardia</category>
  <category>Civilian Defense</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/fearless/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A red herring in the fog of war</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_5_confusion/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_4_facts_2/">Hasselwander noted that</a> historians will sometimes say or suggest that Lt. Fraatz, commander of U 652, might have mistaken <em>Greer</em> for one of the Wickes-class destroyers the US traded to Britain in exchange for Western-hemisphere bases in the deal of September 1940, and thus a legitimate target; Hasselwander specifically cites Kurt Assman to this effect (<em>Nur Assmann erklärt, daß der Kommandant geglaubt habe, sein Verfolger sei einer der fünfzig amerikanischen Zerstörer, welche die Vereinigten Staaten ab September 1940 Großbritannienüberlassen hatten.</em>).<span class="citation" data-cites="hasselwanderUSZerstorerGreerUnd1962"><sup>1</sup></span> I’ll have more to say about destroyers-for-bases another time; for now, I’ll give this post over to a discussion of this possibility of mistaken identity.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_5_confusion/NH67637.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">The USS <em>Greer</em> sometime during the war; image mirrored for comparison. US Naval History and Heritage Command.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_5_confusion/large_000000.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">HMS <em>Newmarket,</em> one of the US destroyers of the same class as <em>Greer</em> traded to Britain in 1940. IWM.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>You can see above a photograph of the <em>Greer</em> and a photograph of one of her sister ships traded to Britain, which became HMS <em>Newmarket.</em> The question of whether <em>Greer</em> might have looked like one of these newly British ships was raised within a couple weeks of the incident, and <em>Time</em> magazine took it up, explaining that the <em>Greer</em> had been modified and therefore looked different from other, once-similar destroyers. It’s true, I think, that you can see this in these photos if you look: the forward stack has been changed, with a “spark screen” added; the stacks have been lowered, too. The guns are different. And of course, so is the livery. <a href="https://content.time.com/time/subscriber/article/0,33009,766028,00.html">Moreover, <em>Time</em> noted, the <em>Greer</em> was sailing on its own, as British destroyers did not.</a> It was, as we have seen, broad daylight—that is why Fraatz did not surface.</p>
<p>Still, I would concede that the two ships look quite similar and if I were looking through a U-boat periscope I might well not be able to tell the difference. Hasselwander notes further that there is no indication Fraatz thought he was looking at a British destroyer. (<em>Die verfügbaren Teile des Logbuchs von U652 deuten jedoch darauf hin, daß die Ähnlichkeit von Greer mit den England überlassenen Zerstörern Fraatz nicht aufgefallen ist.</em>)<span class="citation" data-cites="hasselwanderUSZerstorerGreerUnd1962"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
<p>Moreover, to repeat again what we noted in <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_4_facts_2/">the earlier post,</a> Fraatz <em>did</em> notice that the <em>Greer</em> was not <em>acting</em> like a British destroyer, given its “hesitating behavior” (<em>„zögernde Verhalten,“</em> Hasselwander is quoting Fraatz). Hasselwander goes on to suggest that Fraatz didn’t mean the torpedoes to sink the ship, but rather intended them as a (momentarily successful) effort to throw the <em>Greer</em> off his trail (<em>Die geringe Entfernung, auf die U 652 seinen zweiten Torpedo schoß, und die anscheinend überstürzte Art, in der dies geschah, lassen vermuten, daß Fraatz seinen Angriff hauptsächlich als Ablenkungsmanöver gedacht hatte, um seinen Verfolger abzuschütteln. Tatsächlich gelang es ja U 652, bis 15.07 h weitere Horchkontakte zu vermeiden</em>).<span class="citation" data-cites="hasselwanderUSZerstorerGreerUnd1962"><sup>3</sup></span></p>
<p>We should not, it seems to me, throw out this suggestion absent evidence. But also, it is a bit of a red herring. Roosevelt’s argument about the appropriate US response to the incident did not hinge on the U-boat captain’s knowing that the <em>Greer</em> was a US ship.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Gerard E. Hasselwander, <span>“Der US-Zerstörer <span>‘Greer’</span> Und <span>‘U 652’</span>”</span> 59 (1962): 156.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Hasselwander, <span>“Zerstörer <span>‘Greer’</span>,”</span> 156.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Hasselwander, <span>“Zerstörer <span>‘Greer’</span>,”</span> 155–56.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Greer</category>
  <category>Destroyers-for-bases</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_5_confusion/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Greer: just some more facts</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_4_facts_2/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Earlier I posted a bare-bones, <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_1/">“just-the-facts” narrative</a> of the <em>Greer</em> incident, from Samuel Eliot Morison’s account. Here are some more facts; as the Dude would say, <a href="https://tenor.com/view/new-shit-has-come-to-light-big-lebowski-reveal-gif-16492009">“new shit has come to light.”</a> Or rather, thanks to Inter-Library Loan, I received some new information that I’ve not seen cited in the standard accounts.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_4_facts_2/large_000000.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">An RAF Hudson off the shore of Dunkirk. IWM.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Morison says the British plane, an RAF Hudson, “dropped his depth charges more or less at random.” I did know that <em>Greer</em> was broadcasting the U-boat’s position, so that it wouldn’t have been all that random, but I hadn’t picked up on that in the account.</p>
<p>But there is also the question, often raised, of whether the U-boat commander saw the <em>Greer;</em> you usually read that we don’t know what he observed, or historians will impute behavior to him, as I quoted Waldo Heinrichs doing, saying the U-boat captain “must have regarded as hostile pursuit” the <em>Greer’s</em> continued following of the U-boat. Or consider Kenneth S. Davis’s account: “the harassed U-boat, its desperate commander probably believing the destroyer had made the depth-charge attack actually made by the British plane, suddenly fired a torpedo at the destroyer, then a second one, perhaps a third.”<span class="citation" data-cites="davisFDRWarPresident2000"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
<p>It did occur to me that someone might have sometime looked into the German records, and (again, thanks to ILL) I can now say the U-boat captain’s state of mind was not so clear as all that. Nor was the firing of the torpedo sudden.</p>
<p>The U-boat, U 652, under the command of Lieutenant Georg-Werner Fraatz, had been running on the surface, and then “dived after sighting an aircraft” (<em>und hatte dann nach Sichten eines Flugzeuges getaucht,</em>) according to Gerard E. Hasselwander, who was working with the war diaries (<em>Kriegstachebücher</em>) of U 652. So Fraatz, the U-boat captain, did know he was being pursued by an aircraft—although Hasselwander says that when the depth charges exploded, the crew believed they had come from the destroyer they could hear overhead (<em>glaubte seine Besatzung, daß der Zerstörer, den sie über sich hören konnten, der Angreifer sei</em>).<span class="citation" data-cites="hasselwanderUSZerstorerGreerUnd1962"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
<p>After the two hours’ pursuit without further attack, Fraatz was somewhat confused; he could not understand what he called the destroyer’s “hesitant behavior.” (<em>Der U-Bootkommandant konnte jedoch das „zögernde Verhalten” des Zerstörers nicht verstehen.</em>) So he came to periscope depth and had a look at it. He might even have surfaced, Hasselwander says, had not the weather been so good and the high visibility thus a risk to him—he could see, now, another plane above the <em>Greer.</em> At this point, he fired two torpedoes at the destroyer.</p>
<p>Hasselwander says we don’t really know why those two hours passed before Fraatz fired on the destroyer. Maybe he didn’t have a clean shot. But maybe also he had “concerns” (<em>Bedenken</em>)—about what, Hasselwander doesn’t say; but one possible concern would be that the destroyer was certainly not acting like a British destroyer, which meant that it might belong to a neutral power, possibly the United States.<span class="citation" data-cites="hasselwanderUSZerstorerGreerUnd1962"><sup>3</sup></span> Given what we know about <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_2_nazi/">the division in German thinking about a naval war against the United States at this time,</a> we might suppose that this same division was reflected in Fraatz’s mind.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Kenneth S. Davis, <em>FDR: The War President, 1940--1943</em> (New York: Random House, 2000), 277.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Gerard E. Hasselwander, <span>“Der US-Zerstörer <span>‘Greer’</span> Und <span>‘U 652’</span>”</span> 59 (1962): 153.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Hasselwander, <span>“Zerstörer <span>‘Greer’</span>,”</span> 153–54.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Greer</category>
  <category>convoys</category>
  <category>Nazi strategy</category>
  <category>US strategy</category>
  <category>UK strategy</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_4_facts_2/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Four Fears, Four Freedoms: US ideology</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/atlantic_ideology/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Admiral Stark’s <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_3_dog/">“Plan Dog” memo</a> sets as a basic aim the “preservation of the territorial, economic, and ideological integrity of the United States plus that of the remainder of the Western hemisphere.” Which for me raises a question Stark doesn’t address: what does he mean by “ideological integrity”? That question is difficult enough when applied to the United States; it’s even more knotty when applied to the rest of the Western Hemisphere. We can take up the question of the Good Neighbor Policy later; let’s look specifically at the United States. A couple months after the Plan Dog memo, Roosevelt would speak to Congress and outline the “four freedoms,” an ideological basis for US involvement in the war: freedom of speech, freedom of worship, freedom from want, and freedom from fear—everywhere in the world. I’ll talk more about that speech later, too; for this post I want to talk about the earliest public mention I know of those four basic rights, in <a href="http://www.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/_resources/images/pc/pc0101.pdf">a discussion between the Roosevelts and members of the American Youth Congress on June 5, 1940.</a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/atlantic_ideology/https:/tile.loc.gov/storage-services/service/pnp/hec/27700/27738v.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">William Hinckley of the American Youth Congress addresses the Dies (House UnAmerican Activities) Committee, November 30, 1939. Library of Congress.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The American Youth Congress (AYC) included a variety of organizations, among them the Boy Scouts and Girl Scouts, but it was widely supposed to have fallen under the influence of communists. It was also a favorite cause of Eleanor Roosevelt, who liked the idea of being in touch with the young people of the nation, which is why members of the AYC were in the state dining room of the White House on June 5, to talk to the president—and to prod him from his political left. One delegate after another asked him about the nation’s, and the administration’s, lackluster record on voting rights for Black citizens. They pressed him on the poll tax. They asked him whether the Allies were not in fact colonialist powers with at best a selective implementation of democracy. Roosevelt gave an honestly relativist answer, saying that whatever the Allies were fighting for, it was “a better form of democracy, certainly, than Germany is fighting for.”</p>
<p>After a while, one questioner gave him an opening to try something different. How, the president was asked, would he ensure that an Allied victory would produce a better outcome than it had in 1918?</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Let’s take this assumption that the world, the people of the world entrusted you to write the next peace. . . . How would America be effective in establishing democratic governments if that is the clue to future peace?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>For this question, Roosevelt sounded prepared.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>We have a pretty good idea of what we would seek. That is something. In other words, we have a program that is no secret. It is the elimination—I have put it that way on several occasions—it is the elimination of four fears.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He went on to explain these “four fears” as the worry people had that they might not be able to exercise their essential freedoms: freedom of religion, freedom of expression—and “the fear of arms” as well as, “the fear of not being able to have normal economic and social relations with other nations. . . . freedom of commerce and freedom of culture, because the two go hand in hand.”</p>
<p>Pressed on this amorphous last point—“Doesn’t it seem there should be a fifth item, that of giving people economic security in all countries?”—Roosevelt said, “Yes, that is the fourth point I am making.”</p>
<p>After the president left the room, the First Lady and Harry Hopkins answered more questions. In the course of this continued discussion, Eleanor Roosevelt said of the president’s positions on aid to the Allies,</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>A year and a half, two years ago, he said every single thing on defense that he said aloud today to individual members of Congress and gave the very same reasons. . . . Today, they are all running to him because the circumstances, the life of the world, have hit them in the face. . . . But they were not ready two years ago.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The president’s statement that he had used the “four fears” formulation “on several occasions,” together with Eleanor’s saying that he had been using these reasons for somewhere between eighteen months and two years, suggest—as did the president’s saying that his views were “no secret”—that he had somehow, to someone or several someones, mentioned ensuring these basic rights as the essential basis for US aid to the Allies. But as I say, this is the first public occasion of which I’m aware. And even here, as you can see, the formulation is not complete; the “freedom from want” was anything but clearly framed.</p>
<p>What you can also see is that Roosevelt, whether using this argument with “individual members of Congress” or young, evidently leftist Americans, was trying to provide an ideological answer to why the US should aid the Allies: to fight for a world in which essential human rights were globally guaranteed.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>US strategy</category>
  <category>US politics</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/atlantic_ideology/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The German threat: Plan Dog</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_3_dog/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>On November 12, 1940, shortly after Roosevelt’s re-election to a unique third term in the presidency, Chief of Naval Operations Harold Stark sent a memorandum to the Secretary of the Navy, Frank Knox, outlining the US military position. The document became known as “Plan Dog,” after the US-UK phonetic alphabet for “D” (Able, Baker, Charlie, Dog, Easy, Fox, etc.) because out of the options Stark considered, he recommended proceeding with the one he lettered “D”—a joint offensive with Britain against Germany in the Atlantic, in anticipation of a wider war.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_3_dog/https:/tile.loc.gov/storage-services/service/pnp/hec/47500/47500v.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Admiral Stark, in the light gray business suit, stands behind the president, who is decorating Admiral Yarnell for his recent comportment in China. Photo of August 28, 1939. Library of Congress.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><a href="http://www.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/_resources/images/psf/psfa0048.pdf">The memorandum</a> runs 26 pages and covers a lot of ground. Here is a single paragraph, from page 19, where Stark gives a succinct summary of his argument for US concern about the German threat.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>It is a fundamental requirement of our military position that our homeland remain secure against successful attack. Directly concerned in this security is the safety of other parts of the Western Hemisphere. A very strong pillar of the defense structure of the Americans has, for many years, been the balance of power existing in Europe. The collapse of Great Britain or the destruction or surrender of the British Fleet will destroy this balance and will free European military power for possible encroachment in this hemisphere.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The security of the US depends on the security of the Americas; the security of the Americas depends on a balance of power in Europe; German defeat of Britain will end that balance and its destruction or acquisition of the British fleet would enable a German attack on the Americas and thus imperil the United States.</p>
<p><a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_2_nazi/">We know Hitler thought in similar, if reversed, terms,</a> planning a war on the United States once he had secured his European triumph, though he did not necessarily feel he needed to defeat Britain—merely the Soviet Union, which he expected to do swiftly.</p>
<p>Stark thus believed the first question was how best to preserve Britain from defeat. He rejected focusing on likely war with Japan, or strictly defensive options, and advocated his option D: a joint offensive with Britain in the Atlantic, while keeping a strong defensive posture in the Pacific. The US fleet should remain in the Pacific until war was “imminent.” Assistance to Britain would mean protecting shipping in the western Atlantic, and reinforcing British naval operations around the British Isles and down the coast of Africa, as well as in the Mediterranean.</p>
<p>The chief of naval operations further acknowledged that “purely naval assistance, would not, in my opinion, <em>assure</em> final victory for Great Britain,” and moreover that Britain lacked the manpower to win an infantry campaign on its own. “I believe that the United States, in addition to sending naval assistance, would also need to send large air and land forces to Europe or Africa, or both, and to participate strongly in this land offensive.”</p>
<p>Any other option, Stark believed, would end in British collapse—and thus a serious threat to US security.</p>
<p>The memorandum thus recommended joint Army-Navy plans and moreover, “secret staff talks on technical matters with the British military and naval authorities” to assure coordination of the impending war effort.</p>
<p>The Army accepted Stark’s memo with the addition that the United States should expect to supply substantial air support in a war alongside the British. The president authorized the staff conversations, and on December 2, 1940, Stark invited the British to come to Washington for joint planning.<span class="citation" data-cites="connWesternHemisphereFramework1960"><sup>1</sup></span></p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Stetson Conn and Byron Fairchild, <em>The Western Hemisphere: The Framework of Hemispheric Defense</em>, vol. 12, part 1, United States Army in World War II (Washington, D.C.: Office of the Chief of Military History, 1960), 92.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>convoys</category>
  <category>Greer</category>
  <category>US strategy</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_3_dog/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Greer: Nazi strategy</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_2_nazi/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The September 4, 1941, U-boat attack on the <em>Greer</em> was materially inconsequential, but symbolically vital, and to understand why, we have to think about this particular moment in the war. In this post we will look at this moment in Nazi strategy, just a couple months after the start of Operation Barbarossa, the German assault on the Soviet Union. Although the conclusion of David Stahel is pretty well established—that is to say, that by August the collapse of Barbarossa was already determined; that the failure to put resources into the construction of railroads and other logistical necessities spelled catastrophe—we should remember that even if to us, the tanks racing East look foolishly disconnected from the infantry that could secure their advances, at the time, they looked like the irresistible advance guard of yet another successful Blitzkrieg. As Stahel notes, the British Joint Intelligence Committee thought the Germans would win within six weeks; in the US, Secretary of War Stimson and General George Marshall believed it would take Germany one to three months to defeat the Soviet Union.<span class="citation" data-cites="stahelOpearationBarbarossaGermany2009"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_2_nazi/https:/media.iwm.org.uk/cantaloupe/iiif/2/295%7C%7C613%7C%7Clarge_000000.jpg/full/730,/0/default.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A panzer, part of Army Group Centre, advancing into the East. Imperial War Museum.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>And the Nazi high command, Hitler in particular, thought the same. Victory in the East was certain and imminent, which meant that the German navy need only stay its hand briefly before launching war on the United States.</p>
<p>According to Holger Herwig, Hitler told Admiral Erich Raeder to plan for a fleet of ten “superbattleships” by 1944, for war on Britain, the United States, or both. The Ziel Plan, or Z-Plan, drafted in 1939, sketched out the development of this Navy and, Herwig notes, the plan was modified in 1940 specifically for war on the United States, when Hitler “took an active interest in selecting future Atlantic bases, preferring Iceland, the Azores, the Cape Verdes, and the Canaries”; this in the flush of victory after the fall of France and “with an eye to the future war with America,” as of October 29, 1940.<span class="citation" data-cites="herwigPoliticsFrustrationUnited1976"><sup>2</sup></span> Herwig tells us that Raeder and Hitler viewed this plan differently; Raeder thought of it as an alternative to the war with the USSR, while Hitler—who was ideologically committed to the acquisition of <em>lebensraum</em> in the East and the killing of the people currently living there—thought of it as a consequence to the war with the Soviet Union.<span class="citation" data-cites="herwigPoliticsFrustrationUnited1976"><sup>3</sup></span></p>
<p>Therefore Hitler instructed Raeder repeatedly to avoid any incident with the United States, if only for the time being. Herwig has Hitler saying so as early as May 1941. In June, the day before Barbarossa, Hitler told Raeder, “avoid <em>every</em> incident with the United States until ‘Barbarossa’ unfolded itself. After a few weeks the situation would be cleared up.” In July, with the US occupation of Iceland, Raeder and the naval staff requested “immediate armed assault on all USA ships within our publicly proclaimed war zone.” Hitler did continue planning operations in Gibraltar and Northwest Africa to establish an “offensive stance against America” but also repeated his order to wait for outright operations against the United States until the campaign in the East had reached its successful conclusion. He repeated this order again on August 22.<span class="citation" data-cites="herwigPoliticsFrustrationUnited1976"><sup>4</sup></span></p>
<p>At the time of the <em>Greer</em> attack, Hitler and his naval commanders anticipated a war, soon, against the United States. The navy was eager for it and restrained only by Hitler’s belief that it must wait on the imminent victory against the USSR (which came, even to Hitler, to seem less imminent by the end of August, if still within reach).</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>David Stahel, <em>Opearation Barbarossa and Germany’s Defeat in the East</em> (Cambridge, Eng.: Cambridge University Press, 2009), 148.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Holger H. Herwig, <em>The Politics of Frustration: The United States in German Naval Planning, 1889--1941</em> (Boston: Little, Brown, 1976), 210, 214.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Herwig, <em>Politics of Frustration</em>, 216.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Herwig, <em>Politics of Frustration</em>, 224 and 224n, 226–227, 232 and 232n.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Greer</category>
  <category>convoys</category>
  <category>Nazi strategy</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_2_nazi/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Greer: just the facts</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_1/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>On September 4, 1941, the German submarine U-652 attempted to torpedo the U.S.S. <em>Greer,</em> a destroyer ferrying mail from the United States to Iceland. The president used the occasion to <a href="http://www.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/_resources/images/msf/msf01443">declare in a fireside chat</a> that</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>from now on, if German or Italian vessels of war enter the waters, the protection of which is necessary for American defense, they do so at their own peril.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_1/12248087.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Denmark, including Iceland, from an atlas of 1940–1945. David Rumsey Map Collection.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>There’s a lot to say about this episode, but let’s for this post try to get the facts straight, which historians often do not, even in otherwise reputable books. Consider for example,</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>On 4 September the German submarine U-652 unsuccessfully tried to torpedo the American escort destroyer U.S.S. <em>Greer,</em> which had attempted to depth-charge the U-boat south of Ireland.<span class="citation" data-cites="herwigPoliticsFrustrationUnited1976"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>While “Ireland” is probably an unfortunate typographical error, the assertion that <em>Greer</em> fired first is simply wrong and reflects German propaganda in the days after the attack.<span class="citation" data-cites="ClaimUBoatWas1941"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
<p>The bare facts are these:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>U.S.S. <em>Greer,</em> carrying the pennant of Commander G.W. Johnson and commanded by Lieutenant Commander L.H. Frost, was proceeding independently toward Iceland on 4 September 1941 in lat. 62°45’ N, long. 27°37’ W, at a speed of 17 1/2 knots. At 0840 a British plane signaled to her that a submerged U-boat lay athwart her course some ten miles ahead. <em>Greer</em> commenced zigzagging, increased speed to twenty knots, went to general quarters, laid a course for the reported position, and on reaching it slowed to ten knots in order to allow her sound gear to operate at full efficiency. She made sound contact with the submarine and maintained it for over three hours, keeping the submerged U-boat always on her bow but not attacking. At 1000 the British plane captain inquired whether <em>Greer</em> intended to attack, and was answered in the negative. He then dropped his depth charges more or less at random, and returned to base to refuel. At 1240 the submarine headed toward the American destroyer and launched a torpedo, which was sighted early enough to be dodged. <em>Greer</em> counterattacked with depth charges, and at 1300 the U-boat shot a second torpedo, which was also avoided. Unable to reestablish sound contact, <em>Greer</em> discontinued the search at 1416 and resumed course for Iceland.<span class="citation" data-cites="morisonBattleAtlanticSeptember1950"><sup>3</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>It seems essential to me for historians relating this episode to note that something like two hours passed after the British plane dropped its depth charges and before the U-boat fired on the <em>Greer.</em> The British attack, such as it was, was not ongoing at the time the German U-boat attempted to torpedo the American destroyer, although one may charitably say (as Waldo Heinrichs does) that the U-boat captain “must have regarded as hostile pursuit” the <em>Greer’s</em> continued persistence in tailing it.<span class="citation" data-cites="heinrichsThresholdWarFranklin1988"><sup>4</sup></span></p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Holger H. Herwig, <em>The Politics of Frustration: The United States in German Naval Planning, 1889--1941</em> (Boston: Little, Brown, 1976), 231.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>See, e.g., <span>“Claim U-Boat Was Acting in Self Defense,”</span> <em>Honolulu Star-Bulletin</em>, September 6, 1941, 1.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Samuel Eliot Morison, <em>The Battle of the Atlantic, September 1939--May 1943</em>, vol. 1, History of United States Naval Operations in World War II (Boston: Little, Brown, 1950), 79–80.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Waldo Heinrichs, <em>Threshold of War: Franklin D. Roosevelt and American Entry into World War II</em> (New York: Oxford University Press, 1988), 167.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Greer</category>
  <category>convoys</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_1/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The German threat to the United States, 1940–1941: Atlantic geography</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/atl_dist/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>This is a follow-up to <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/">the previous post</a> on Roosevelt’s assessment of the German threat in December 1940, pursuing the big question, “How much of a threat did Germany pose to the United States before Pearl Harbor?” This post looks at the question of Atlantic geography and German ambitions.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Likewise, the military scenarios Roosevelt sketched had little basis in reality. . . . He also stressed the narrowness of the Atlantic, even if not at the obviously most relevant place: “At one point between Africa and Brazil the distance is less than from Washington to Denver, Colorado—five hours for the latest type of bomber.”<span class="citation" data-cites="thompsonExaggerationAmericanVulnerability1992"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Let’s consider the Atlantic situation at the time of Roosevelt’s speech at the end of 1940.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/atl_dist/atlmap.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">The strategic situation in the Atlantic at the end of 1940.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>You can see the short distance from Brazil to West Africa; you can also see that French West Africa was at the time under the jurisdiction of the Vichy regime. France had fallen to Germany in June; Italy had entered the war and struck west across North Africa. Though the Italians had failed to take Egypt and were then suffering under British counter-attack, the Germans would shortly organize the Afrika Corps under Erwin Rommel and deploy it to the region.<span class="citation" data-cites="weinbergWorldArmsGlobal2005"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
<p>The status of West Africa was thus anything but evidently secure at the end of 1940, and indeed would only seem less secure quite soon.</p>
<p>Even as Roosevelt was warning that the Americas were vulnerable to German assault across the Atlantic, Hitler was planning for such an attack. In response to the Roosevelt administration’s September 1940 agreement to trade US destroyers for British bases in the western hemisphere, Hitler told Admiral Raeder that “England-USA must be thrown out of North-West Africa.” He opened negotiations with Spain to trade French Morocco for one of the Canary Islands, to establish a military outpost in the far West of the European hemisphere; he also began to consider whether the Azores could be used “to carry out aerial attacks from a land base against the United States.” German bomber technology would not then support it but nobody could then know of the limits on even the longest-range German bombers then under development, the Heinkel 177.<span class="citation" data-cites="herwigPreludeWeltblitzkriegGermany1971"><sup>3</sup></span></p>
<p>In the period between the fall of France and Pearl Harbor, Germany appeared to be at peak power, to Germans and to outside observers alike. Through 1941, aware of the impending Japanese attack, Hitler would continue to plan for a German war on the United States, in which an assault across the Atlantic would play a part.<span class="citation" data-cites="herwigPreludeWeltblitzkriegGermany1971"><sup>4</sup></span> There is thus no obvious reason to believe that Roosevelt was wrong, or alarmist, to consider the relative narrowness of the ocean or the possibility of a German aerial assault across its expanse.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>John A. Thompson, <span>“The Exaggeration of American Vulnerability: The Anatomy of a Tradition,”</span> <em>Diplomatic History</em> 16, no. 1 (January 1992): 30.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Gerhard L. Weinberg, <em>A World at Arms: A Global History of World War II</em>, 2nd ed. (Cambridge, Eng.: Cambridge University Press, 2005), 215.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Holger H Herwig, <span>“Prelude to Weltblitzkrieg: Germany’s Naval Policy Toward the United States of America, 1939-41,”</span> <em>Journal of Modern History</em> 43, no. 4 (December 1971): 657–58.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Herwig, <span>“Prelude to Weltblitzkrieg,”</span> 660–62.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>airpower</category>
  <category>Nazi strategy</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/atl_dist/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The German threat to the United States, 1940–1941: bomber range</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>How much of a threat did Germany pose to the United States before Pearl Harbor? That’s the big question; let’s look at a small part of it. Historians often say Roosevelt exaggerated the specific threats Nazi Germany posed; here we’ll look at one claim about the threat posed by German bombers.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Likewise, the military scenarios Roosevelt sketched had little basis in reality. . . . In December 1940 he made the remarkable claim that “even today we have planes that could fly from the British Isles to New England and back again without refueling.”<span class="citation" data-cites="thompsonExaggerationAmericanVulnerability1992"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>It might seem to us remarkable that in December 1940, airplanes could fly the distance of an Atlantic round trip, but it was not remarkable to claim it. The crossing comes to about a 3,000-mile flight one way, so a return journey would total 6,000 miles. The Imperial Airways seaplane <em>Mercury</em> completed a flight of more than 6,000 miles non-stop from Dundee, Scotland to the Orange River in South Africa in October 1938.<span class="citation" data-cites="wraggBoatsAirIllustrated1984"><sup>2</sup></span> This feat was <a href="https://nyti.ms/3nTEwJC">reported in the newspapers, together with comparable records.</a> Not only was Roosevelt’s statement simply true, many of his listeners would have known it already.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/https:/www.nli.ie/digital/vtls000249986.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">The <em>Mercury</em> shown atop its launcher airplane, the flying boat <em>Maia.</em> National Library of Ireland.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Let’s look more closely at Roosevelt’s specific claim. This is what it says in the reading copy:</p>
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/range_claim.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>And here’s what Roosevelt actually said, according to transcription at the time:</p>
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/range_claim_as_said.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>First, this claim was refined in the process of writing the speech. Thanks to the FDR Presidential Library, we can <a href="http://www.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/_resources/images/msf/msf01403,">link to the relevant folder in the Master Speech File</a> and see that in earlier drafts, this paragraph read,</p>
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/earlier_claim.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The claim that planes could fly return from New York to London was probably supportable enough, given the flight of the <em>Mercury.</em> But at the seventh draft, Roosevelt changed it (notice the handwriting):</p>
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/revised_claim.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Now not only is the distance more accurate and defensible—from “the British Isles” to “New England” is more accurately the route Imperial Airways was even then, despite the war, flying; but by changing its direction Roosevelt was, of course, emphasizing the potential threat should Britain fall to Germany.</p>
<p>Second, the claim about the outside range of existing aircraft is coupled here with a second claim. It’s clear with these two sentences that Roosevelt and his speechwriters are making a distinction between what the longest-distance airplanes could already do, and what modern bombers could soon do. This observation supports a generalization I want to make and will probably make again: Roosevelt and his speechwriters were quite careful.</p>
<p>The claim about how bombers were then developing, and what their capacity would be, was also correct. The B-29, though it was still on the drawing board, would have a <a href="https://www.boeing.com/history/products/b-29-superfortress.page">maximum range of 5,830 miles.</a> The experimental predecessor to the B-29, the XB-15, had already flown in 1937, and derived from a plan for a bomber with an effective range of 5,000 miles.<span class="citation" data-cites="knaackEncyclopediaAirForce1988"><sup>3</sup></span> Americans attentive to the news would have known about the XB-15; Major Caleb Haynes of the US Army air corps <a href="https://nyti.ms/3GlePbu">had flown one on an earthquake relief mission from Langley to Santiago, Chile, stopping in Panama and Peru, in February 1939.</a></p>
<p>Again, not only did Roosevelt make a carefully constructed and factually correct claim, he made one that many of his listeners would have understood to be readily supportable.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>John A. Thompson, <span>“The Exaggeration of American Vulnerability: The Anatomy of a Tradition,”</span> <em>Diplomatic History</em> 16, no. 1 (January 1992): 30.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>David W. Wragg, <em>Boats of the Air: An Illustrated History of Flying Boats, Seaplanes and Amphibians</em> (London: Robert Hale, 1984), 149.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Marcelle Size Knaack, <em>Encyclopedia of U.S. Air Force Aircraft and Missile Systems</em>, vol. 2: Post–World War II Bombers, 1945--1973 (Washington, D.C.: Office of Air Force History, 1988), 479.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>airpower</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
