<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>a necessitous blog</title>
<link>https://erauchway.github.io/</link>
<atom:link href="https://erauchway.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>A blog about the era of the Roosevelt administration, 1933--1945</description>
<generator>quarto-1.5.55</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2024 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Japanese Americans, per IPUMS</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/japanese_americans/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>IPUMS has now made available a preliminary complete-count sample—that is to say, everyone in the Census is represented in the <a href="https://usa.ipums.org/usa/full_count.shtml">sample—for 1950.</a> Having both 1940 and 1950 makes it possible to look at the before-and-after for Japanese American imprisonment without trial. Here’s a preliminary look.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/japanese_americans/ja_locs.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Three panel chart showing location by county of Japanese American population in 1930, 1940, and 1950; the increase of people in cities and East of the Rockies is pronounced between 1940 and 1950.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Japanese Americans</category>
  <category>Internment</category>
  <category>IPUMS</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/japanese_americans/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Compelled to look beyond</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/gold/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In February 1935 the Supreme Court was about to issue an opinion on the question of whether the Roosevelt administration’s policy of taking the country off the gold standard was constitutional.</p>
<p>On first coming into office Roosevelt ended the gold standard—people could no longer exchange a dollar for the statutory rate of $20.67 to an ounce of pure gold. By this measure Roosevelt meant to induce the expectation of inflation, and start money out of hoarding and into circulation. Over the course of 1933 the administration devalued the dollar by various means and early in 1934, using the authority of the new Gold Reserve Act, set the dollar at $35 to an ounce of gold, subject to change.</p>
<p>The administration viewed its policy of moving away from the gold standard and toward a managed dollar as an effective means of fighting the Depression and also of rallying other countries to recovery. Indeed, it proved effective, both economically and eventually as a tool to assemble an international coalition against fascism.<span class="citation" data-cites="rauchwayMoneyMakersHow2015 hausmanRecoveryGreatDepression2019a eggertssonGreatExpectationsEnd2008a"><sup>1</sup></span> To reverse this policy in 1935 and return to the lower prices of 1932 would be calamitous economically, politically, and diplomatically.</p>
<p>Roosevelt and his advisors considered various options for getting around an adverse Court opinion; one idea the president floated was to have Federal Reserve branches honor the commitment to redeem paper money in gold at the teller window, but to forbid depositors from taking that gold out of the building, requiring them instead to exchange it for paper money if they wished to return it to circulation.</p>
<p>Roosevelt also prepared an address to give in the event of the Court demanding he reverse course. In it, he prepared to illustrate in concrete terms how dangerous such a policy would be, and to conclude,</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>They have decided these cases in accordance with the letter of the law as they saw it. It is nevertheless my duty to protect the people of the United States to the best of my ability. To carry through the decision of the Court to its logical and inescapable end will so endanger the people of this Nation that I am compelled to look beyond the letter of the law to <a href="http://www.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/_resources/images/msf/msf00790">the spirit.”</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>He promised further messages and actions to that end in the coming days.</p>
<p>He never had to give the speech; the Court left this policy—unlike many others—intact. But he meant to fight the Court if he had to.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Eric Rauchway, <em>The Money Makers: How Roosevelt and Keynes Ended the Depression, Defeated Fascism, and Secured a Prosperous Peace</em> (New York: Basic Books, 2015); Joshua K. Hausman, Paul W. Rhode, and Johannes F. Wieland, <span>“Recovery from the Great Depression: The Farm Channel in Spring 1933,”</span> <em>The American Economic Review</em> 109, no. 2 (2019): 427–72; Gauti B. Eggertsson, <span>“Great Expectations and the End of the Depression,”</span> <em>American Economic Review</em> 98, no. 4 (September 2008): 1476--1516.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>Gold</category>
  <category>SCOTUS</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/gold/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>He reads to us from something called ‘Ulysses’</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/comstockery/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2024/03/26/comstock-act-supreme-court-abortion-pill/">Justices Thomas and Alito have brought the Comstock laws back into the news</a> in an effort to craft a national ban on abortion. The laws banned a lot more, including James Joyce’s masterpiece <em>Ulysses,</em> until the dawn of the New Deal.</p>
<p>On March 3, 1873, Congress substantially expanded section 148 of the existing statute defining the scope and activities of the Post Office. The law already banned any “obscene book, pamphlet, picture, print, or other publication of a vulgar or indecent character” from the mails and defined sending such stuff as a misdemeanor for which a perpetrator could be fined not more than $500 and serve not more than a year in prison.<sup>1</sup> Now they went much further:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>no obscene, lewd, or lascivious book, pamphlet, picture, paper, print, or other publication of an indecent character, or any article or thing designed for the prevention of conception or procuring of abortion, nor any article or thing intended or adapted for any indecent or immoral use or nature, nor any written or printed card, circular, book, pamphlet, advertisement or notice of any kind gfiving information, directly or indirectly, where, or how, or of whom, or by what means either of the things before mentioned may be obtained or made</p>
</blockquote>
<p>—nothing like that could go in the mails, and anyone convicted of doing it could be fined not less than $100 and not more than $5000 or imprisoned not less than a year or more than ten years, or both.<sup>2</sup> Forty years later, in 1913, this statute and its revisions were summarized in the Post Office’s regulations as below, prohibiting anything “filthy”; the penalty was now not more than $5000 in fines and not more than 5 years in prison.</p>
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/comstockery/po_com.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>That’s what the New York postmaster, Thomas Patten, cited in 1919 when asking Judge W.H. Lamar, solicitor of the Post Office, what he thought of the May 1919 issue of the <em>Little Review,</em> which contained the “Scylla and Charybdis” episode of James Joyce’s yet unfinished novel <em>Ulysses.</em> Lamar found it “unmailable.” The Post Office found the same of the issue containing the “Cyclops” episode, for political reasons possibly relating to the Espionage Act passed during the Great War; the nation was now fully into the red scare.<span class="citation" data-cites="weirWhatDidHe2000"><sup>3</sup></span></p>
<p>But it was in 1920 when the real Comstockery came: Anthony Comstock’s successor as head of the New York Society for the Suppression of Vice, John Sumner, lodged a complaint against the <em>Little Review</em> for publishing the “Nausicaa” episode, which includes a scene—obscured, to be sure, under literary prose—of Leopold Bloom masturbating while looking at Gerty MacDowell on the beach. At trial, a three-judge panel found the publishers of the <em>Little Review,</em> Margaret Anderson and Jane Heap, guilty. As Anderson wrote,</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>They “don’t care who James Joyce is or whether he has written the finest books in the world”; their only function is to decide whether certain passages of “Ulysses” (Incidentally the only passages they can understand) violate the statute. . . . This decision establishes us as criminals and we are led to an adjoining building where another bewildered official takes our fingerprints!!!<span class="citation" data-cites="andersonUlyssesCourt1921"><sup>4</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The key point there is that the judges confined themselves to the question of whether the particular passage should be understood as “filthy.”</p>
<p>In 1933, when <em>Ulysses</em> came once more to court, Judge John Woolsey of the Southern District of New York had the whole book.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I have read “Ulysses” once in its entirety and I have read the passages of which the government particularly complains several times. . . . “Ulysses” is not an easy book to read or to understand. But there has been much written about it, and in order properly to approach the consideration of it it is advisable to read a number of other books which have now become its satellites. The study of “Ulysses” is, therefore, a heavy task.<sup>5</sup></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Judge Woolsey had previously established himself as a dedicated scholar; in holding that the book <em>Married Love</em> was not obscene, he mentioned he derived necessary perspective from reading Havelock Ellis.<sup>6</sup> He was also a pretty good literary critic.<span class="citation" data-cites="vanderhamLiftingBanUlysses1994"><sup>7</sup></span></p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Joyce has attempted—it seems to me, with astonishing success—to show how the screen of consciousness with its ever-shifting kaleidoscopic impressions carries, as it were on a plastic palimpsest, not only what is in the focus of each man’s observation of the actual things about him, but also in a penumbral zone residua of past impressions, some recent and some drawn up by association from the domain of the subconscious. He shows how each of these impressions affects the life and behavior of the character which he is describing. . . .</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>If Joyce did not attempt to be honest in developing the technique which he has adopted in “Ulysses,” the result would be psychologically misleading and thus unfaithful to his chosen technique. Such an attitude would be artistically inexcusable.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>It is because Joyce has been loyal to his technique and has not funked its necessary implications, but has honestly attempted to tell fully what his characters think about, that he has been the subject of so many attacks. . . .</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In short: people think about sex. Sometimes quite a lot. So portraying it—along with the many, many other things Joyce portrays in <em>Ulysses</em>—is true to the book’s purpose.</p>
<p>Woolsey wasn’t above being a little funny.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>My considered opinion is, after long reflection, is that, whilst in many places the effect of “Ulysses” on the reader undoubtedly is somewhat emetic, nowhere does it tend to be an aphrodisiac.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Considering the entire book, rather than the allegedly offending passage, was an important shift in the law on obscenity.<span class="citation" data-cites="gillersTendencyDepraveCorrupt2007"><sup>8</sup></span></p>
<p>So <em>Ulysses</em> could come into the United States. And so, as Morris Ernst, the attorney for Random House, wrote in the foreword to US edition of <em>Ulysses,</em> “The New Deal in the law of letters is here.”<span class="citation" data-cites="joyceUlysses1961"><sup>9</sup></span></p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>17 Stat. 302.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>18 Stat. 599.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>David Weir, <span>“What Did He Know, and When Did He Know It: The <span>‘Little Review,’</span> Joyce, and <span>‘Ulysses’</span>,”</span> <em>James Joyce Quarterly</em> 37, no. 3/4 (Spring-Summer 2000): 394. Records are incomplete, Weir points out, so it’s not always entirely clear what the rationale was for suppression.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Margaret Anderson, <span>“Ulysses in Court,”</span> <em>Little Review</em> 7, no. 4 (January--March, 1921): 23, 25.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p><em>United States v. One Book Called “Ulysses,”</em> December 6, 1933, 5 F. Supp. 182 (S.D.N.Y. 1933).↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn6"><p><em>United States v. One Obscene Book Entitled “Married Love,”</em> April 6, 1931, 48 F.2d 821 (1931).↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn7"><p>Not everyone agrees. Paul Vanderham, <span>“Lifting the Ban on <span>‘Ulysses’</span>: The Well-Intentioned Lies of the Woolsey Decision,”</span> <em>Mosaic</em> 27, no. 4 (December 1994): 179--197.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn8"><p>The old way of thinking—the <em>Hicklin</em> test, looking only at the offending passage—wouldn’t go completely until <em>Roth v. US</em> in 1957. Stephen Gillers, <span>“A Tendency to Deprave and Corrupt: The Transformation of American Obscenity Law from <em>Hicklin</em> to <em>Ulysses II</em>,”</span> <em>Washington University Law Review</em> 85, no. 2 (2007): 215--296.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn9"><p>James Joyce, <em>Ulysses</em> (New York: Vintage, 1961), v.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>SCOTUS</category>
  <category>Comstock</category>
  <category>Ulysses</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/comstockery/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Not a review of Masters of the Air</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/air/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This is not a review of <em>Masters of the Air;</em> I’m not a tv critic and in the end I mainly enjoyed it for what it was—this is instead a discussion of what it’s not: a story of the US bomber war in Europe, which I think could still be dramatized someday.</p>
<p>The basic, traditional history of the US bomber war in Europe has a clear dramatic arc. It starts with high hopes; these are swiftly tempered by cruel realities; in the end much is gained though much also is lost, and at the close of it, one would be hard-pressed to say that the right lessons are learned or that the just will prosper while the unjust receive their comeuppance. That’s a narrative with which a talented dramatist could keep an audience, I think.</p>
<p>We could put a few concrete details on that narrative line:</p>
<p>It began with the idea of precision strikes at the means of making war by bombers capable of self-defense tasked with achieving, to pick a phrase, <a href="https://archive.org/details/VictoryThroughAirPower">“victory through air power.”</a></p>
<p>That idea is what sent US air crews and factory-fresh B-24s to the North African desert in 1942, with the intention of striking at the vitals of the German war machine—the oil refineries in Romania. This little raid inspired the local Luftwaffe colonel to observe, “This is the beginning.” The Germans, recognizing what would come next, prepared. Subsequent raids on the oil refineries by North Africa-based B-24s incurred heavy US losses—some 280 aircraft and some 2,800 airmen.</p>
<p>That pattern, of striking at industrial targets with the idea of crushing the factories that made modern war possible, and finding out that German defenses could destroy more bombers than the Americans could afford to lose, persisted. Moreover, precision bombing—as the RAF already knew—was a fantasy. The much-celebrated Norden bombsight could, maybe, deliver precision over the sunny US southwest, where many pilots trained—bombs into pickle barrels from thousands of feet in the air!—but it was a very different thing over cloudy and fighter-infested northern and central Europe.</p>
<p>The bombing campaign in 1942–43 (I am reasonably persuaded by modern historians like Phillips O’Brien) may have achieved more than conventional wisdom allows.<span class="citation" data-cites="obrienHowWarWas2015a"><sup>1</sup></span> But those gains came at unsustainable costs: the US couldn’t afford to lose so many trained pilots and crews.</p>
<p>It wasn’t until the advances of fighter technology (increased range for P-47s and the arrival of P-51s) as well as advances of the Allies into Western Europe that allowed a free range of bombing in Germany and German-held territory. And the campaigns of early 1944 helped pave the way for D-Day.</p>
<p>In the end the bombing campaign became more what the RAF leaders, particularly Arthur Harris, always insisted it had to be: a parallel to and would-be replacement for the ground war, an attempt to pummel the Germans into surrender. The destruction of Dresden in February 1945 stuck out in the minds even of some airmen at the time as exceptionally brutal—though that feeling was swiftly muddied by news out of the liberated concentration camps, and a renewed feeling (for some people, anyway) that the savagery had to be stopped, even if by savage means.</p>
<p>Whatever the justice of that sentiment, its essence (“we did terrible things that had to be done”) was a long way from the (literally) Disneyfied original vision of the bomber war.</p>
<p>Anyway: that’s the narrative of the US bomber war which I kind of wanted to see dramatized. It’s not exactly <em>not</em> in <em>Masters of the Air,</em> but nor is it foregrounded; the series is really the story of a few guys who were among the last out of Stalag Luft III and, for the sake of perspective, a couple of their luckier squadron members. Which is fine, that’s a real story. And you get to see some B-17s and P-51s, and some of the misery and horror of aerial combat.</p>
<p>But though some of those narrative beats I outlined above do appear in the series, they do so only fleetingly. Indeed, owing to the focus on the pilots who were shot down, the air war itself largely vanishes from the narrative. I wanted to see some discussion of Hamburg, Caen, Dresden, the bombing of the IG Farben site at Auschwitz-Birkenau; they’re not here.</p>
<p>As I say, this is <em>not</em> a review of <em>Masters of the Air,</em> because it would be annoying if it were. But I did want to sketch quickly a story of the bomber war that could be dramatized.</p>
<p>And because I just have to, here’s a chart that shows why I’d like to see some airplanes that aren’t B-17s or P-51s.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/air/airplot.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Plot showing B-17s, B-24s, P-51s, and P-47s in theaters vs.&nbsp;Germany.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Phillips Payson O’Brien, <em>How the War Was Won: Air-Sea Power and Allied Victory in World War II</em> (Cambridge, Eng.: Cambridge University Press, 2015).↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>B-24</category>
  <category>airpower</category>
  <category>US strategy</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/air/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Betty expects</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/flags/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As previously <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_3_dog/index.html">noted,</a> Admiral Harold “Betty” Stark, Chief of Naval Operations, wrote the “Plan Dog” memo on November 12, 1940, advocating a joint US-UK naval strategy against Germany in the Atlantic. The president invited the British to come to Washington for joint staff conversations on December 2, 1940.<span class="citation" data-cites="connWesternHemisphereFramework1960a"><sup>1</sup></span> But before that—on November 28—Stark, as Chief of Naval Operations, issued an order to ensure practical preparedness for Anglo-American cooperation: he asked the New York Navy Yard to manufacture twenty sets of Royal Navy signal flags, for use by US warships needing to communicate with their British counterparts.<span class="citation" data-cites="chiefofnavaloperations1941a"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/flags/flags1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Part of the Royal Navy signal card for 1937.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The US navy and the British navy used different sets of signal flags, so for an American destroyer, say, to communicate with its British counterpart would require the use of a common language.<span class="citation" data-cites="unitedstatesnavyBluejacketsManual1940a SignalCard1937a"><sup>3</sup></span> Stark decided therefore that US ships should be issued with sets of British flags and pennants, and extra fabric to repair them. In February 1941, after the staff conferences, Stark increased the order from twenty to one hundred, fifty to be stored in New York and fifty in Norfolk, for issue to ships on the Atlantic squadron.<span class="citation" data-cites="chiefofnavaloperations1941a"><sup>4</sup></span> By April they were available for distribution; on May 6, the USS <em>Greer</em> received its set from the supply ship USS <em>Prairie.</em><span class="citation" data-cites="supplyofficerussprairieInvoice41a commandantnorfolknavyyard1941a"><sup>5</sup></span></p>
<p>The president had long since articulated <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/panama/index.html">a vision of hemispheric defense,</a> which would involve de facto assistance to Britain. On February 27, 1941—in, as it happens, a speech to the Oscars—he reminded listeners of this hemispheric policy and made explicit the implicit link to a broader defense:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>the defense of all the democracies of all the Americas . . . involves the future of democracy wherever it is imperiled by force or terror.<span class="citation" data-cites="rooseveltAddressAnnualAwards1950a"><sup>6</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>In March, Lend Lease passed Congress; on April 25, the administration declared the “patrol” being conducted by US Navy ships looking for aggressor activity would be extended, though Roosevelt said the United States was still not, per se, <a href="http://www.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/_resources/images/pc/pc0116.pdf">conducting convoys.</a> But:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Q Mr.&nbsp;President, if this patrol should encounter some apparently aggressive ships headed toward the western hemisphere, what would it do about it?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>THE PRESIDENT: Let me know. (loud laughter)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Or, perhaps, use its new signal flags to communicate the presence of a German vessel to the Royal Navy. Three weeks after the <em>Greer</em> received its set of British signal flags, the president declared an unlimited national emergency, in which the naval patrol would play a vital part.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>These ships and planes warn of the presence of attacking raiders, on the sea, under the sea, and above the sea. The danger from these raiders is, of course, greatly lessened if their location is definitely known. . . . Our patrols are helping now to insure delivery of the needed supplies to Britain. All additional measures necessary to deliver the goods will be taken.<span class="citation" data-cites="rooseveltRadioAddressAnnouncing1950a"><sup>7</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Stetson Conn and Byron Fairchild, <em>The Western Hemisphere: The Framework of Hemispheric Defense</em>, vol. 12, part 1, United States Army in World War II (Washington, D.C.: Office of the Chief of Military History, 1960), 92.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Chief of Naval Operations to Bureau of Ships, February 17, 1941, RG 19, box 66, fldr JJ5-(7), National Archives and Records Administration.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>United States Navy, <em>The Bluejackets’ Manual</em> (Annapolis: United States Naval Institute, 1940), <a href="https://archive.org/details/bluejacketsmanua00mcle/page/n5/mode/2up">https://archive.org/details/bluejacketsmanua00mcle/page/n5/mode/2up</a>; <em>Signal Card</em> (London: Admiralty, 1937), <a href="https://archive.org/details/b.-r.-232-signal-card-1937/mode/2up">https://archive.org/details/b.-r.-232-signal-card-1937/mode/2up</a>.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Chief of Naval Operations to Bureau of Ships, February 17, 1941.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>Supply Officer, USS Prairie, <span>“Invoice,”</span> May 6, 41AD, RG 19, box 135, fldr DD145(vol. 1), National Archives and Records Administration; Commandant, Norfolk Navy Yard to Bureau of Ships, April 1, 1941, RG 19, box 66, fldr JJ5-(7), National Archives and Records Administration.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn6"><p>Franklin D. Roosevelt, <span>“Address to Annual Awards Dinner of Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences--February 27, 1941,”</span> in <em>Public Papers and Addresses of Franklin Delano Roosevelt, 1941 Volume</em>, vol. 10, 13 vols. (New York: Harper &amp; Brothers, 1950), 40--42.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn7"><p>Franklin D. Roosevelt, <span>“Radio Address Announcing the Proclamation of an Unlimited National Emergency---May 27, 1941,”</span> in <em>Public Papers and Addresses of Franklin Delano Roosevelt, 1941 Volume</em>, vol. 10, 13 vols. (New York: Harper &amp; Brothers, 1950), 187--194.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>US strategy</category>
  <category>Navy</category>
  <category>UK strategy</category>
  <category>Neutrality</category>
  <category>Greer</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/flags/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Panic and confidence</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/wigmore/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Barrie A. Wigmore has an article of 1987 asking whether the gold panic of early 1933 was caused by fears of devaluation, to which he answers “yes.”<span class="citation" data-cites="wigmoreWasBankHoliday1987a"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
<p>But immediately on taking office, Roosevelt began the process of devaluing, and the panic ended. Here’s Wigmore’s own data of daily gold holdings in the New York Federal Reserve Bank, charted.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/wigmore/wigmore_gold.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Chart showing the NY Fed’s gold holdings falling before Roosevelt’s inauguration, then immediately rebounding.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Wigmore’s argument is that Roosevelt’s immediate actions might have done something to restore confidence, but not much.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>There is no doubt that his inaugural speech, his fireside chat about the banking system, the various measures he rushed through Congress, and his general ability to take command had a very favorable impact on confidence. Measurement of this impact is highly subjective, but intuitively it cannot be a large part of the explanation.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And yet depositors brought much of the gold they had withdrawn back to Federal Reserve banks over the course of March—before Roosevelt’s April 5 order requiring them to do it. Indeed, as you can see from the chart, the steepest rise in gold holdings comes between the inauguration and the fireside chat.</p>
<p>During that time, in his first presidential press conference, on March 8, 1933, Roosevelt allowed as how, according to a definition of the gold standard he pulled from the newspaper, the United States wasn’t on it at the moment, shied away from the term “controlled inflation,” and then almost immediately said,</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>What you are coming to now really is a managed currency, the adequateness of which will depend on the conditions of the moment. It may expand one week and it may contract another week. That part is all off the record.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>A reporter asked if they could print “that part—managed?” Roosevelt replied, “No, I think not.” A little later a reporter pressed him further on what he meant.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Q When you speak of a managed currency, do you speak of a temporary proposition or a permanent system?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>THE PRESIDENT: It ought to be part of the permanent system—that is off the record—it ought to be part of the permanent system so we don’t run into this thing again.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Two days later, when he announced the plan for reopening banks, he noted this would include all usual banking functions—</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Except, of course, for as to gold. That is a different thing. I am keeping my finger on gold.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>These press conferences are now online <a href="http://www.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/_resources/images/pc/pc0183.pdf">here</a> as they were not when I was writing <em>The Money Makers,</em> in which I discuss this period.<span class="citation" data-cites="rauchwayMoneyMakersHow2015"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
<p>In any case, it looks as though Roosevelt was certainly letting the information get out, albeit off the record, that he wanted a permanent system of managed currency and that he wasn’t allowing gold convertibility—and yet, during that time, depositors brought an awful lot of gold back into the Federal Reserve banks. It seems to me that confidence in the new administration’s actions—the first stages of a devaluation—restored some confidence even though they constituted precisely what people were supposed to have feared.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Barrie A. Wigmore, <span>“Was the Bank Holiday of 1933 Caused by a Run on the Dollar?”</span> <em>Journal of Economic History</em> 47, no. 3 (September 1987): 739--755.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Eric Rauchway, <em>The Money Makers: How Roosevelt and Keynes Ended the Depression, Defeated Fascism, and Secured a Prosperous Peace</em> (New York: Basic Books, 2015).↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>Gold</category>
  <category>Monetary policy</category>
  <category>New Deal recovery</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/wigmore/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Book tripleversary</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/tripleversary/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>While doing a <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/AskHistorians/comments/187kiyq/hello_im_eric_rauchway_a_historian_of_the_new/?rdt=53843">Reddit AMA for <em>Myth America,</em></a> in which I have a chapter on pernicious myths about the New Deal, I received <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/AskHistorians/comments/187kiyq/comment/kbfqmwp/">a question about <em>Murdering McKinley,</em></a> reminding me that book is twenty years old this year.<span class="citation" data-cites="rauchwayNewDeal2022a rauchwayMurderingMcKinleyMaking2003a"><sup>1</sup></span> A quick glance at <a href="http://htmlpreview.github.io/?https://github.com/erauchway/cv_pub/blob/main/rauchway_cv.html">my c.v.</a> told me that by a coincidence of timing, that means <em>The Great Depression and the New Deal: A Very Short Introduction</em> is fifteen years old, and <em>Winter War: Hoover, Roosevelt, and the First Clash over the New Deal</em> is five.<span class="citation" data-cites="rauchwayGreatDepressionNew2008 rauchwayWinterWarHoover2018"><sup>2</sup></span> These arbitrary digital anniversaries don’t mean a thing, except that we make them so, which is no reason not to. So here are some thoughts, which are mainly for me before I forget them.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/tripleversary/tr_fdr.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Franklin Roosevelt (at the far right of the photo, in profile looking left, wearing a straw boater) at a reception for Theodore Roosevelt (middle left, facing forward) on the former president’s return from Africa in 1910. FDR Presidential Library.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>First, these are easily the three most popular of my books. That popularity owes to different causes. The VSI is in a well known series with a good reputation. The VSI and <em>Winter War</em> happened to appear shortly before moments when their topics seemed relevant (<a href="https://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=95737884">the Great Economic Unpleasantness of the late Bush administration</a> and <a href="https://www.vox.com/policy-and-politics/21563753/2020-election-trump-biden-transition-fdr-hoover">the Trump–Biden transition,</a> respectively). <em>Murdering McKinley</em> hadn’t either of those advantages, but Brian Lamb did like it for <a href="https://booknotes.org/Watch/177827-1/Eric-Rauchway">Booknotes.</a></p>
<p>All three of them came out of definite ideas that then changed in significantly in the process of researching and writing, though for different reasons.</p>
<p><em>Murdering McKinley</em> started out of my sense that the transition from McKinley to Theodore Roosevelt was much more consequential than then-current historiography supposed, and the willingness of Thomas LeBien, then an editor at Hill and Wang, to believe I could write it relatively quickly and well. With my reading of the Vernon Briggs papers in the Massachusetts Historical Society, the book morphed into a kind of social scientific detective story. For the most part the narrative looks over Briggs’s shoulder as he tries to figure out Czolgosz’s motives. Owing to the amorphous state of psychiatry at the time, Briggs looked into a wide range of possibilities, and his investigation of Czolgosz took him in turn into almost every troubled corner of American life at around 1900. Everywhere he looked he could see motives, which in the end meant he couldn’t know what <em>the</em> motive was: almost every way you could say Czolgosz had suffered, so had millions of other Americans—but he was the one who pulled the trigger.</p>
<p>I remain reasonably happy with the book although if I had it to do again I would give more attention to foreign policy. Czolgosz did at one point indicate dissatisfaction with the hypocrisy of US colonization of the Philippines (among the many other aspects of American society with which he was unhappy), and given that the book came out just as the Iraq War was beginning, it would have been a useful time for historical reflection on that episode.</p>
<p>The <em>Very Short Introduction</em> came about because Oxford University Press editor Susan Ferber asked me if I’d like to do a VSI on the Great Depression. I had just done <em>Blessed Among Nations</em> which, with <em>Murdering McKinley,</em> established that I was willing to write about matters like the tariff and the gold standard and the mess left of the US economy after the Great War. Susan must have thought that caring about all that stuff was a good qualification for writing about the slump of 1929–1933, even if I hadn’t yet written directly about that period. I wanted to do it because I was then thinking about writing a book that would end with the 1930s, so it would be useful to me.</p>
<p>The VSI series was already well established in the British headquarters of OUP, but this was going to be one of the first volumes commissioned by the US office, and there was some uncertainty about format—whether it would have scholarly apparatus, and so forth—but the key thing was, it would be Very Short, as the titles indicate. There was a strict word count, which I don’t remember, but it was small; nevertheless I had barely thought about it before I went back to Susan and said I wanted it to cover the New Deal as well as the Great Depression. She said yes: as long as I stuck within the word count.</p>
<p>The book reflects the state of historiography at the time and I would certainly write it differently if I could write it now. But maybe then it wouldn’t be as popular. I was determined to integrate as much of the history of the New Deal done in departments of economics as I could with the history done in departments of history, and that led to a book that did indeed have perhaps more to say about tariffs and the gold standard and public works policies than most. It reflects the good work done by then-beginning historians of the New Deal, like Andrew W. Cohen, Meg Jacobs, and Jason Scott Smith.</p>
<p>It also reflects the interpretations of the two major New Deal historians of the 1990s, Alan Brinkley and David M. Kennedy. And while including Brinkley’s observations about the broader possibilities of the 1930s, and Kennedy’s insistence on the continuity between the New Deal and the war, I wanted to go a bit further in crediting the New Deal itself; so much of the literature aimed at what it <em>hadn’t</em> done. So my contribution, I thought, was to emphasize—and expand a bit—John Kenneth Galbraith’s concept of countervailing power. The New Deal not only supported labor unions, but also workers, consumers, and farmers more broadly, as well as ill developed regions like the South and the intermountain West, and so forth, in rebalancing unbalanced markets; that was more than security—that was a lasting structural effect.</p>
<p>I got some comments about the VSI from established New Deal historians, who said various versions of “I couldn’t have written about it that succinctly,” which I chose to take as a compliment.</p>
<p>I also thought I should keep Franklin D. Roosevelt out of it as much as possible. I was not—and still don’t think I am—a presidential historian, and I understood the New Deal (like Progressivism) to result from much broader forces than the election of a single person. Still, those elections and those persons matter in funneling or focusing those factors. So you’ve got to talk about presidents and presidencies, even if you don’t want them to dominate the narrative unduly. Roosevelt scarcely appears in the VSI as a force in himself until the last chapter, which I think is probably a good way at least to begin thinking about the New Deal—as a product of long-pent forces released and given focus by his election, rather than the product of the Roosevelt White House per se—though ultimately one does have to reckon with him, just as Americans at the time did.</p>
<p>That need to reckon with what Roosevelt did, and didn’t, do led to <em>Winter War.</em> I worked on it with Lara Heimert at Basic Books, who had also edited my previous book, <em>The Money Makers,</em> about Roosevelt’s repeated reliance on monetary policy from 1933–1945. In the course of writing that book I became persuaded that, contrary to a lot of commentary, Roosevelt had a clear agenda going into November 1932 and that his actions between election and inauguration had to do with protecting and furthering that agenda. As with <em>Murdering McKinley,</em> I made a good archival find that enabled greater insight into Roosevelt’s campaign and embryonic administration. During some research at the Hoover Institution, I found some correspondence of Robert Jackson—not the later Supreme Court justice and Nuremberg prosecutor, but the political operator—in which Jackson mentioned his diary; I was able pretty easily to find the diary was archived at his alma mater, Dartmouth. And it contained some terrific material on how the campaign functioned, and what it was like to work with Roosevelt and his inner circle. Using that and the diaries of some Hoover aides—Edgar Rickard, Theodore Joslin, James MacLafferty—as well as that of Raymond Moley’s secretary, Celeste Jedel, I had a pretty good picture of the Democratic and Republican camps.</p>
<p>Roosevelt liked to compare himself to a football quarterback: he knew where he needed to go, and the rules for getting there, but whether he might pass, hand off, or run the ball himself remained open, and he liked to keep his options open until the last possible second. It seemed to me an apt comparison, in its emphasis on shifting tactics and even strategy, but clear ultimate aims.<sup>3</sup> He viewed the New Deal as a program to reinvigorate and improve democracy in the United States—reinvigorating and improving the economy was a first step in that direction, and it had to be done in a way that was broadly beneficial if people were to begin to trust Washington, DC, again. And from the start, he and his aides saw the New Deal in the context of a world where democracy was under threat; as Jackson wrote just before Roosevelt took office,</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The world situation is no better than here in the United States. The Japs are attacking China. In Germany. . . . the upstart Hitler, the rabble-rouser … is now Chancellor and demanding powers that will make him a dictator. . . . Such is the chaos that confronts Franklin Delano Roosevelt.<sup>4</sup></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I got some nice feedback from established Roosevelt biographers, and some historians seem to feel it helped them reconceptualize the New Deal and the administration’s relationship to its constituencies, which is gratifying. I hope it continues to appeal to students of the New Deal. It certainly informed how I wrote about the New Deal <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/04/16/opinion/fdr-new-deal.html">in my next book</a>—but <em>Why the New Deal Matters</em> doesn’t have a neat anniversary this year, so I’ll have to reflect on it another time.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Eric Rauchway, <span>“The New Deal,”</span> in <em>Myth America: Historians Take On The Biggest Legends and Lies About Our Past</em>, ed. Kevin M. Kruse and Julian E. Zelizer (New York: Basic Books, 2022), 141–53; Eric Rauchway, <em>Murdering McKinley: The Making of Theodore Roosevelt’s America</em> (New York: Hill and Wang, 2003).↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Eric Rauchway, <em>The Great Depression and the New Deal: A Very Short Introduction</em> (New York: Oxford University Press, 2008); Eric Rauchway, <em>Winter War: Hoover, Roosevelt, and the First Clash over the New Deal</em> (New York: Basic Books, 2018).↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>I know some historians hate sports analogies, but it is his, not mine; as for a wheelchair-using US president’s comparison of himself to a top athlete, that is left for analysts better suited to the topic than I am.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Robert Jackson diary, March 1, 1933.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <category>Historiography</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/tripleversary/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Istrian annexationists</title>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/europes2/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Thanks to <a href="https://staging.bsky.app/profile/davidwondrich.bsky.social/post/3kfg2v36xfm2shttps://staging.bsky.app/profile/davidwondrich.bsky.social/post/3kfg2v36xfm2s">David Wondrich</a> and <a href="https://staging.bsky.app/profile/kschultz.bsky.social/post/3kfgrs2qmma2f">Ken Schultz</a> I now know cshapes has an error regarding interwar Italy, which it depicts without the Istrian peninsula. I have endeavored to correct it.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/europes2/eurs.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>A map of Europe before and after the Great War, this time with the Istrian peninsula as part of Italy.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Maps</category>
  <category>Nazi strategy</category>
  <category>Corrections</category>
  <category>Great War</category>
  <category>Geography</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/europes2/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Declaration of Panama</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/panama/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Franklin Roosevelt told George VI during the king’s visit to the United States early in June 1939 that the Americans planned to control an area extending five hundred miles east of the U.S. coast, if it could use bases at Bermuda and Trinidad; by the end of the month, the president was meeting with the British ambassador, Ronald Lindsay, to formalize the request for leases at Bermuda, Trinidad, and St.&nbsp;Lucia.<span class="citation" data-cites="baptisteBritishGrantAir1976a"><sup>1</sup></span> In retrospect we can identify these plans as an early phase of what became Admiral Stark’s <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/greer_3_dog/index.html">Plan Dog,</a> providing for naval assistance to the Allies in the western Atlantic. Late in July, the Army asked for bases in Trinidad and Natal, Brazil; the Navy confirmed its need of bases, and on August 24, <a href="http://www.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/_resources/images/psf/b-psfc000062.pdf">Stark wrote Roosevelt</a> to confirm that leases were available in Trinidad and in Bermuda, where the US Navy would take over some or all of the facilities then operated by Pan American Airways and Imperial Airways. Two days later, the Soviet news agency TASS would issue the terms of the Nazi-Soviet Pact, allocating to the USSR a “special position” in the Baltics and the division of Poland between the two; the Germans and the Soviets began the invasion of Poland shortly afterward.</p>
<p>On September 4, the day after the British declaration of war on Germany, the United States finalized leases to bases in Bermuda, Trinidad, and St.&nbsp;Lucia, paying a rent of $500 a year for the site in Bermuda; on September 6, Stark directed the commander of the Atlantic squadron to maintain a patrol of 300 miles offshore, and to report the movements of foreign men-of-war. Some of the destroyers thus tasked went to Newfoundland as the Grand Banks Patrol, with the acquiescence of the British government, to render assistance in emergencies and to observe and report movements of foreign warships.<span class="citation" data-cites="cressmanOfficialChronologyNavy2000a"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
<p>The Division of the American Republics in the U.S. State Department asked the Office of the Geographer to prepare maps with 300-mile radiuses laid out from the outermost limits of the American Republics, and sent that map to the White House, where the president selected the points of a zone defined by those varius circles, and returned it to the geographer with a request to neaten up the map <a href="https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1939v05/map-panama">thus defined.</a> The Declaration of Panama, of October 2, 1939, <a href="https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1939v05/pg_36">formalized that zone.</a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/panama/panama_d.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Map of the Panama Declaration, made with R and ggplot because I could never find a good one available.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Britain allowed unlimited U.S. overflight of the Bahamas after the Panama Declaration. This declaration looked neutral and formally was neutral, though Roosevelt plainly intended it as a form of neutrality that would aid the Allies. As he told Lindsay’s replacement, Lord Lothian, on August 30, 1939, the declaration would allow</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>all the American republics to combine to patrol half the distance to the coast of Europe and the African coast to prevent entry by belligerent war vessels or acts of war. . . . that would be of great assistance to England and France because it would relieve strain on their navies and would make possible safe transport of food and war materials from Pan-American coasts say, to Halifax, whence they would be conveyed to Europe in Allied bottoms thus lessening the strain on shipping as a whole.<span class="citation" data-cites="baptisteBritishGrantAir1976a"><sup>3</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>With the adoption of the Neutrality Act of 1939 in November, this shipping would include arms bound for the Allies.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>F.A. Baptiste, <span>“The British Grant of Air and Naval Facilities to the United States in Trinidad, St. Lucia and Bermuda in 1939 (June–December),”</span> <em>Caribbean Studies</em> 16, no. 2 (July 1976): 14–16.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Robert J. Cressman, <em>The Official Chronology of the U.S. Navy in World War II</em> (Annapolis: Naval Institute Press, 2000), 2–3.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Baptiste, <span>“British Grant,”</span> 16.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>US strategy</category>
  <category>Nazis</category>
  <category>Geography</category>
  <category>Neutrality</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/panama/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Architecture after a Green New Deal, UCLA</title>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/gnd/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Here are my slides from my presentation at the rather wonderful conference, <a href="https://www.aud.ucla.edu/news-events/events/fall2023-aagnd-conference">“Architecture after a Green New Deal,”</a> at the UCLA Department of Architecture and Urban Design.</p>
<div class="columns v-center-container">
<div class="column" style="width:50%;">
<iframe height="480" width="640" src="https://erauchway.github.io/present/gnd_ucla.html">
</iframe>
</div><div class="column" style="width:50%;">

</div>
</div>
<p>My assignment was to talk a bit about the o.g. New Deal, so I took the opportunity to talk about how the Roosevelt administration used public works programs for political and ideological ends. That is, Roosevelt’s concept of a sample publicly owned facility as a “yardstick,” to determine fair pricing and operating procedures, was ideological; the use of a sufficiently large public works program to influence labor standards, wage practices, and the legitimacy of unions was an ideological purpose; Roosevelt’s own statement that direct employment would “help restore the close relationship with the people which is necessary to preserve our democratic form of government” was ideological, reflecting his view that public works programs could help to reverse the alienation endemic to the modern condition.<span class="citation" data-cites="rauchwayWhyNewDeal2021"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
<p>Moreover, the ubiquity of public works designed to foster community and edifying leisure pursuits constituted an ideological commitment to establish a right to the good life for everyone, regardless of station.</p>
<p>All of that constituted an imperative to design for democracy, more or less; I also discussed the way that the TVA in particular exemplified an imperative to design for sustainability.</p>
<p>You can see some of the visuals I assembled to argue the case on the slides.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Eric Rauchway, <em>Why the New Deal Matters</em> (New Haven: Yale University Press, 2021), 32.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>Public works</category>
  <category>Green New Deal</category>
  <category>TVA</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/gnd/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 10 Nov 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Mobilization, Philadelphia Navy Yard edition</title>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/pnavy_emp/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Just for fun, a quick visualization of the number of employees, clerical and mechanical, at the Philadelphia Navy Yard.<span class="citation" data-cites="mccauleyWarHistoryFourth1946a"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/pnavy_emp/pnavy_emp.png" class="img-fluid"></p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Data from E.S. McCauley, <em>The War History of the Fourth Naval District from December 7th, 1941</em> (Philadelphia: Fourth Naval District, 1946).↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>US mobilization</category>
  <category>Philadelphia Navy Yard</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/pnavy_emp/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 10 Nov 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Americans in a World at War, Washington History Seminar</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/blower/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Below are my comments, as prepared, from the Washington History Seminar session of October 16, 2023, if you’d like to read them. If you’d like to see the whole session as it actrually transpired, video is at <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IgK0oWftoTM">this link.</a> Thanks to Eric Arnesen, Christian Ostermann, and Rachel Wheatley for organizing the session on behalf of the American Historical Association and the Woodrow Wilson Center’s History and Public Policy Program.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/blower/blower.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Book jacket for Blower, <em>Americans in a World at War.</em></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<hr>
<p>I want first of all to congratulate Brooke on this book, which is as readable a work of history, and as fascinating a narrative, as I have come across in a long time.<span class="citation" data-cites="blowerAmericansWorldWar2023c"><sup>1</sup></span> I can assure you it will fill a spot on a number of my holiday gift lists this year, and I imagine it will do the same for many people listening; it is a handsome book and will, I suspect, be a welcome gift for the readers you know, so make a note wherever you make your notes about what to get people for the holidays.</p>
<p>It’s a beautifully conceived book: that is, it’s one thing to think of writing a book around the uncertain time in 1943 when it was not yet clear that the Allies would win the war, but it’s a stroke of genuine inspiration to ground that book in this particular, dramatic event—the crash of Pan Am’s <em>Yankee Clipper</em>—and to use the lives of the people on board to develop all the ways that uncertainty and that war manifested themselves in individual lives.</p>
<p>Perhaps still more extraordinary, it’s a good idea that is exceptionally well executed. You’ve pursued, methodically and carefully, a wide range of sources, familiarizing yourself with the histories of politics, business, law, theater, aviation, shipping, and much more. In so doing, you’ve demonstrated an active and empathetic historical imagination, an ability to envision and then to encompass the strange old world of a vanished past.</p>
<p>So the book is not only beautifully conceived, but carefully constructed, which is a rare combination indeed.</p>
<p>For the purposes of sparking further discussion, I’d like to highlight two points.</p>
<p>First, the book really does show you, as the title says it will, a variety of Americans experiencing the world at war—not just from 1939 or 1931, or whenever you date the beginning of the Second World War, but really from 1914 onward, as your section titles indicate. And so—one of the things I really like about his book is that it’s narrative, rather than argumentative; you show, rather than tell—but for the purposes of our discussion here it might be appropriate for you to show your hand a bit more—so it seems to me you’re taking the position, taken by Winston Churchill and many others before you, that this is essentially the twentieth century’s Thirty Years War, a continuous event from 1914 through to 1945, and properly embraced as such.<span class="citation" data-cites="churchillGatheringStorm1950a"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
<p>Now, as I say that’s not an uncommon position to take, but it’s one that might have interpretive implications that, in a book like this, run under the surface, but I wonder if you could draw them out. How does it change your understanding of the Second World War to say that it’s really of a piece with the First?</p>
<p>So that’s my first question.</p>
<p>Okay, now for a second point. I’ve been very complimentary to this point, so I hope you won’t mind the least critical remark possible: I don’t think you needed to be even a tiny bit defensive, as I did think you were in the closing “note on method,” about writing a book about the Second World War. I think this is a subject that falls squarely into the category of “things that are endlessly popular because they are, in fact, endlessly interesting.” You would have had to apologize, perhaps, if you’d written a book that simply trundled over known territory and known evidence—which of course many people do. Which is why, for example, when Max Hastings wrote his one-volume survey in 2011 he set himself the challenge of using “relatively obscure anecdotage at the expense of justly celebrated personal recollections,” as he put it.<span class="citation" data-cites="hastingsInfernoWorldWar2011a"><sup>3</sup></span></p>
<p>Now, the structure of your book leads you to all kinds of areas and byways which do this naturally, that is, you follow the people’s stories where they go—so we hear about the fascinatingly gray area of trade with neutral, but Axis-aligned, Spain, which we don’t often get to; we hear about some of the actual mechanics of Lend-Lease, which was a wonderful, world-wide system, a genuine logistical achievement, which is usually just sort of waved at. When you talk about some of Frank’s broadcasts, you talk about the challenge he faced in trying to “make real” the complex web of connections in the Pacific world, this legacy of empire transformed by the exigencies of war. You get a lot of wonderful anecdotage of your own because of it. I was especially taken with the sad side effect of the Nazi-Soviet Pact on Tamara’s production—that is, “Dancing Stalin would have to be cut.” What a wonderful line.</p>
<p>I’m curious, though: in writing a book about people to whom, for the most part, the war is happening—they are <em>Americans <strong>In</strong> a World At War,</em> not “waging a world war,” or something like that—which I think correctly describes the felt experience of most Americans, that this war happened to them. And that effect is I think amplified by your choice of date; after all, this crash happens, and the book ends, just at the point when the United States really began to take much more of a leading role in the war.</p>
<p>So that’s my second question: what do you think it does for our understanding of the Second World War, to narrate it more as an event that happened to Americans, rather than one in which they were in the drivers’ seat?</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Brooke L. Blower, <em>Americans in a World at War: Intimate Histories from the Crash of Pan Am’s Yankee Clipper</em> (New York: Oxford University Press, 2023).↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Winston S. Churchill, <em>The Gathering Storm</em> (London: The Reprint Society, 1950), ix.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Max Hastings, <em>Inferno: The World at War, 1939–1945</em> (New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 2011), xix.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/blower/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>You didn’t build that</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/willow/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>There’s a pivotal moment in <em>Ford v. Ferrari</em> when Henry Ford II explains why the American automaker is going to defeat the Italian one.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><video src="fvf_trim.mp4" class="img-fluid" controls=""><a href="fvf_trim.mp4">Video</a></video></p>
<figcaption>Go ahead, Carroll. Go to war.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It’s a great scene as played (by Tracy Letts and Matt Damon) and it’s a great scene as written, by Jez Butterworth, John-Henry Butterworth, and Jason Keller.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/willow/fvf.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>From the <a href="https://assets.scriptslug.com/live/pdf/scripts/ford-v-ferrari-2019.pdf">shooting script</a> of <em>Ford v. Ferrari.</em></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’d be lying if I claimed I didn’t enjoy it, or the rest of the movie. But it is, of course, total nonsense in any number of ways.</p>
<p>The germ of truth there is that Ford did build a lot of B-24 Liberator bombers at the Willow Run plant it operated in Ypsilanti, Michigan. David M. Kennedy says about half the 18,000 or so Liberators built during the war came from Willow Run, and that at peak efficiency, the plant turned out one every sixty-three minutes.<span class="citation" data-cites="kennedyFreedomFearAmerican1999a"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/willow/willow_run.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>B-24s on the Willow Run assembly line. Library of Congress.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>So Willow Run was run by Ford and it did build a lot of bombers that were vital to the Eighth Air Force’s bombing campaign in Europe. Especially before D-Day, the long-range B-24 presented the best hope of striking deep into the heart of the continent. (Although if you know anything about the Ploesti raid, you know that hope was far too costly to realize until long-range fighters were generally available.)</p>
<p>But of course, (A) about half the B-24s is nowhere near three-fifths of the bombers and (B) the bombing campaign didn’t defeat Hitler, though it certainly made a difference.</p>
<p>Maybe most important, Ford didn’t build the plant. Let’s look at <a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/uiug.30112055484221?urlappend=%3Bseq=190%3Bownerid=32088860-189">the relevant page in the report on <em>War Industrial Facilities Authorized July 1940–August 1945.</em></a><span class="citation" data-cites="unitedstatescivilianproductionadministrationWarIndustrialFacilities1946a"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/willow/wr_fund.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The relevant part of the relevant page from <em>War Industrial Facilities Authorized July 1940–August 1945.</em></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Maybe the writing there is a bit small. It says, “Willow Run Airplane Factory, Ypsilanti Mich, New Plant; Heavy Bombers, B-24, Additional sub-assemblies.” Then it says, “Total cost, $94,898”—that’s in thousands of dollars, so about $95 million. Then it says that of the total cost of $94,898,000, the public funds contributed were $94,898,000. In other words, all of it. As you can see, under “Privately financed,” there is the entry “–”.</p>
<p>Mark Wilson did his best to make this point in <em>Destructive Creation,</em> but I guess the <em>Ford v. Ferrari</em> writers didn’t read it. Wilson notes that not only did the federal government foot the bill for this, as it did for much wartime construction, it actively ran the programs, setting costs, specification, laboring conditions, and lots more. To use the case of the B-24 as a continuing example, the bomber was originally developed by Consolidated Aircraft of San Diego, and Roosevelt administration officials grew dissatisfied with its progress in 1941. One wrote that “I have never seen so large an outfit run as ‘haphazardly’ as this one.”<span class="citation" data-cites="sittersonAircraftProductionPolicies1946a"><sup>3</sup></span> So, as Wilson notes, the administration edged out Consolidated’s CEO, facilitated the firm’s takeover by Vultee and the installation of Tom Girdler (formerly of Republic Steel) to run it.<span class="citation" data-cites="wilsonDestructiveCreationAmerican2016a"><sup>4</sup></span> Girdler, <em>Time</em> <a href="https://content.time.com/time/subscriber/article/0,33009,772968,00.html">alleged,</a> had by then “made his peace with Franklin Roosevelt and the C.I.O.”</p>
<p>So no, it wouldn’t be right to say that “Roosevelt beat Hitler,” of course. But it’s not right to say that Willow Run was exactly Henry Ford’s doing, either.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>David M. Kennedy, <em>Freedom from Fear: The American People in Depression and War, 1929–1945</em> (New York: Oxford University Press, 1999), 653–54.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>United States, Civilian Production Administration, <em>War Industrial Facilities Authorized July 1940–August 1945</em> (Washington, D.C.: Civilian Production Administration, 1946).↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>J. Carlyle Sitterson, <em>Aircraft Production Policies Under the National Defense Advisory Commission and Office of Production Management, May 1940 to December 1941</em> (Washington, D.C.: War Production Board, 1946), 153.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Mark Wilson, <em>Destructive Creation: American Business and the Winning of World War II</em> (Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 2016), 209.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>US mobilization</category>
  <category>B-24</category>
  <category>Movies</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/willow/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Wine grape varieties in California</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/wine_var/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The fine folks at AAWE posted <a href="https://staging.bsky.app/profile/wineecon.bsky.social/post/3kb6i5vhfew2x">a chart a week ago,</a> showing how as recently as 1960, Bordeaux was planted mainly to white grapes, perhaps contrary to one’s modern preconceptions, which reminded me of some data we had kicking around here, on the course of California’s wine grape plantings. Below, a chart—which I couldn’t have made without gracious help from Kieran Healy—showing the pattern of California wine-grape planting between repeal and the Judgment of Paris in 1976.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/wine_var/wine_var.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Acres planted to wine grape varieties in California.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The varieties you might associate with high-end California wines—the ones California vintners used to win the Judgment of Paris blind taste-test by emulating Bordeaux whites and reds—don’t really appear until they have a renaissance starting in the 1950s. The varieties at the top of the chart are those bred by UC Davis viticulturist Harold Olmo, as grapes that would make reasonably good wine and also thrive in California’s valley heat. What you see at the bottom, in terms of the varieties that were being grown at the time of repeal, is a certain amount of selection—Grenache and Colombard increase, Alicante Bouschet decreases—and also of consolidation, as a smaller number of winemakers work to meet the demands of an increasing consumer market.</p>
<p>These data were originally collected as part of a joint effort among the Agricultural Adjustment Administration, Bureau of Agricultural Economics, Works Progress Administration, and the state of California Department of Agriculture, for AAA statistical publication no. 1.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/wine_var/IMG_6102.JPG" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>AAA statistical publication no. 1</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Wine</category>
  <category>Prohibition</category>
  <category>Repeal</category>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>UC Davis</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/wine_var/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Field on the New Deal recovery</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/field_nd/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In addressing various arguments against the New Deal, I’ve generally cited Alexander Field’s fine (and wonderfully titled) <em>A Great Leap Forward.</em><span class="citation" data-cites="fieldGreatLeapForward2011a"><sup>1</sup></span> I’ve never cited his franker argument from <em>Challenge,</em> which somehow seems relevant today:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The consequences of putting a political party that frequently disparaged government in charge of providing essential government services became clear, however, in the federal government’s response to Hurricane Katrina. While the micropolitics may have seemed like a win for ideologically driven Republicans—provision of shoddy government services could reinforce the claim that only the private sector is able to provide decent services—the philosophy eventually turned a cropper at the polls and has been decisively rejected. It is clear that the American public wants well-thought-out government programs and policies, competently executed.<span class="citation" data-cites="fieldGreatDepressionNew2009a"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>So far as the argument about the New Deal goes, Field addresses the “misconceptions and frankly silly claims” he’s seen made “by both economists and non-economists.” Did the New Deal see off the Great Depression altogether? No, but</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Although they did not restore us to full employment until the war, New Deal fiscal policies nevertheless operated in the right direction through Roosevelt’s first term.<span class="citation" data-cites="fieldGreatDepressionNew2009a"><sup>3</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>He goes on to note that the often cited argument by Ohanian is “unpersuasive,” inasmuch as—for all its shortcomings—the NRA did do its part in “arresting deflation” and anyway in no way constitutes the whole of the New Deal.<span class="citation" data-cites="fieldGreatDepressionNew2009a"><sup>4</sup></span></p>
<p>Field concludes—this is 2009—that Barack Obama’s key advisors, notably Lawrence Summers and Tim Geithner, “have been too deferential toward Wall Street.” And he likens “New Deal denialism, as some have called it,” to creationism; that is, that it has no more proper relation to economics as a science than creationism does to biology.<span class="citation" data-cites="fieldGreatDepressionNew2009a"><sup>5</sup></span></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/field_nd/bizcycles_redone.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Index of industrial production 1919–1940, with shaded areas showing recessions.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Anyway, it seems like a good enough reason to put up the latest version of a graph I commonly use, depicting U.S. business cycles over the course of the interwar period, using the monthly series of the index of industrial production. The collapse of 1929–1933 is obvious, as is the sharp turn-around in March 1933, and the improvement over the course of the New Deal, with the exception of the 1937–1938 recession.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Alexander Field, <em>A Great Leap Forward: 1930s Depression and U.S. Economic Growth</em> (New Haven: Yale University Press, 2011).↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Alexander Field, <span>“The Great Depression, the New Deal, and the Current Crisis,”</span> <em>Challenge</em> 52, no. 4 (July 2009): 95.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Field, <span>“Great Depression,”</span> 99.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Field, <span>“Great Depression,”</span> 99.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>Field, <span>“Great Depression,”</span> 104.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal denialism</category>
  <category>Economists</category>
  <category>New Deal recovery</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/field_nd/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Price levels and the Nazi vote</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/nsdap/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>People will commonly blame the Weimar hyperinflation for the rise to power of the Nazi party, disregarding the ten-year lag and the intervening Great Depression, an episode of severe deflation. Recently one historian set forth a “precise mechanism” for how inflation produced antisemitism:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>In stable times, we expect each partner in a commercial transaction to believe that the price was fair, and that both sides benefit from the exchange. I buy a meal that satisfies my hunger, and the innkeeper in return has money that can be used to satisfy their needs. When prices move [sic; it should say “rise”], I am upset by having to pay more. The innkeeper is angry because the money I have given no longer buys so many goods. We both think that we have lost out in the transaction, [to this point, the characterization seems fine, if naïve: it’s in the next word that I begin to disagree] and that we have been manipulated by some sinister force. We also feel guilty for taking advantage of others—getting rid of our banknotes as soon as possible. We start to think that we are behaving in a speculative and grasping way. Non-Jewish Germans after the First World War in the middle of the currency disorder thus took up activities that they associated with Jewish actions, hated themselves for their breach of traditional norms, and externalized that powerful emotion by blaming the groups associated with finance and money.<span class="citation" data-cites="jamesSevenCrashesEconomic2023a"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>It seems to me that this explanation fails on two grounds. First, unless you already associate Jews with “speculative and grasping” behavior and are prone to see them as involved in sinister conspiracies to do with money and finance—unless, that is, you are already an antisemite—there is no reason for inflation to lead to extreme antisemitism. The problem isn’t inflation, it’s antisemitism.</p>
<p>Second, if this the mechanism, then shouldn’t it be reversed by deflation? In those transactions, the author’s non-Jewish German should be grateful to have to part with less money than previously; the author’s innkeeper should be pleased to be able to buy more with his money than before; both should be happy that the groups they associate with finance and money have treated them thus . . . yes, well, I grant it’s implausible—<em>because we’re talking about a deeply antisemitic culture.</em> The fault lies not with rising prices, but with antisemitism.</p>
<p>Moreover, of course, it’s not the Weimar hyperinflation that correlates with the increasing power of Nazism. It’s the deflation of the Great Slump, 1928 (in Germany) to 1933.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/nsdap/germanelec_cpi.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Chart showing the correlation between NSDAP vote share and falling prices; hyperinflation goes off the top of the chart because otherwise it would be unreadable.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Which is why, of course, the economist George Warren observed at the time, “It seems to be a choice between a rise in prices or a rise in dictators.”<span class="citation" data-cites="rauchwayMoneyMakersHow2015"><sup>2</sup></span></p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Harold James, <em>Seven Crashes: The Economic Crises That Shaped Globalization</em> (New Haven: Yale University Press, 2023), 108.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Eric Rauchway, <em>The Money Makers: How Roosevelt and Keynes Ended the Depression, Defeated Fascism, and Secured a Prosperous Peace</em> (New York: Basic Books, 2015), 80.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Nazis</category>
  <category>Inflation</category>
  <category>Deflation</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/nsdap/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The only thing worse than being assimilated to the Borg</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/borg/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The <em>Atlantic</em> ran <a href="https://www-stage.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2023/09/books3-database-generative-ai-training-copyright-infringement/675363/">an article</a> or <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2023/08/books3-ai-meta-llama-pirated-books/675063/">two</a> about the Books3 database, into which some 180,000 books were fed to form a corpus for Meta’s large language model LLaMa, among other purposes. There’s <a href="https://full-stack-search-prod.vercel.app">an app</a> that lets you search for an author’s name to see if it’s in there. And, well:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/borg/borg.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>A screenshot demonstrating the presence of my first three New Deal books in Books3.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I haven’t fully thought through (nor, I am heartened to see, have legal scholars) the implications of one’s books being thus used. But I was not best pleased that Meta had apparently acquired the text of my books from a site containing pirated material. After all, surely Mark Zuckerberg can afford the possibly dozens of dollars it would cost to acquire these three texts. Why must the heralds of the future be simultaneously grandiose and ungenerous?</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <category>Madness</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/borg/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What did U.S. Voters Want from the New Deal in 1932?</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/po_32/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I published an article in 2019 arguing that “the New Deal was on the ballot in 1932”—that is, that Roosevelt “ran on the New Deal and was elected on it; while 1933 predates modern polling, we may suppose that the voters had a reasonable expectation he would deliver it.”<span class="citation" data-cites="rauchwayNewDealWas2019a"><sup>1</sup></span> My view is contrary to a conventional wisdom which held that Roosevelt did not say much of consequence about the New Deal. I argue that the much tougher burden of proof lies with people who want to prove a negative—that Roosevelt didn’t say anything about key elements of the New Deal—and if you can point to speeches in which he did say things—about support for massively increased public works programs, or stock market regulation, or a lower tariff—then it’s pretty clear where one should come down on the question. But I didn’t have direct evidence about what voters thought, just what Roosevelt said and how vehemently Hoover opposed it.</p>
<p>As it turns out, at about the same time as my article appeared in <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/modern-american-history/article/new-deal-was-on-the-ballot-in-1932/8CDA127BFA5DACAD00893104E04CCA12"><em>Modern American History,</em></a> a scholar named Helmut Norpoth published <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/ps-political-science-and-politics/article/american-voter-in-1932-evidence-from-a-confidential-survey/9C75907376FD0D45811C4357ADD7E8AE">an article in PS</a> discussing an internal poll conducted by the market research firm J. David Houser for the Hoover campaign close to the 1932 election and arguing that its results show</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>the Depression was not the dominant issue for American voters in the 1932 election as is commonly assumed. The American people overwhelmingly favored repeal [of Prohibition]. . . . Radical measures such as providing unemployment benefits and a government takeover of the economy enjoyed little support, even among Democrats. . . . Depression, where is thy sting?<span class="citation" data-cites="norpothAmericanVoter19322019a"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>It’s well known among scholars of public opinion polling that market research was closely related to the infant industry, and you can find a discussion of that in standard works.<span class="citation" data-cites="converseSurveyResearchUnited1987a"><sup>3</sup></span> So it’s quite reasonable to treat a survey conducted by a market resarch company as a kind of proto-opinion poll.</p>
<p>You would want to be careful, though. Looking at the poll, the author notes,</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>the Houser Poll inquired whether a respondent (or a family member) was unemployed and [sic; should be “or”] had lost money in a bank failure. It is true that unemployment was more common among FDR Defectors [i.e., people who voted for Hoover in 1928 and intended to vote for Roosevelt in 1932] than among Hoover Loyalists—whether personally or in one’s family—and so was losing money in bank failures (figure 4). Although these experiences may have driven some voters to FDR, the majority of Americans appears not to have been affected personally by the Depression.<span class="citation" data-cites="norpothAmericanVoter19322019a"><sup>4</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Figure 4, cited there, shows that among the “FDR Defectors,” 13 percent were unemployed, while among “Hoover Loyalists,” 8 percent were unemployed. The thing is, this was at a time when the unemployment rate, as best we can estimate, was around 23 percent.<span class="citation" data-cites="carterHistoricalStatisticsUnited2006a"><sup>5</sup></span> So it seems quite likely that the Houser respondents did not represent the overall populace—they were much less likely to be unemployed—and that characterizing their views as representative of “the majority of Americans” is unwarranted; certainly characterizing their experiences as showing who was affected personally by the Depression seems unwarranted. They suffered much less than the average American and we may suppose their attitudes diverged correspondingly from those of the average American.</p>
<p>At the same time, it’s useful to note what they did want from the government. I reproduce the article’s next chart, figure 5, here.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/po_32/norp_5.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Bar chart showing attitudes toward various possible policies for remedying the Depression.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Note that, as the author says, hardly anyone—FDR defector or Hoover loyalist—favored giving money to the unemployed or a government takeover of business. Neither Hoover nor Roosevelt favored these, either. Slightly over half of FDR defectors favored paying the veterans’ bonus, as against only sixteen percent of Hoover loyalists; Hoover emphatically opposed the bonus and, infamously, sent the army to burn out the bonus marchers’ encampment and tear gas the protesters, probably causing the death of an infant. Roosevelt didn’t support paying the bonus either (though, as he privately noted, he didn’t think the marchers ought to be gassed) but eventually the Democratic congress would vote for it and pass it over his veto.<span class="citation" data-cites="rauchwayWhyNewDeal2021"><sup>6</sup></span></p>
<p>More interesting, though, note what the FDR defectors favored by large margins: a lower tariff (56 percent), stock market regulation (67 percent), and spending more on public works (77 percent). And there’s clear daylight between FDR defectors and Hoover loyalists on these issues—just as there was clear daylight between Roosevelt and Hoover on the stump. Inasmuch as these issues—along with repeal of Prohibition—were key elements of the New Deal featured in Roosevelt’s speeches and campaign literature (as I discussed in the 2019 article), it seems like the New Deal messaging did get through to voters.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Eric Rauchway, <span>“The New Deal Was on the Ballot in 1932,”</span> <em>Modern American History</em> 2, no. 2 (July 2019): 202.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Helmut Norpoth, <span>“The American Voter in 1932: Evidence from a Confidential Survey,”</span> <em>PS</em> 52, no. 1 (January 2019): 14.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>See Jean M. Converse, <em>Survey Research in the United States: Roots and Emergence, 1890-1960</em> (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1987).↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Norpoth, <span>“American Voter in 1932,”</span> 17.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>Susan B. Carter et al., eds., <em>Historical Statistics of the United States, Earliest Times to the Present</em>, Millennial, 5 vols. (New York: Cambridge University Press, 2006), series Ba475.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn6"><p>On Hoover, Roosevelt, and the bonus march, see Eric Rauchway, <em>Why the New Deal Matters</em> (New Haven: Yale University Press, 2021), 25–33.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>Election of 1932</category>
  <category>Public opinion</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/po_32/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Bluesky “What’s History” Feed</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/bsky/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Awhile ago I set up a feed called <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/did:plc:6brknehpd7ecbvd56ko6mhlm/feed/aaaby3zazwhrq">“What’s History”</a> on Bluesky, the as-yet invite-only microblogging social media service that is a bit livelier than some and freer of unpleasantly trollish features than others.</p>
<p>Feeds are a Bluesky feature; essentially they allow you to curate your own algorithm. This one is simple: if you’re on a set list of approved posters, and you post using the card file box emoji 🗃, that post will show up in the feed. If you go to the feed at the link above, and “like” it, it will appear among your feeds; if you pin it, you can set it so it appears on your Bluesky homepage, like this. <strong>UPDATED TO ADD</strong> that I’ve amended the feed to include any post that uses the word “skystorians” to accommodate people who don’t care for emoji. So you can use either the card file box or skystorians to send a skeet to the feed.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/bsky/bsky_home.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Bluesky homepage, with “What’s History” next to Following and Mutuals feeds.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As you can see there, a user on the approved list can quote-skeet something that did not have the card file box emoji with the emoji, and have it stuck in the feed.</p>
<p>FAQ</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><em>Why “What’s History?”</em> The original Bluesky feed was called “What’s Hot,” and any post with a given number of likes (I think it was twelve?) would appear on the feed. Soon after, someone set up “What’s Science,” with an approved poster list and an emoji, so I followed suit with “What’s History.”</li>
<li><em>Why an emoji instead of a hashtag?</em> One character toward your total, instead of several.</li>
<li><em>Why <strong>that</strong> emoji?</em> I wanted something that looked like something relating to historical practice that wasn’t field specific and which people were very unlikely to post incidentally. The card file box, familiar to historians of more advanced ages (like me) as a place to store your notes and bibliography, seemed to fit the bill.</li>
<li><em>Why is the list of approved posters a “mute list”?</em> That list, <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/did:plc:6brknehpd7ecbvd56ko6mhlm/lists/3jzmymatqtf2u">here,</a> is as it says not for muting but to provide the basis for the feed. At the time of creating the list, a mute list was the only kind of list Bluesky recognized.</li>
<li><em>How can I set up my own feed?</em> Paul Musgrave has a good guide <a href="https://www.paulmusgrave.info/the-moderately-skilled-persons-guide-to-making-a-bluesky-feed/">here.</a></li>
<li><em>How can I get on the list?</em> Just @ me on Bluesky.</li>
<li><em>How can I get on Bluesky?</em> Someone on Bluesky can invite you.</li>
<li><em>Do I want to be on Bluesky?</em> Man, I don’t know, but I think a lot of historians missed the community provided by certain other sites, and an increasing number have shown up on Bluesky. There are a few journalists who are worth your time. Maybe someday soon there will be a substantial number of editors and publishers, too, and then it will begin to be a more useful professional network. More seem to be appearing all the time.</li>
<li><strong>ADDED: WHY DIDN’T IT WORK?</strong> Every now and then I get this one, and, well, ¯\_ (ツ)_/¯. If you’re on the list (again, <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/did:plc:6brknehpd7ecbvd56ko6mhlm/lists/3jzmymatqtf2u">here</a>) and you used the emoji, it should work! All I can plead is that it’s a beta site, I guess; sorry. I have noticed it does take a little time, sometime, especially on busy days. It is <strong>possible</strong> that it’s something to do with spacing around the emoji, i.e., that you need to have a space before and/or after, but I’m not sure.</li>
</ol>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <category>Madness</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/bsky/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Teflon Doug</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/macarthur/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Some <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/joekatz45.bsky.social/post/3k6qaya4cyy2e">current nonsense on social media</a> reminded me that Douglas MacArthur did have at least one substantial secret, about which historians now know pretty well thanks to the work of Carol M. Petillo.<span class="citation" data-cites="petilloDouglasMacArthurManuel1979a"><sup>1</sup></span> MacArthur received half a million dollars from Philippine president Manuel Quezon in early 1942, at just about the time MacArthur changed his mind about whether Quezon should be evacuated from Corregidor. As Petillo puts it,</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>MacArthur, one day after the transfer of funds was ordered, reversed his position and decided that indeed the president’s evacuation could be achieved. On February 20, just after he received verification of the transfer, this decision was carried out and Quezon headed south toward the unoccupied islands on the submarine <em>Swordfish.</em><span class="citation" data-cites="petilloDouglasMacArthurManuel1979a"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Petillo is scrupulous about not imputing causality, but the timing certainly should raise eyebrows. As she says, “we must ask if MacArthur’s ‘personal ties and devotion to the Philippine nation’ were influenced by half a million dollars.” She goes on to note that Washington had been apprised about the money and supposes that the general’s superiors were concerned that without such inducements, the “angry” MacArthur might therefore “refuse to follow orders.” Although Petillo doesn’t mention it here, they had good reason to be concerned, inasmuch as MacArthur had directly defied Herbert Hoover’s orders to stand down during the Bonus Army operation in 1932, and instead proceeded to empty and burn the encampments.<span class="citation" data-cites="lisioBlunderBecomesCatastrophe1967a"><sup>3</sup></span> Petillo also notes that MacArthur’s decision to free Manuel Roxas in 1944, in contrast to the other members of the collaborationist regime in the Philippines, might have had something to do with Roxas’s signature appearing on the order to pay the money.</p>
<p>Petillo’s discovery was not, and is not, unknown. It received coverage <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/archive/politics/1980/01/29/macarthur-given-500000/3ad863a3-8caa-4792-b038-d91bb3f804b4/">in the <em>Washington Post</em></a> at the time—unusual for articles in the <em>Pacific Historical Review,</em> estimable though that journal is. It’s also known that Dwight Eisenhower later refused a similar payment, saying he was sure it was legal, but there was significant <a href="https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/americanexperience/features/macarthur-secret-payment/">“danger of misapprehension or misunderstanding.”</a></p>
<p>Yet MacArthur, the disobeyer of presidential orders and the taker of secret payments from foreign governments for mysterious reasons, enjoys rather a good reputation.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Carol M. Petillo, <span>“Douglas MacArthur and Manuel Quezon: A Note on an Imperial Bond,”</span> <em>Pacific Historical Review</em> 48, no. 1 (February 1979): 107--117.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Petillo, <span>“MacArthur and Quezon,”</span> 114.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Donald J. Lisio, <span>“A Blunder Becomes Catastrophe: Hoover, the Legion, and the Bonus Army,”</span> <em>Wisconsin Magazine of History</em> 51, no. 1 (March 1967): 37--50.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>MacArthur</category>
  <category>Pacific</category>
  <category>Philippines</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/macarthur/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
