<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>a necessitous blog</title>
<link>https://erauchway.github.io/</link>
<atom:link href="https://erauchway.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>A blog about the era of the Roosevelt administration, 1933--1945</description>
<generator>quarto-1.8.27</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 08:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Unemployment in Puerto Rico, 1930–2010</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/2026-02-09_pr_unemp/pr_unemp.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As I’ve indicated before, despite the profound and ultimately catastrophic conflict with the Nationalists during the 1930s, the New Deal had <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/pr_wages/pr_wages.html">a materially salutary effect</a> on Puerto Rico in many respects. That effect extended beyond the time of the New Deal proper; the enactment of the Puerto Rico Labor Relations Act in 1945, and its amendment in 1947, were directly influenced by the Wagner Act, and the economic development programs of Luis Muñoz Marín were too.<span class="citation" data-cites="barelaPuerto1965"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
<p>Here’s another thing to think about: unemployment in Puerto Rico as against the US overall.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/2026-02-09_pr_unemp/unemp_pr.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Chart showing convergence in unemployment over the 1930s.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>There’s a lot going on here, but it is true that during the New Deal, the Puerto Rico Emergency Relief Administration (from 1933) and then the Puerto Rico Reconstruction Administration (from 1935) had a definite impact on Puerto Rico’s economy. Even if by 1940 the territory’s economy remained largely agricultural (and indeed, largely devoted to the single crop of sugar) significant shifts had occurred: the agricultural sector shrank by about 8 percentage points, indicating a shift of workers into transportation, trade, services and government.<span class="citation" data-cites="dietzEconomic1986"><sup>2</sup></span> During the war rum became immensely profitable, owing to the nearly total shutdown of distilling in the 48 United States. Then after the wear a period of extended manufacturing growth began—although the proceeds, like the proceeds of the sugar trade in earlier years, tended to leave Puerto Rico rather than remain there.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Fred Barela, <em>The Puerto Rico Labor Relations Act: A State Labor Policy and Its Application</em> (Editorial Universitaria, 1965).↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>James L. Dietz, <em>Economic History of Puerto Rico: Institutional Change and Capitalist Development</em> (Princeton University Press, 1986), 176–77.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>Puerto Rico</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/2026-02-09_pr_unemp/pr_unemp.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The New Deal and Some Rockbound Republicans</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/2026-01-29_fc3/fc3.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In the summer of 1933, Hugh Auchincloss—a physician at Columbia Presbyterian—wrote Franklin Roosevelt to convey his colleagues’ view of the controversy over who should be commissioner of education in Puerto Rico, and concluded,</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I heard you speak last night and had a good deal of pleasure in being the only Republican who voted for you, in a crowd of rockbound Republicans who didn’t vote for you. You may be glad to know that every one of them were delighted with it and your ears would have tingled if you could have heard their comments.<span class="citation" data-cites="auchinclos1933-07-25"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Auchincloss was referring to <a href="http://www.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/_resources/images/msf/msf00662">the third of Roosevelt’s “Fireside Chats,”</a> addressing what had been done in the hundred days. This was one of several occasions on which Roosevelt rejected the idea of a recovery solely to previous conditions.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Now I come to . . . a more lasting prosperity. I have said that we cannot attain that in a nation half boom and half broke. If all of our people have work and fair wages and fair profits, they can buy the products of their neighbors and business is good. But if you take away the wages and the profits of half of them, business is only half as good. It doesn’t help much if the fortunate half is very prosperous—the best way is for everybody to be reasonably prosperous.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And to get there, Americans had to address long-standing problems. Eliminate child labor. Raise wages. Shorten hours. Reduce farm production. Manage the currency—deflation made it so “the dollar was a different dollar from the one with which the average debt had been incurred.” Roosevelt also mentioned the Civilian Conservation Corps and the $3 billion voted for the Public Works Administration. Here, as on other occasions, he distinguished the “regular” expenses of government, which he cut, from these extraordinary ones. But he didn’t shy away from outlining the scale and scope of the extraordinary measures.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I have no sympathy with the professional economists who insist that things must run their course and that human agencies can have no influence on economic ills. One reason is that I happen to know that professional economists have changed their definition of economic laws every five or ten years for a very long time.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Hard to imagine Auchincloss’s “rockbound Republican” colleagues thrilling to that, but it was a dire time and people did want something better.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./babson_oh_yeah_36.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Page 36 of Edward Angly, Oh Yeah? indicating the esteem in which professional economists might have been held at the time. Click to enlarge."><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/2026-01-29_fc3/babson_oh_yeah_36.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Page 36 of Edward Angly, Oh Yeah? indicating the esteem in which professional economists might have been held at the time. Click to enlarge."></a></p>
<figcaption>Page 36 of Edward Angly, <em>Oh Yeah?</em> indicating the esteem in which professional economists might have been held at the time. Click to enlarge.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Hugh Auchincloss to Franklin D. Roosevelt, July 25, 1933, fldr <span>“Commissioner of Education, 20324,”</span> box 937, RG 350.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>Economists</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/2026-01-29_fc3/fc3.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Bit of the New Deal in the Philippines</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/2026-01-26_AAA_phils/aaa_philippines.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The New Deal in the territories <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/relief_pc/relief_st_terr.html">mostly applied to those US territories whose people were, by law, US citizens—Alaska, Hawaiʻi, Puerto Rico, and the Virgin Islands.</a> The Philippines didn’t fall into this category because they were supposed to become independent of the United States and by 1934 the Tydings–McDuffie Act had set a schedule for it. But one part of the New Deal did apply to the commonwealth—the Agricultural Adjustment Administration (AAA).</p>
<p>Early in 1933 Congress passed a Philippine independence act over Herbert Hoover’s veto. Hoover said he thought the islands weren’t ready for self-government but also told an aide he was “afraid” Congress would during his lame-duck period dispose of so many controversial issues (including repeal of Prohibition and the Agricultural Adjustment Act) that “Roosevelt will get out of an extra session of Congress in the spring”—and if that happened, Roosevelt wouldn’t have obviously taken responsibility for the Depression.<span class="citation" data-cites="hooverVeto1933 joslinDiary"><sup>1</sup></span> But Congress was determined to set the archipelago on the path to independence. The Philippine legislature vetoed the provision in large part because wrangling over the control of sugar prices remained unsettled; the Tydings-McDuffie Act of 1934 passed when an outline for a sugar program was mostly settled, and it provided broadly the same terms of independence as the 1933 law.<span class="citation" data-cites="kramerBlood2006"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./fdr_tm.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Roosevelt signs a proclamation recognizing the new Philippine Commonwealth, 1935. Library of Congress. Click to enlarge"><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/2026-01-26_AAA_phils/fdr_tm.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Roosevelt signs a proclamation recognizing the new Philippine Commonwealth, 1935. Library of Congress. Click to enlarge"></a></p>
<figcaption>Roosevelt signs a proclamation recognizing the new Philippine Commonwealth, 1935. Library of Congress. Click to enlarge</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>But the Philippines’s economy remained closely tied to that of the mainland United States and the Department of Agriculture determined that the AAA’s sugar program needed to go into force there, to levy a tax on processing sugar and payments to compensate growers for reducing production. Normally, farmers would agree to sign AAA contracts and those contracts would go to Washington to be processed for payment. But the Philippines were so far away it would take mabye three months to process payment. “Such delay would be fatal to the program,” M.L. Wilson (who was Mr.&nbsp;Domestic Allotment) wrote.<span class="citation" data-cites="wilson1934-04-09 rowleyML1970"><sup>3</sup></span> So the program would have to be administered in the commonwealth.</p>
<p>According to the summary report on the AAA, this program went into effect for about 18,200 Filipino producers and reduced the size of the archipelago’s sugar crop from about 1.6m tons to about 700,000 tons, in exchange for about $12.5m in benefit payments by 1936, when the Supreme Court voided the program.<span class="citation" data-cites="unitedstaAgricultural1936"><sup>4</sup></span></p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Herbert Hoover, <span>“Veto of a Bill Providing for the Independence of the Philippine Islands, January 13, 1933,”</span> in <em>Public Papers of the Presidents of the United States</em> (Government Printing Office, 1977), 1932–1933; Theodore Joslin, diary, HHL, January 17, 1933.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Paul A. Kramer, <em>The Blood of Government: Race, Empire, the United States, &amp; the Philippines</em> (University of North Carolina Press, 2006), 424.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>M.L. Wilson to Comptroller General, April 9, 1934, fldr <span>“Farm Relief - Sugar,”</span> box 1993; on Wilson see William D. Rowley, <em>M.L. Wilson and the Campaign for the Domestic Allotment</em> (University of Nebraska Press, 1970).↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>United States Department of Agriculture, <em>Agricultural Adjustment, 1933 to 1935</em> (Government Printing Office, 1936), 222.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>Territories</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/2026-01-26_AAA_phils/aaa_philippines.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>AI and students here (and maybe where you are)</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/2026_01_22_ai_students/AI and our students.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This is simply a post documenting the extent to which our students live in a world thick with AI.<sup>1</sup> My thoughts on its use for reading and writing probably won’t seem fresh to anyone<sup>2</sup> so this isn’t a post about that; I’m simply noting its ubiquity.<sup>3</sup></p>
<p>UC Davis provides affiliates with</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://servicehub.ucdavis.edu/servicehub?id=ucd_kb_article&amp;sys_id=a706700d6f9ce100bc4f8a20af3ee455&amp;spa=1">Google workspace accounts,</a> which means students have access to Gemini</li>
<li><a href="https://servicehub.ucdavis.edu/servicehub?id=ucd_kb_article&amp;sys_id=6a661eae6f5b65002f5fe811af3ee4b4&amp;spa=1">A Microsoft Office site license</a> which means students have access to Copilot</li>
<li>Access <a href="https://iet.ucdavis.edu/aggie-ai/chatgpt-edu/get-started">to ChatGPT</a></li>
<li>An OpenAI-powered local tool called <a href="https://iet.ucdavis.edu/aggie-ai/ai-tools/rocky">Rocky,</a> which I haven’t found to do much more than a sound google site search would do</li>
<li>Zoom with built-in <a href="https://iet.ucdavis.edu/aggie-ai/ai-tools/zoom-ai-companion">AI features</a></li>
</ul>
<p>To the best of my knowledge we do not have Claude Code freely available on campus, which is odd because it is the AI application IT people are most likely to tell you does, genuinely, work as advertised.</p>
<p>In addition to the above, many of our students have Apple products with Apple Intelligence. When they use the library website to access monographs, they are offered AI summaries by the database provider. And of course they can go further afield and get <a href="https://chat.deepseek.com/">other AI tools</a> on their own.</p>
<p>As you can see, our students can scarcely escape some kind of AI.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>“AI” is a misnomer and sales tactic and <a href="https://buttondown.com/apperceptive/archive/is-artificial-intelligence-as-a-term-per-se-racist/">possibly worse;</a> we should be talking about “large language models” or LLMs. But I feel like fighting the terminology battle is a losing proposition so I’m going to say “AI.”↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>tldr; (a) it <a href="https://royalsocietypublishing.org/rsos/article/12/4/241776/235656/Generalization-bias-in-large-language-model">doesn’t work</a> and <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-025-02853-8">maybe never will</a> and (b) if it did <a href="https://www.alfiekohn.org/article/ai/">you wouldn’t be learning anything</a>—see, I told you there wasn’t going to be anything original here.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>As my remark on Claude Code here indicates I am sensible of the possibility that there are specific tools which maybe do work—though not for reading or writing per se—and maybe even very well, and I want to think through that possibility before I write about it in another post.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <category>Madness</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/2026_01_22_ai_students/AI and our students.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Brief Remembrance of Dan Howe as a Colleague</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/2026-01-11_dwh/dwh.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://newsroom.ucla.edu/stories/in-memoriam-daniel-walker-howe-pulitzer-prize-winner-history-professor">Dan Howe</a> spoke with a deliberation that inspired in me both admiration and antsiness, with pauses indicating the care he was taking in formulating the phrase to come. Like many historians I first met Dan through his writing, which featured the precision of his speech while omitting the pauses. As an eager student I could take Dan’s insights at my own speed, reading with delight his accounts of the self-serious young American republic’s thinkers in action, as the Whigs seemed to me then. What Dan was doing, what my advisor George Fredrickson was doing, what a few other scholars were then doing (notably, Ann Douglas) excited me. They treated ideas like serious business. I wanted to do it too.</p>
<p>Dan had the sunniest temperament of any professor I have known. He had a wide ready smile that seemed to persist while he talked and even over the phone—even when he was possibly quite cross—you could hear the upturned corners of his mouth. Together with his broad chin and glasses, that smile made him look uncannily like Franklin Roosevelt, with whom he shared that impression of invariable cheer and also the capacity to deliver a sly jab, the more unexpected for the enduring smile.</p>
<p>Now that I am closer to Dan’s age then than to my own youth I can appreciate that as his junior colleague I must have seemed to him a bit like the cartoon dog Chester, hopping up and down and around, asking his methodical companion “what are we going to do today, Spike? what are we going to do?” Except, of course, Spike would be smiling.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/2026-01-11_dwh/spike.gif" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Chester and Spike (Spike should be smiling)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In another university Dan wouldn’t have had to spend as much time listening to me as he did, but there were, I think, only four post-holders in US history then and Dan was tasked with administering them. I have since learned that not all senior colleagues or administrators are as tolerant or willing to give young people free rein. But Dan was patient and supportive where many people might have been obstinate and discouraging. He let me try ambitious things.</p>
<p>Five or so years later—after we had both moved on—when Dan published <em>What Hath God Wrought,</em> the enjoyment with which I read the book brought back to me the happiness wth which I had first read Dan’s work. I am glad I got a chance to chat with him and congratulate him on it.</p>
<p>But I am always going to remember Dan for the way he spoke and how evidently happy he was for others to succeed. I will always remember both in the voice message he left for me, eight time zones away, when he called to tell me I had got the job—which I felt meant I was going to have an academic career after all.</p>
<p>“Hullo, Eric! this is Dan Howe. I’m calling with”—long, thoughtful pause; I expect he was deciding how discreet this recording had to be—“good news!” Sometimes he was; it seemed like he always wanted to be.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Professional</category>
  <category>Personal</category>
  <category>Oxford</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/2026-01-11_dwh/dwh.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Franklin Roosevelt Corollary to the Monroe Doctrine</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/2026-01-09_monroe_d/2026-01-09_monroe_d.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>On December 28, 1933, Franklin D. Roosevelt <a href="http://www.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/_resources/images/msf/msf00691">argued to the members of the Woodrow Wilson Foundation in Washington DC that</a> “the maintenance of law and the orderly processes of government in this hemisphere is the concern of each individual nation within its borders first of all. It is only if and when the failure of orderly processes affects the other nations of the continent that it becomes their concern; and the point to stress,” he underlined,</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>is that in such an event it becames the joint concern of a whole continent in which we are all neighbors.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Just a few days before, the United States had joined the other American nations at Montevideo in agreeing to a convention including the <a href="https://www.oas.org/juridico/english/treaties/a-40.html">provision,</a> “No state has the right to intervene in the internal or external affairs of another.” Roosevelt had already publicly stated <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/monroe_d/monroe_d.html">he wanted to get rid of the Platt Amendment,</a> guaranteeing the US right to intervene in Cuba; the Montevideo conference generalized that idea, and his speech in Washington extended it to a broad modification of the Monroe Doctrine.</p>
<p>Ernest Gruening, an anti-imperialist journalist and historian of Mexico who had served as an aide to the US delegation in Montevideo, wrote,</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>this epoch-making policy has gone far to remove the accumulated suspicion and fear inculcated by a generation of military and financial penetration. The Franklin Roosevelt extension of the Monroe Doctrine had replaced the Theodore Roosevelt intensification of that doctrine of 30 years ago.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It meant “the New Deal is being extended, as far as lies within our province, to the New World,” and that the administration was “giving up the pursuit of empire.”<span class="citation" data-cites="grueningNew1934"><sup>1</sup></span></p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Ernest Gruening, <span>“The <span>‘New Deal’</span> for Our Neighbors; the Roosevelt Administration Is Giving up the Pursuit of Empire,”</span> 1934, fldr <span>“Haiti - 1934 - Letters, papers,”</span> box 9, Gruening Papers, University of Alaska, Fairbanks.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>Good Neighbors</category>
  <category>Monroe Doctrine</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/2026-01-09_monroe_d/2026-01-09_monroe_d.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How to Renovate the White House</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/whitehouse/whitehouse.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In 1934, the Public Works Administration undertook renovation of the West Wing of the White House, increasing its office space and moving the Oval Office to its present location. In <a href="http://www.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/_resources/images/msf/msf00734">his fifth “fireside chat” radio address,</a> of June 28, 1934, Roosevelt discussed the construction.</p>
<p>The president explained there would be modern plumbing, wiring, and air conditioning, as well as increased office space:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>But the structural lines of the old Executive Office Building will remain. The artistic lines of the White House buildings were the creation of master builders when our Republic was young. The simplicity and the strength of the structure remain in the face of every modern test.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So you needn’t worry: nobody was going to add “some strange new Gothic Tower, or a factory building or perhaps a replica of the Kremlin.” You see, the new construction was a metaphor for the New Deal:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>the new structure shall blend with the essential lines of the old. . . . All that we do seeks to fulfill the historic traditions of the American people. Other nations may sacrifice democracy for the transitory stimulation of old and discredited autocracies. We are restoring confidence and well-being under the rule of the people themselves.”</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./whitehouse.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="The renovated West Wing. Library of Congress. Click to enlarge."><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/whitehouse/whitehouse.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The renovated West Wing. Library of Congress. Click to enlarge."></a></p>
<figcaption>The renovated West Wing. Library of Congress. Click to enlarge.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It’s a fascinating speech in other ways—Roosevelt talks here about the “three R’s,” which are actually four, and about including the American people of the territories in his conception of the nation. But for some reason the White House renovation metaphor struck me.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>White House</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/whitehouse/whitehouse.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>This Man Mamdani</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/thisman/thisman.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>W. Kingsland Macy, chair of the New York Republican State Committee, had this to say about Governor Franklin D. Roosevelt:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“Look out you don’t make the mistake of liking Roosevelt. . . . I’ve seen people taken in by it.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“By what?” he was asked.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Macy groped for words, finally burst out with, “By a perfectly grand political personality, you fool!”<span class="citation" data-cites="looker1932"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Anyway, <a href="https://hellgatenyc.com/trump-and-mamdani-sitting-in-a-tree/">the mayor elect of New York met the president today.</a> The president <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/paleofuture.bsky.social/post/3m66ikvtt2s2c">remarked</a> of the mayor elect, “he’s a big fan of the New Deal I guess.”</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./mamdani.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Zohran Mamdani standing in front of the portrait of Franklin D. Roosevelt on his visit to the White House, November 21, 2025. Click to enlarge."><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/thisman/mamdani.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Zohran Mamdani standing in front of the portrait of Franklin D. Roosevelt on his visit to the White House, November 21, 2025. Click to enlarge."></a></p>
<figcaption>Zohran Mamdani standing in front of the portrait of Franklin D. Roosevelt on his visit to the White House, November 21, 2025. Click to enlarge.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Earle Looker, <em>This Man Roosevelt</em> (Brewer, Warren &amp; Putnam, 1932), 4.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Franklin D. Roosevelt</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/thisman/thisman.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Historiographical Hot Take</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/hot_take/hottake.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>It’s time for Historiographical Hot Take Halloween!<sup>1</sup> Let’s spin the wheel and see this year’s Terrifyingly Toasty Take:</p>
<p>There are two (2) historiographical traditions in US policy history that have had genuine serious consequences on US policy—and both of them for ill.&nbsp;<strong>To be clear:</strong> I distinguish here between history of policy that is consequential on policy, that is, which affected thinking, and that which merely reinforced existing prejudices; there is a lot of the latter.</p>
<p>The first is the Dunning School of Reconstruction, which held that rather than being an essential project of guaranteeing the civil rights of Black Americans, the period was one of unique corruption best left behind. By the 1930s this idea was commonplace among white Americans. When Claude Bowers published <em>The Tragic Era,</em> Franklin Roosevelt wrote him of his experience talking to his friends—“and they have not been confined to Georgians or southerners”—about the book, which “more than any other book in recent years, had a very definite influence on public thought.”<span class="citation" data-cites="leuchtenburg2005"><sup>2</sup></span> Even some of Roosevelt’s advisees who actively favored and promoted civil rights, like Harry Hopkins, echoed this view, referring to “the incredibly vicious period of Reconstruction.”<sup>3</sup> So although Roosevelt did some things to promote Black civil rights—creating the civil rights section in the Department of Justice—he might have done a good deal more were it not for the pervasive acceptance of the Dunning School among white policymakers.<sup>4</sup></p>
<p>The second historiographical school with significant policy influence is the literature denigrating the New Deal itself. Generally this kind of history sets at zero the value of efforts at relief and reform, and asks, how well did the New Deal promote economic recovery?</p>
<p>I have written about this view at some length in my <a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/myth-america-historians-take-on-the-biggest-legends-and-lies-about-our-past-julian-e-zelizer/0216b21fa0282c75"><em>Myth America</em> chapter</a> so I will say here only two brief things. First, even if we stipulate that the New Deal slowed recovery, it didn’t slow recovery enough to prevent quite a rapid recovery.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/field_nd/bizcycles_redone.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Chart showing the pace of recovery under the New Deal by the monthly index of industrial production. Click to enlarge."><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/field_nd/bizcycles_redone.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Chart showing the pace of recovery under the New Deal by the monthly index of industrial production. Click to enlarge."></a></p>
<figcaption>Chart showing the pace of recovery under the New Deal by the monthly index of industrial production. Click to enlarge.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>And second, saying effectively, “setting aside relief and reform, how well did the New Deal do at recovery” is in effect saying, “How well did the New Deal restore things to where they were”—an aim Roosevelt expressly and repeatedly rejected. The effect is to produce an entire body of literature which finds—perhaps not surprisingly!—that this popular and effective Democratic policy program didn’t do all that well at promoting a Republican agenda.</p>
<p>And yet, of course, that’s the view of the New Deal that was current among members of the Barack Obama administration, including the president himself; it was <a href="https://miscellanycentral.blogspot.com/2020/04/wasting-away-in-hooverville-chait.html">frequently referenced by conservatives during the debate over relief and reform during the 2008 financial crisis.</a></p>
<p>So: two historiographical traditions consequential for US policy—producing bad outcomes. Boo! That’s your Halloween Historiography Hot Take.<sup>5</sup></p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>That is too a thing.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>William E. Leuchtenburg, <em>The White House Looks South: Franklin D. Roosevelt, Harry S. Truman, Lyndon B. Johnson</em> (Louisiana State University Press, 2005), 35.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>“Harry Hopkins Plan to Help South,” <em>The Progress,</em> August 12, 1938.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>I would argue, though I haven’t room here, that when Roosevelt referred to the New Deal in the Virgin Islands of the United States as an “experiment,” he meant partly that it was an experiment in demonstrating that Black Americans could democratically run a prosperous and orderly society, given the chance—that is, an experiment in disproving the racist foundations of the “tragic era” thesis.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>Bonus corollary, for which there is also no room here! Glib bashing of the John F. Kennedy administration is a subset of <em>both</em> these traditions.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Historiography</category>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>Reconstruction</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/hot_take/hottake.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The great essayist, or as I like to call him, ‘Babe’</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/fdr_conservative/fdr_conservative.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Running for reelection in 1936, Franklin Roosevelt emphasized that the New Deal had averted revolution. He referred to the threat of communism, but I don’t believe he had ever really believed communism was in the offing; what he really feared in 1933 was dictatorship.</p>
<p>In the course of defending democracy, he argued, the New Deal had achieved the highest form of conservatism.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Never has a Nation made greater strides in the safeguarding of Democracy than we have made during the past three years. Wise and prudent men—intelligent conservatives—have long known that in a changing world worthy institutions can be conserved only by adjusting them to the changing time. In the words of the great essayist—‘The voice of great events is proclaiming to us—Reform if you would preserve.’ I am that kind of conservative because <a href="http://www.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/_resources/images/msf/msf00949">I am that kind of liberal.</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Anyway it seems like some people need to hear this sort of thing.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/fdr_conservative/fdr_conservative.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What this country needs</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/hoover_cigar/hoover_cigar.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Herbert Hoover’s problem was <em>not</em> that he was a technocrat who didn’t understand politics. He was a savvy political operator and a master of public relations who understood that it was to his advantage to <em>seem</em> like a technocrat who didn’t understand politics. So when you say he was a technocrat who didn’t understand politics, you are falling for a hustle, in the manner of someone who perceives Fast Eddie Felson isn’t striking the balls quite so smartly as you had heard.</p>
<p>James MacLafferty, one of Hoover’s aides and fixers, kept a diary and in the entry for April 14, 1932, he wrote about what he called a “morning after” scene in the Cabinet room of the White House.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Cigarette and cigar ends were crowding ash trays to their full capacity, empty cigarette packages were on the cabinet table and on the floor as were also wadded pieces of paper on which memorandums had been made. On the floor, by the President’s chair, were four paper bands that had once been around cigars the President had smoked. I recognized them at once and I picked them up determined that I would make them a part of this history.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>MacLafferty pasted a couple of Hoover’s cigar bands into his diary. (Because he kept the diary in duplicate, there are two in each copy. One’s in the Herbert Hoover Presidential Library in West Branch, Iowa, and the other is in the Hoover Institution Archives in Stanford, California.)</p>
<p>MacLafferty was commemorating one of Hoover’s successful lobbying efforts: the President had cajoled Congress into <a href="https://hoover.blogs.archives.gov/2020/07/29/the-economy-act-of-1932/">cutting federal salaries as a Depression-fighting measure.</a></p>
<p>Now you can say this episode shows that Hoover had terrible instincts, so far as macroeconomic policy goes, but I wouldn’t say it shows he didn’t know how to do politicking. He was able by dint of traditional jawboning and soft-selling to get his bad ideas through a Democratic House majority. He was a very good politician—which doesn’t by any stretch mean he had good policies.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Hoover</category>
  <category>Historiography</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/hoover_cigar/hoover_cigar.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Social Security at 90</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/ssa_100/ssa_100.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The Social Security Act is ninety years old this year. Here’s a chart showing expenditures in its first ten years, 1936–1935, from the <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015086702803&amp;seq=484&amp;q1=June">United States <em>Treasury Bulletin.</em></a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./ssa.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Chart showing Social Security Board expenditures by category, 1936–1945. Click to enlarge."><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/ssa_100/ssa.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Chart showing Social Security Board expenditures by category, 1936–1945. Click to enlarge."></a></p>
<figcaption>Chart showing Social Security Board expenditures by category, 1936–1945. Click to enlarge.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>Social Security</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/ssa_100/ssa_100.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Some interwar booknotes from recent TLS issues</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/tls_interwar/tls_interwar.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The TLS has recently run a number of essays on books that cover fascism in the interwar period, which thus fall within this blog’s <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/about.html">very sternly enforced remit.</a></p>
<p>Fintan O’Toole <a href="https://www.the-tls.com/politics-society/politics/burn-them-out-padraig-og-o-ruairc-year-of-the-rat-harry-shukman-book-review-fintan-otoole">writes</a> about Pádraig Óg Ó Ruairc’s history of fascism in Ireland, including “the IRA’s collaboration with the Nazis during the Second World War (on the time-honoured but idiotic grounds that ‘England’s difficulty is Ireland’s opportunity’).”</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./blue_blouses.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="A line of mostly women (Blue Blouses) with some men (Blueshirts) all giving a stiff-armed fascist salute. RTE. Click to enlarge."><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/tls_interwar/blue_blouses.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A line of mostly women (Blue Blouses) with some men (Blueshirts) all giving a stiff-armed fascist salute. RTE. Click to enlarge."></a></p>
<figcaption>A line of mostly women (Blue Blouses) with some men (Blueshirts) all giving a stiff-armed fascist salute. RTE. Click to enlarge.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The book also discusses the Irish Blueshirts, fascists who opposed the Irish government, which they believed “a crowd of Spaniards, Jews and Manxmen” O’Toole aptly notes, “I have yet to discover what the Irish fascists had against the Manx, but the point is obvious enough – it is the far right that generates the alien threat and not the other way around.”</p>
<p>Charles Darwent <a href="https://www.the-tls.com/arts/visual-arts/comrades-in-art-andy-friend-book-review-charles-darwent">reviews</a> Andy Friend’s study of the Artists International (swiftly renamed the Artists International Association, to avoid unwanted if accurate associations), a leftist anti-fascist organization. Though the book covers the period up to 1943, the essay doesn’t mention how the AIA dealt with the pact. I guess I have to read the book.</p>
<p>Catherine Taylor <a href="https://www.the-tls.com/literature-by-region/european-literature/crooked-cross-sally-carson-book-review-catherine-taylor">writes about</a> Sally Carson’s recently reprinted <em>Crooked Cross,</em> a 1934 novel about how the rise of the Nazi government affects a family in a small Bavarian mountain town. I picked up a copy earlier this year when I was in Britain and read it then. It’s so prescient, it’s difficult to believe it was written before the Hitler government had long been in power. Indeed Carson died before the Nazis’ horrors could be fully revealed: she passed away on June 21, 1941, as the Germans were just invading the Soviet Union.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Nazis</category>
  <category>Fascism</category>
  <category>TLS</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/tls_interwar/tls_interwar.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Plattism and the Gibraltar of Puerto Rico</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/monroe_d/monroe_d.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Cuba provided one of the first tests of Franklin Roosevelt’s initially ill defined “good neighbor” policy in 1933. Down to the autumn, Roosevelt’s Ambassador to Cuba Sumner Welles had been advising that the US might well need to send troops to Cuba under the terms of the Platt Amendment—the clause <a href="https://www.archives.gov/milestone-documents/platt-amendment">US officials inserted into the Cuban constitution of 1901</a> to permit US military intervention—to restore order after the fall of the Machado government.<span class="citation" data-cites="cronon1959-11"><sup>1</sup></span> But in November, Roosevelt said he wanted <a href="https://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/documents/presidential-statement-non-intervention-cuba">“a modification of the permanent treaty between the United States and Cuba,”</a> which as E. David Cronon writes, “could only mean that Washington contemplated relinquishing some of its rights under the Platt Amendment.”<span class="citation" data-cites="cronon1959-11"><sup>2</sup></span> In the following month, at the Pan American Conference in Montevideo, Secretary of State Cordell Hull agreed to a general nonintervention pledge and in 1934, the US signed a revised treaty with Cuba removing the Platt Amendment. The Platt Amendment, and what Latin Americans called “Plattism” more broadly, was gone; the good neighbor policy, so vague at the start, suddenly had a clear meaning: the era of interpreting the Monroe Doctrine as a general license for US military action in the Americas had ended.</p>
<p>As part of this revision of hemispheric policy, the Roosevelt administration also adjusted US relations to the territories it would not relinquish: Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, Alaska, and Hawaiʻi. Each of them would get its own version of the New Deal, including relief, public works, and programs for economic development.</p>
<p>The implementation of the New Deal in Puerto Rico was vexed, to say the least: for all that it achieved, much remained undone, and no party or faction in Puerto Rican politics lacked a critique of the Roosevelt administration’s policies. But many Puerto Rican politicians nevertheless preferred the New Deal to the treatment of their island “as a Caribbean Gibraltar”—that is, as a strategically located military outpost, whose inhabitants’ welfare was of little interest to Washington.<span class="citation" data-cites="ErnestGrueningdiary"><sup>3</sup></span></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./sf_pr.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="The fortess of San Felipe del Morro, Puerto Rico, 1943. US Navy History and Heritage Command. Click to enlarge."><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/monroe_d/sf_pr.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The fortess of San Felipe del Morro, Puerto Rico, 1943. US Navy History and Heritage Command. Click to enlarge."></a></p>
<figcaption>The fortess of San Felipe del Morro, Puerto Rico, 1943. US Navy History and Heritage Command. Click to enlarge.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Anyway it seems Marco Rubio has announced that <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cx23nzwjnwwo">Plattism is back.</a> And it has brought <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/sep/05/trump-fighter-planes-puerto-rico-venezuela-drug-cartel">Puerto Rico-as-Gibraltar</a> with it.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>E. David Cronon, <span>“Interpreting the New Good Neighbor Policy: The Cuban Crisis of 1933,”</span> <em>Hispanic American Historical Review</em> 39, no. 4 (1959): 538–67.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p><span>“Interpreting,”</span> 560.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Ernest Gruening, diary, Ernest Gruening Papers, Arctic and Polar Regions Collections, University of Alaska, Fairbanks, May 12, 1939.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Empire of the New Deal</category>
  <category>Puerto Rico</category>
  <category>Cuba</category>
  <category>Platt Amendment</category>
  <category>Monroe Doctrine</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/monroe_d/monroe_d.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Full of, buckets of</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/language/language.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As <a href="https://www.google.com/books/edition/Days_of_Fire/eXCJDQAAQBAJ?hl=en&amp;gbpv=1&amp;dq=john+nance+garner+%22bucket+of+warm+spit%22&amp;pg=PA60&amp;printsec=frontcover">recently as 2014,</a> serious writers of nonfiction still considered it appropriate to coyly bowdlerize John Nance Garner’s reported remark that the vice presidency was not worth a bucket of warm piss.<sup>1</sup> (Garner, Roosevelt’s vice president for his first two terms, was picked to assuage Texas and William Randolph Hearst in the nominating convention of 1932. Had Roosevelt been killed when he was shot at in February 1933, Garner would have become president. The New Deal would have looked a good deal different with the Texan who was (according to Hearst at least) an America Firster at the helm.)</p>
<p>I wonder what will become of the current vice president’s <a href="https://nymag.com/intelligencer/article/rfk-jr-to-testify-before-senate-committee-live-updates.html#reaction-time">similarly excretory remark</a> about the health and human services secretary’s senatorial critics. Will the likes of Peter Baker (cited above) feel they must clean it up for publication? Or have we entered an era of greater authenticity in rendering vice presidential speech?</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Which he may actually have said, and <a href="https://www.historynewsnetwork.org/article/not-worth-a-bucket-of-warm-spit">maybe even to Lyndon Johnson.</a>↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>John Nance Garner</category>
  <category>Language</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/language/language.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The American Family</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/duke/duke.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The FDR Library has this photo, captioned, “The Last of the Royalty of Hawaii! Salutes the President—26 July 1934,” <a href="https://fdr.blogs.archives.gov/hawaii1-2/">on its website.</a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./duke.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Outrigger canoes, one with a platform covered in what are maybe ki leaves bearing a man in a traditional feathered cape and headdress. Click to enlarge."><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/duke/duke.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Outrigger canoes, one with a platform covered in what are maybe ki leaves bearing a man in a traditional feathered cape and headdress. Click to enlarge."></a></p>
<figcaption>Outrigger canoes, one with a platform covered in what are maybe ki leaves bearing a man in a traditional feathered cape and headdress. Click to enlarge.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’m pretty sure—especially from the description in the US Navy Historical Command’s <a href="https://www.history.navy.mil/research/histories/ship-histories/danfs/h/houston-ii.html">history of the <em>USS Houston</em></a>—that the caption, written on the original photo, is intentionally whimsical, and the person wearing the feathered cape and headdress of Hawaiian aliʻi (familiar to viewers of <em>Chief of War</em>) is actually Duke Kahanamoku, Olympic swimming champion, longboard surfer, and then-serving sheriff of Honolulu. Duke Kahanamoku would also greet Ernest Gruening, as administrator of the Division of Territories and Island Possessions, in 1937—though apparently without the special garb.</p>
<p>Roosevelt’s 1934 trip was a combined Good Neighbor Policy / Territorial relations tour. He would first visit Haiti, from which <a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015049924361?urlappend=%3Bseq=409%3Bownerid=13510798884175400-409">he had ordered the accelerated end</a> of the US occupation (reversing not only US policy but his own earlier views, when he was Assistant Secretary of the Navy under Wilson); he would also go to Colombia.</p>
<p>Maybe more importantly, he visited Puerto Rico and the Virgin Islands, and afterward Hawaiʻi (the first sitting president to do so). He had just created the Division of Territories and Island Possessions to administer the New Deal in Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, Hawaiʻi, and Alaska—the territories whose people were US citizens—and on this trip he would explain that US citizens in the territories were as much a part of the “American family” as anyone else.<span class="citation" data-cites="frankind.Radio1934 PresidentStCroix1934 franklindRadio1934-07-28"><sup>1</sup></span></p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Franklin D. Roosevelt, <span>“Radio Address of the President, San Juan, Puerto Rico,”</span> July 7, 1934, <span>“July 7–21, 1934,”</span> Master Speech File, FDRL; <span>“The President at St. Croix, V.I. (Transcript),”</span> July 8, 1934, fldr <span>“Speech at San Juan, St. Croix, Panama—Caribbean Tour,”</span> Master Speech File, FDRL; Franklin D. Roosevelt, <span>“Radio Address at Honolulu, T.H.”</span> July 28, 1934.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Empire of the New Deal</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/duke/duke.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Unconditional Surrender</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/USgrant/usgrant.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>On January 24, 1943, Franklin Roosevelt and Winston Churchill held a joint press conference in Morocco, after some days discussing combined Allied strategy in the Casablanca meeting. (Stalin declined to attend.) They met there—they could meet there—because the US army had begun to assist the British army in clearing the Nazis from North Africa.</p>
<p>The most important immediate result of the conference was probably the plan for the Combined Bomber Offensive, but the more important in terms of strategy—and one that was very much, like the “United Nations,” like the prioritization of North Africa, Roosevelt’s personal preference—was the announcement of an Allied policy to demand unconditional surrender.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/USgrant/usgrant.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Press conference text of Roosevelt’s “unconditional surrender” remarks.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Roosevelt believed peace could only come with the utter defeat of the fascist powers. Not the destruction of their people, as he was quick to stipulate: but the destruction of their ability to make war. For him, the war was, necessarily, a war against fascism, not merely against a particular enemy, and fascism needed to be not only defeated but widely seen to have been defeated.</p>
<p>The demand for unconditional surrender was, and remains, debated in its wisdom. As Marc Gallicchio’s <em>Unconditional</em> establishes quite clearly, though, it was the New Dealers’ position; people on the political right—the pre-war isolationists, chiefly—were the ones who preferred an accommodation with the fascist powers.<span class="citation" data-cites="gallicchioUnconditionalJapaneseSurrender2020"><sup>1</sup></span></p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Marc Gallicchio, <em>Unconditional: The Japanese Surrender in World War II</em> (New York: Oxford University Press, 2020).↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Strategy</category>
  <category>Unconditional surrender</category>
  <category>Isolationists</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/USgrant/usgrant.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Beginning a Planned Program</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/concepts_plan/concepts.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>On April 7, 1932, while campaigning for the Democratic presidential nomination, Governor Franklin D. Roosevelt gave a radio speech laying out “a few essentials, a beginning, in fact, of a planned program” of economic recovery; what you might call the basic concepts of a plan.</p>
<p>First, he said, the plan needed to run “bottom to top and not from top to bottom”—in contrast to the recently created Reconstruction Finance Corporation, which put some billions of dollars “at the disposal of the big banks, the railroads and the corporations of the nation.”</p>
<p>He said that even a large emergency public works program “would be only a stopgap,” and said that really what the nation needed was a “cure.”</p>
<p>He then sketched three basic ideas: pushing up the prices of farm commodities “to restore purchasing power to the farming half of the country”; protection for homeowners from foreclosure by protecting the smaller banks and lending companies; lowering tariffs “on the basis of a reciprocal exchange” with other countries.</p>
<p>He said these would be “only a part of ten or a dozen vital factors.” But that “temporary relief from the top down” would not suffice; the nation needed “permanent relief from the bottom up.”<span class="citation" data-cites="rooseveltAlbany1932-04-08"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
<p>The <em>New York Times</em> editorial board were shocked at this “demagogic claptrap.” The Reconstruction Finance Corporation was “conceived by the best financial and business brains of this country.” As for the smaller banks, “the closing of these little local banks has been stayed and almost stopped.” It had not, of course, been stopped on what the governor would have called a “permanent” basis and would resume and accelerate later in the summer.<span class="citation" data-cites="BottomManApril"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
<p>Roosevelt enjoyed “the howl from the New York Times and other leading papers,”<span class="citation" data-cites="roosevelt1932-04-12"><sup>3</sup></span> as he wrote to Josephus Daniels, who had been his boss in the Navy Department. For his part, Daniels said, “you hit the bullseye”:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>We cannot win by letting the folks think the Republican party is 51% bad and we are only 49% bad. Some of our folks in Washington have thought if we acted not quite as subservient to the big interests as the Republicans we could win. You have shown that we must have a definite policy and that prosperity cannot be invoked by incantations and lending money to people who do not use it to start the wheels of industry.<span class="citation" data-cites="daniels1932-04-09"><sup>4</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/concepts_plan/daniels.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Franklin Roosevelt and Josephus Daniels in 1940. FDRL</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Roosevelt would come to emphasize a large program of public works more, later in the campaign; at one point he would say that his proposed reforestation program alone—the idea that became the Civilian Conservation Corps—might employ a million workers.<span class="citation" data-cites="rooseveltChicago1932-07-02"><sup>5</sup></span> And he would continue to campaign on the ideas of propping up farm prices, lowering tariffs, and protecting the smaller lenders and borrowers.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Franklin D. Roosevelt, <span>“Albany, NY - Radio Speech,”</span> April 8, 1932, Master Speech File, FDRL.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p><span>“The <span>‘Bottom’</span> Man,”</span> <em>New York Times</em>, April 9, 1932.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Franklin D. Roosevelt to Josephus Daniels, April 12, 1932, fldr <span>“Daniels, Josephus, 1932,”</span> box 19, series 1, FDR Governorship Papers, FDRL.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Josephus Daniels to Franklin D. Roosevelt, April 9, 1932, fldr <span>“Daniels, Josephus, 1932,”</span> box 19, series 1, FDR Governorship Papers, FDRL.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>@ Franklin D. Roosevelt, <span>“Chicago, IL - Acceptance Speech for Presidential Nomination,”</span> July 2, 1932, Master Speech File, FDRL.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/concepts_plan/concepts.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 09 Aug 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Rapid Involuntary Retirement</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/stewart/stewart_sacked.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Shortly after the chief of the Bureau of Labor Statistics declined to support a factually insupportable rosy jobs report, the president had him forcibly retired. In 1932, labor statistics commissioner Ethelbert Stewart was indignantly reclassified as dispensable.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I have a contract with the Government and it has been broken. Retired? Don’t put it that way. I’ve had a tin can tied to the end of my coat tail.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He had very recently been yelled at by Secretary of Labor William Doak in front of reporters for <a href="https://time.com/archive/6749502/the-cabinet-tin-can/">disputing a bright employment forecast.</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Hoover</category>
  <category>Depression</category>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/stewart/stewart_sacked.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Empire of Relief, 1933</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/relief_pc/relief_st_terr.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The Federal Emergency Relief Act of 1933, <a href="https://uscode.house.gov/statviewer.htm?volume=48&amp;page=55">48 Stat. 56,</a> proposed to relieve “hardship and suffering caused by unemployment” in the United States, which meant not only the States and the District of Columbia, but the Territories, as the title and the first section of the law stated. The people of the United States in the Territories were also entitled to relief from the Depression, in keeping with Roosevelt’s broadly inclusive message about the interdependence of all the sprawling republic’s people.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="./pc_relief.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Per capita relief in states and territories. Click to enlarge."><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/relief_pc/pc_relief.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Per capita relief in states and territories. Click to enlarge."></a></p>
<figcaption>Per capita relief in states and territories. Click to enlarge.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As you can see in the chart, relief went to the territories (shown in orange) on a basis commensurate with that of the states. While I’m skeptical of drawing any substantial inference based on the relative position of localities in the per-capita expenditures of the New Deal, the fact that the territories are in the same general run of per-capita spending as the states, and not outliers, suggests to me the early relief programs in the territories were comparable to those in the states. At least, for these four territories: these were the ones whose people were, by law, US citizens.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>New Deal</category>
  <category>Territories</category>
  <category>Empire of the New Deal</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/relief_pc/relief_st_terr.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
