<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>necessitous</title>
<link>https://erauchway.github.io/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://erauchway.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>A blog full of pedantry about the era of the Roosevelt administration, 1933--1945</description>
<generator>quarto-1.2.269</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>The German threat to the United States, 1940–1941: Atlantic geography</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/atl_dist/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>This is a follow-up to <a href="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/">the previous post</a> on Roosevelt’s assessment of the German threat in December 1940, pursuing the big question, “How much of a threat did Germany pose to the United States before Pearl Harbor?” This post looks at the question of Atlantic geography and German ambitions.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Likewise, the military scenarios Roosevelt sketched had little basis in reality. . . . He also stressed the narrowness of the Atlantic, even if not at the obviously most relevant place: “At one point between Africa and Brazil the distance is less than from Washington to Denver, Colorado—five hours for the latest type of bomber.”<span class="citation" data-cites="thompsonExaggerationAmericanVulnerability1992"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Let’s consider the Atlantic situation at the time of Roosevelt’s speech at the end of 1940.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/atl_dist/atlmap.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">The strategic situation in the Atlantic at the end of 1940.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>You can see the short distance from Brazil to West Africa; you can also see that French West Africa was at the time under the jurisdiction of the Vichy regime. France had fallen to Germany in June; Italy had entered the war and struck west across North Africa. Though the Italians had failed to take Egypt and were then suffering under British counter-attack, the Germans would shortly organize the Afrika Corps under Erwin Rommel and deploy it to the region.<span class="citation" data-cites="weinbergWorldArmsGlobal2005"><sup>2</sup></span></p>
<p>The status of West Africa was thus anything but evidently secure at the end of 1940, and indeed would only seem less secure quite soon.</p>
<p>Even as Roosevelt was warning that the Americas were vulnerable to German assault across the Atlantic, Hitler was planning for such an attack. In response to the Roosevelt administration’s September 1940 agreement to trade US destroyers for British bases in the western hemisphere, Hitler told Admiral Raeder that “England-USA must be thrown out of North-West Africa.” He opened negotiations with Spain to trade French Morocco for one of the Canary Islands, to establish a military outpost in the far West of the European hemisphere; he also began to consider whether the Azores could be used “to carry out aerial attacks from a land base against the United States.” German bomber technology would not then support it but nobody could then know of the limits on even the longest-range German bombers then under development, the Heinkel 177.<span class="citation" data-cites="herwigPreludeWeltblitzkriegGermany1971"><sup>3</sup></span></p>
<p>In the period between the fall of France and Pearl Harbor, Germany appeared to be at peak power, to Germans and to outside observers alike. Through 1941, aware of the impending Japanese attack, Hitler would continue to plan for a German war on the United States, in which an assault across the Atlantic would play a part.<span class="citation" data-cites="herwigPreludeWeltblitzkriegGermany1971"><sup>4</sup></span> There is thus no obvious reason to believe that Roosevelt was wrong, or alarmist, to consider the relative narrowness of the ocean or the possibility of a German aerial assault across its expanse.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>John A. Thompson, <span>“The Exaggeration of American Vulnerability: The Anatomy of a Tradition,”</span> <em>Diplomatic History</em> 16, no. 1 (January 1992): 30.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Gerhard L. Weinberg, <em>A World at Arms: A Global History of World War II</em>, 2nd ed. (Cambridge, Eng.: Cambridge University Press, 2005), 215.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Holger H Herwig, <span>“Prelude to Weltblitzkrieg: Germany’s Naval Policy Toward the United States of America, 1939-41,”</span> <em>Journal of Modern History</em> 43, no. 4 (December 1971): 657–58.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Herwig, <span>“Prelude to Weltblitzkrieg: Germany’s Naval Policy Toward the United States of America, 1939-41,”</span> 660–62.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>airpower</category>
  <category>Nazi strategy</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/atl_dist/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/atl_dist/atlmap.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="172" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The German threat to the United States, 1940–1941: bomber range</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Rauchway</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>How much of a threat did Germany pose to the United States before Pearl Harbor? That’s the big question; let’s look at a small part of it. Historians often say Roosevelt exaggerated the specific threats Nazi Germany posed; here we’ll look at one claim about the threat posed by German bombers.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Likewise, the military scenarios Roosevelt sketched had little basis in reality. . . . In December 1940 he made the remarkable claim that “even today we have planes that could fly from the British Isles to New England and back again without refueling.”<span class="citation" data-cites="thompsonExaggerationAmericanVulnerability1992"><sup>1</sup></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>It might seem to us remarkable that in December 1940, airplanes could fly the distance of an Atlantic round trip, but it was not remarkable to claim it. The crossing comes to about a 3,000-mile flight one way, so a return journey would total 6,000 miles. The Imperial Airways seaplane <em>Mercury</em> completed a flight of more than 6,000 miles non-stop from Dundee, Scotland to the Orange River in South Africa in October 1938.<span class="citation" data-cites="wraggBoatsAirIllustrated1984"><sup>2</sup></span> This feat was <a href="https://nyti.ms/3nTEwJC">reported in the newspapers, together with comparable records.</a> Not only was Roosevelt’s statement simply true, many of his listeners would have known it already.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/https:/www.nli.ie/digital/vtls000249986.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">The <em>Mercury</em> shown atop its launcher airplane, the flying boat <em>Maia.</em> National Library of Ireland.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Let’s look more closely at Roosevelt’s specific claim. This is what it says in the reading copy:</p>
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/range_claim.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>And here’s what Roosevelt actually said, according to transcription at the time:</p>
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/range_claim_as_said.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>First, this claim was refined in the process of writing the speech. Thanks to the FDR Presidential Library, we can <a href="http://www.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/_resources/images/msf/msf01403,">link to the relevant folder in the Master Speech File</a> and see that in earlier drafts, this paragraph read,</p>
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/earlier_claim.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The claim that planes could fly return from New York to London was probably supportable enough, given the flight of the <em>Mercury.</em> But at the seventh draft, Roosevelt changed it (notice the handwriting):</p>
<p><img src="https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/revised_claim.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Now not only is the distance more accurate and defensible—from “the British Isles” to “New England” is more accurately the route Imperial Airways was even then, despite the war, flying; but by changing its direction Roosevelt was, of course, emphasizing the potential threat should Britain fall to Germany.</p>
<p>Second, the claim about the outside range of existing aircraft is coupled here with a second claim. It’s clear with these two sentences that Roosevelt and his speechwriters are making a distinction between what the longest-distance airplanes could already do, and what modern bombers could soon do. This observation supports a generalization I want to make and will probably make again: Roosevelt and his speechwriters were quite careful.</p>
<p>The claim about how bombers were then developing, and what their capacity would be, was also correct. The B-29, though it was still on the drawing board, would have a <a href="https://www.boeing.com/history/products/b-29-superfortress.page">maximum range of 5,830 miles.</a> The experimental predecessor to the B-29, the XB-15, had already flown in 1937, and derived from a plan for a bomber with an effective range of 5,000 miles.<span class="citation" data-cites="knaackEncyclopediaAirForce1988"><sup>3</sup></span> Americans attentive to the news would have known about the XB-15; Major Caleb Haynes of the US Army air corps <a href="https://nyti.ms/3GlePbu">had flown one on an earthquake relief mission from Langley to Santiago, Chile, stopping in Panama and Peru, in February 1939.</a></p>
<p>Again, not only did Roosevelt make a carefully constructed and factually correct claim, he made one that many of his listeners would have understood to be readily supportable.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>John A. Thompson, <span>“The Exaggeration of American Vulnerability: The Anatomy of a Tradition,”</span> <em>Diplomatic History</em> 16, no. 1 (January 1992): 30.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>David W. Wragg, <em>Boats of the Air: An Illustrated History of Flying Boats, Seaplanes and Amphibians</em> (London: Robert Hale, 1984), 149.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Marcelle Size Knaack, <em>Encyclopedia of U.S. Air Force Aircraft and Missile Systems</em>, vol. 2: Post–World War II Bombers, 1945--1973 (Washington, D.C.: Office of Air Force History, 1988), 479.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>airpower</category>
  <guid>https://erauchway.github.io/posts/exagg_air/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.nli.ie/digital/vtls000249986.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
